<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>podcasts on Nicholas Johnson</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/podcasts/</link><description>Recent content in podcasts on Nicholas Johnson</description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/podcasts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>[Podcast] The Key to Trump's Appeal</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/podcast-the-key-to-trumps-appeal/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/podcast-the-key-to-trumps-appeal/</guid><description>&lt;p>There are many things I don&amp;rsquo;t agree with but I understand the motivation behind them. Religion is an example. I am not a religious person, but I can easily see the &lt;em>appeal&lt;/em> of religion. Religion offers consolation for death anxiety. People need to feel like their lives have meaning. Religion offers purpose. People want to believe there&amp;rsquo;s something more to life than everyday conscious experience because frankly, for lots of people, everyday experience just isn&amp;rsquo;t good enough. Everyday experience is dissatisfaction, disappointment and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dukkha">dukkha&lt;/a>. People need hope that &amp;ldquo;this&amp;rdquo; isn&amp;rsquo;t all there is. Religion gives people that hope. Even if you&amp;rsquo;re nonreligious, it&amp;rsquo;s not hard to see &lt;em>why&lt;/em> religion appeals to people.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Donald Trump&amp;rsquo;s appeal to half of Americans on the other hand is something that has puzzled me for years. It&amp;rsquo;s not that he doesn&amp;rsquo;t appeal to &lt;em>me&lt;/em>. It&amp;rsquo;s that I haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to comprehend how he appeals to &lt;em>anyone&lt;/em>, especially such a large fraction of American voters. I&amp;rsquo;m not alone in the confusion. &lt;a href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris&lt;/a> has also admitted to struggling to understand Trump&amp;rsquo;s appeal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve made many inquiries to Trump supporters about what they find appealing about him. I get a wide variety of answers but none of the answers given, even taken altogether, seem to account for his appeal. Conversations I&amp;rsquo;ve had with Trump supporters have made me disinclined to take their word for why they support him. Here&amp;rsquo;s an example of how one such conversation typically goes:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Myself&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;What makes Trump appeal to you?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Trump Supporter&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;He wants to build a wall.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Myself&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;If he didn&amp;rsquo;t would you still vote for him?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Trump Supporter&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;Yes.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Myself&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;So the wall isn&amp;rsquo;t the reason he appeals to you. At least it&amp;rsquo;s not the only reason. What else makes Trump appeal to you?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Trump Supporter&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;He tells the truth.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Myself&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;Here&amp;rsquo;s concrete examples of him contradicting himself.&amp;rdquo; (I show examples)&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Trump Supporter&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;So? All politicians lie.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Myself&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;So truthtelling isn&amp;rsquo;t the real reason he appeals to you either. What&amp;rsquo;s his strongest appeal?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Trump Supporter&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;He runs the country like a business. He&amp;rsquo;s a businessman, not a politician.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Myself&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;But he routinely blames everyone else for &lt;em>his&lt;/em> failures. In a business setting, doing that gets you fired. So he&amp;rsquo;s not running the country like a business.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Trump Supporter&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t care.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Myself&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;What if he kicked a baby?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Trump Supporter&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;He wouldn&amp;rsquo;t do that.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip;and so on and so forth. So you can see the reason I&amp;rsquo;m not inclined to take Trump supporters at their word on why Trump is appealing. Even when I remove their stated reasons for supporting him it makes zero difference. They still find him appealing. I don&amp;rsquo;t think they&amp;rsquo;re purposely misdirecting me or being deceptive. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty clear there&amp;rsquo;s something else going on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Studies in the field of psychology have shown that the color of the walls in a room, the temperature of a coffee offered to test subjects, and the wording of a question can all influence the outcome of an experiment. But the test subjects &lt;em>never&lt;/em> cite those things as significant factors in their decision making despite the statistics indicating they &lt;em>were&lt;/em> significant influences. The same sort of phenomenon is occurring when Trump supporters explain why Trump is appealing. The reasons they give are reasons they &lt;em>believe&lt;/em> they find him appealing, but not the &lt;em>actual&lt;/em> reasons. There are underlying psychological influences at play.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sam Harris has a fascinating take on Trump&amp;rsquo;s appeal which suggests what one of those underlying psychological influences might be. I&amp;rsquo;ll let him do &lt;a href="https://invidious.snopyta.org/watch?v=j3xBUNIkA_c&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1">the talking&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; width: 100%; height: 0; padding-bottom: 51%;">
&lt;iframe style="position: absolute; width: 100%; height: 100%; left: 0; top: 0;" src="https://invidious.snopyta.org/embed/j3xBUNIkA_c" frameborder="0" sandbox allowfullscreen="true" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>[Podcast] Why Trump is Unfit For Office</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/podcast-why-trump-is-unfit-for-office/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/podcast-why-trump-is-unfit-for-office/</guid><description>&lt;p>In his &lt;a href="https://samharris.org/podcast">Making Sense&lt;/a> podcast &lt;a href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris&lt;/a> talks about why Donald Trump is unfit for public office. For reference, these clips come from Making Sense episodes &lt;a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/the-end-of-faith-sessions-2/">#38&lt;/a> and #45. They were recorded before the 2016 presidential election but the past 4 years have only shown how right Harris was in his judgement of Trump.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen anyone else speak with the same clarity and completeness about Trump as Harris, so that&amp;rsquo;s why I picked these clips.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I had a very similar if not the same opinion of Trump 4 years ago. I immediately recognized him as a narcissistic unintelligent con man unfit for public office. If I had expressed my opinion at the time in writing it probably would have sounded much like these clips from the Making Sense podcast. Although much has happened since 2016, I still find these clips worth sharing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Links Below]&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://invidious.snopyta.org/watch?v=jLvabd32jDA&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1&amp;amp;start=544&amp;amp;end=2366">Episode #38&lt;/a> (31 min)&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://invidious.snopyta.org/watch?v=3yBGE80covk&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1">Episode #45&lt;/a> (15 min)&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>