<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>society on Nicholas Johnson</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/society/</link><description>Recent content in society on Nicholas Johnson</description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/society/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>[Video] Don't Talk to the Police</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-dont-talk-to-the-police/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-dont-talk-to-the-police/</guid><description>&lt;p>American law professor at Regent University School of Law and former criminal defense attorney James Duane explains why you should never talk to police without an attorney present, especially if you&amp;rsquo;re innocent.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=d-7o9xYp7eE&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1">[Video Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;There is no one in the United States over the age of 18 who cannot be indicted for some federal crime. That is not an exaggeration&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; retired LSU Law Professor John Baker.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>[Documentary] The Norden: Prison</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/documentary-the-norden-prison/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/documentary-the-norden-prison/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-norden">The Norden&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://thetvdb.com/series/the-norden">The Norden&lt;/a> is a documentary series made in 2014 first aired by Finland&amp;rsquo;s national public broadcasting company &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yle">YLE&lt;/a>. It presents the Nordic welfare model from an outsider&amp;rsquo;s perspective. The first episode looks at the Norwegian prison system. It captures so much of what&amp;rsquo;s wrong with &amp;ldquo;tough&amp;rdquo; prisons like those in America and most importantly it shows a better alternative. It promotes a prison model based on &lt;strong>rehabilitation, not revenge&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can watch it for free on archive.org:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Link below]&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://archive.org/details/TheNordenS01E01-Prison">https://archive.org/details/TheNordenS01E01-Prison&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="philosophy">Philosophy&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Prison reform is a subject I&amp;rsquo;m very passionate about. It is an urgent moral necessity to address the pointless suffering that goes on in tough prisons. What&amp;rsquo;s wrong with tough prisons? Simply put, &lt;strong>tough prisons are based on falsehoods, disregard for historical data, incoherent philosophy, and confused ideas about human psychology&lt;/strong>. The term &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Fractal_wrongness">fractal wrongness&lt;/a> is a perfect descriptor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In The Norden documentary, retired prison warden James Conway of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attica_Correctional_Facility">Attica State Prison&lt;/a> in New York travels to 4 Nordic prisons to see how they operate. Now I don&amp;rsquo;t want to pick on him in particular but I do want to use him as an example because he perfectly embodies everything wrong with American prisons. So for the rest of this post I&amp;rsquo;m going to take quotes from Mr. Conway in the documentary, explain what he gets wrong and why the US and other countries should immediately transition to Norwegian-style prisons.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="james-conway">James Conway&lt;/h2>
&lt;h4 id="bad-philosophy">Bad Philosophy&lt;/h4>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;New York State and the department of correctional services are not responsible for you being an inmate. And that means &lt;strong>you put yourself here&lt;/strong>. Don&amp;rsquo;t blame the department. Don&amp;rsquo;t blame the staff. Don&amp;rsquo;t blame the judge. Don&amp;rsquo;t blame society. It was your actions that put yourself here&amp;hellip;A lot of folks unfamiliar with prisons think that it&amp;rsquo;s the prison&amp;rsquo;s job to make sure this person comes out as a law-abiding citizen and those of us in prison realize that&amp;rsquo;s not the case.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; James Conway&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This quote is based on bad philosophy. Specifically it&amp;rsquo;s based on the believe that people possess libertarian free will. I&amp;rsquo;ve already talked &lt;em>at length&lt;/em> about how &lt;a href="../../free-will-is-incoherent-part-1">free will is incoherent&lt;/a>. For someone to have free will and be ultimately responsible for their actions would be &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Circular_reasoning">circular&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This bad philosophy regarding free will is related to confusion about &lt;a href="../../the-self">the self&lt;/a>. For example, in a sense there&amp;rsquo;s not &lt;em>really&lt;/em> such a thing as a chair. There are legs, a seat and armrests and when they are put together a certain way in space and used for sitting, we call the result a &amp;ldquo;chair&amp;rdquo;. But if you only stand on it to reach high places it might be a &amp;ldquo;step stool&amp;rdquo;. Point being &amp;ldquo;chair&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;stool&amp;rdquo; are mere &lt;em>nouns&lt;/em>. They aren&amp;rsquo;t the &lt;em>real&lt;/em> thing because reality isn&amp;rsquo;t words. The same is true of the nouns &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;self&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;ego&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;person&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To say of inmates &amp;ldquo;It was your actions that put yourself here.&amp;rdquo; and the thinking that it&amp;rsquo;s their responsibility to change themselves is to be confused about the self. Who is the &amp;ldquo;you&amp;rdquo; that put yourself there and who is the &amp;ldquo;you&amp;rdquo; that got put there? Who is the &amp;ldquo;you&amp;rdquo; that is doing the changing and who is the &amp;ldquo;you&amp;rdquo; that is being changed? It makes no sense. Of course people can change but there&amp;rsquo;s a contradiction in assigning ultimate blame to inmates.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t want to make this whole post a lecture about free will and self. For that you can read 2 sections of my other post on free will &lt;a href="../../free-will-is-incoherent-part-2#responsibility">responsibility&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="../../free-will-is-incoherent-part-2#justice">justice&lt;/a>. For those of you who think I&amp;rsquo;m just &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intellectualization">intellectualizing&lt;/a> to make excuses for inmates, I&amp;rsquo;m not. People &lt;em>should&lt;/em> admit their past mistakes. They &lt;em>should&lt;/em> make an effort to improve. They just shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be thought of as &lt;em>ultimately&lt;/em> responsible. Maybe there is a sense in which they are responsible, but not ultimately. Moving on.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="double-standards">Double Standards&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>James Conway explains to Jarmo Haavisto, Assistant Director of Hameenlinna Prison, how cells are searched in Attica:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>James Conway:&lt;/strong> &amp;ldquo;I would search the bed first. Totally top to bottom it comes off and then leave that in a pile and then go around the room systematically and put everything on the bed that I&amp;rsquo;m frisking, so that when she came back in all of her property would be right here on the bed.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Jarmo Haavisto:&lt;/strong> &amp;ldquo;So you don&amp;rsquo;t put them back where they were?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>James Conway:&lt;/strong> &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s her job.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Apparently the ultimate responsibility for your own actions doesn&amp;rsquo;t apply to guards. According to Conway it&amp;rsquo;s okay for guards to search a cell displacing all the inmate&amp;rsquo;s belongings but then it&amp;rsquo;s the inmate&amp;rsquo;s responsibility to put all the items back. It seems self-contradictory. As a proponent of ultimate responsibility for your own actions why wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it be the guard&amp;rsquo;s responsibility to put all the inmate&amp;rsquo;s items back given they&amp;rsquo;re the one who displaced them? Seems like a double standard.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="hyperfixation-on-punishment">Hyperfixation on Punishment&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>At Svartsjö minimum security prison there was an incident where an inmate didn&amp;rsquo;t consent to being on camera by putting a hood over his head.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Journalist:&lt;/strong> &amp;ldquo;James seems a bit absentminded. He just can&amp;rsquo;t get over the incident with the inmate during our arrival.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>James Conway:&lt;/strong> &amp;ldquo;Would this be a good time to talk about the guy with the white hood this morning?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Prison staff:&lt;/strong> &amp;ldquo;Yeah sure.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>James Conway:&lt;/strong> &amp;ldquo;We would never allow an individual to cover their face&amp;hellip;he would be called in and he would be given some kind of a sanction for that episode this morning. If he likes to walk every day, he wouldn&amp;rsquo;t walk for 5 days.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Journalist:&lt;/strong> &amp;ldquo;What if it&amp;rsquo;s right to be more therapeutic? Would you have happier prisoners if you tried it you know their way?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>James Conway:&lt;/strong> &amp;ldquo;No.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Journalist:&lt;/strong> &amp;ldquo;Why not? Why are you so sure?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>James Conway:&lt;/strong> &amp;ldquo;Our prisoners would try to manipulate the system. They misinterpret kindness for weakness.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m no prison warden but I&amp;rsquo;m sure the prisoner wasn&amp;rsquo;t just &lt;em>trying&lt;/em> to make an issue. The audio in the film presents a man who just didn&amp;rsquo;t want to be on camera and didn&amp;rsquo;t trust the film crew to blur out his face. He wasn&amp;rsquo;t acting violently. Yet Mr. Conway&amp;rsquo;s response to this was that the inmate shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be allowed to go on walks for 5 days. Conway later video calls a colleague who laughs about the idea of inflicting harsh deprivation on the inmate for an extremely minor dispute. This leads us straight into the next topic.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="lack-of-compassion">Lack of Compassion&lt;/h4>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;The inmate has given up his right to be in society by violating the law, by violent crime, by committing murder, by committing rape. That person shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be coddled, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be given a situation where we&amp;rsquo;re concerned about how they would feel if somebody was to walk by their cell and see them on the toilet. &lt;strong>Who cares how they feel.&lt;/strong>&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; James Conway&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Who cares how they feel? Someone made a mistake so it&amp;rsquo;s okay to disregard their feelings? It&amp;rsquo;s okay to treat them as subhuman because they broke the law? Isolating them from society is done because it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>necessary&lt;/em> to protect society. But not giving them privacy while using the toilet? If that&amp;rsquo;s not &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cruel_and_unusual_punishment">cruel and unusual punishment&lt;/a> then I don&amp;rsquo;t know what is.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Inmates are human beings.&lt;/strong> It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter what they&amp;rsquo;ve done. They deserve to be treated with dignity and respect just like everyone else. It&amp;rsquo;s that simple.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="cherry-picking">Cherry Picking&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>One of the reasons we have more people in jail in the United States than any other country is &lt;a href="https://www.salve.edu/sites/default/files/filesfield/documents/Incarceration_and_Recidivism.pdf">we throw people in jail for things that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t justify incarceration&lt;/a> elsewhere. US prisons are filled with &lt;em>nonviolent&lt;/em> drug offenders, victims of the war on drugs which &lt;a href="../../legalize-all-drugs">should never have been waged in the first place&lt;/a>. There wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be as many &lt;em>violent&lt;/em> drug offenders either if not for the war on drugs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mr. Conway doesn&amp;rsquo;t mention any of that. Like a true &lt;a href="https://www.shondaland.com/act/news-politics/a34729330/the-radical-individualism-raging-throughout-america/">radical individualist&lt;/a>, he shrugs off societal influences, such as poverty and poor education, which &lt;em>we know&lt;/em> based on evidence push people into a lives of crime. Instead he cherry picks the criminals we have the &lt;em>least&lt;/em> sympathy for. That is, murderers and rapists.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="disregard-for-evidence-dogmatism">Disregard for Evidence (Dogmatism)&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Mr. Conway claims we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t care about how inmates feel and they shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be coddled. But how does he know that? What logic did he use to take the step from &amp;ldquo;The inmate has given up his right to be in society by violating the law, by violent crime&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;That person shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be coddled, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be given a situation where we&amp;rsquo;re concerned about how they would feel&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;? How did he go about determining that?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>People with Mr. Conway&amp;rsquo;s attitude would probably say it&amp;rsquo;s self-evident. Isn&amp;rsquo;t it obvious they shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be treated well? After all they committed a crime. To that I would give the same general answer I give to all moral questions: &lt;a href="../../metaethics">What do you care about?&lt;/a>. I care about minimizing the number of people in prison. I care about people getting better even if that means we have to treat them better than their victims would approve of. I care about the &lt;em>evidence&lt;/em> and &lt;em>results&lt;/em> from the Nordic prison system as compared to other systems.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It really comes down to your values. If you value living in a society where where you don&amp;rsquo;t have millions of citizens going through the rotating door of prison, poverty and crime more than any other country, where you don&amp;rsquo;t punish and degrade people for the sake of it, where people getting better is &lt;em>more important&lt;/em> than revenge, then the best working example of that is the Nordic prison model and you should want to shift other countries closer towards it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Just ask Christer Karlsson, an ex-criminal that served 27 years in a Norwegian prison:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Journalist:&lt;/strong> &amp;ldquo;And is that a good thing that they are soft?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Christer Karlsson:&lt;/strong> &lt;em>thinking&lt;/em>&amp;hellip;&amp;ldquo;Yeah. I think it&amp;rsquo;s good, to behave to treat people with human thinking. I think it&amp;rsquo;s good. Because if you are treat them badly they be badly more badly by themself. Do some more awful crime when they come out.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>If you only value retribution, punishing people even though all the evidence shows it causes them to become more hardened criminals in the future making society &lt;em>less&lt;/em> safe with mass incarceration and recidivism paid for at the taxpayers' expense, inmates becoming more antisocial not getting the help they need just to fulfill a dogmatic fantasy based on nothing and in contradiction with our current understanding of &lt;a href="../../free-will-is-incoherent-part-1">the brain&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="../../the-self">the self&lt;/a>, modern psychology &lt;em>and&lt;/em> sociology, then punishment is the way to go.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="red-herring">Red Herring&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>When Mr. Conway saw a unit inside the maximum security Halden prison he said this:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;I would think the crime victims would be opposed to this type of living arrangement for the criminal.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; James Conway&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>To use the same words for victims that Mr. Conway used to describe inmates: &amp;ldquo;Who cares how they feel&amp;rdquo;. I thought it was the department of correctional services, not the department of victim&amp;rsquo;s feelings. &lt;strong>We should try to cultivate compassion for those who have wronged us, not be bent on getting revenge.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Darkness cannot drive out darkness; only light can do that. Hate cannot drive out hate; only love can do that.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; Martin Luther King Jr.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h4 id="budget">Budget&lt;/h4>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;When you have an unlimited budget their models fine and it&amp;rsquo;s all wine and roses&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; James Conway&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The budget is actually be a valid concern in the small scale. American prisons are overcrowded and underfunded. The Nordics have better social services than the US and universal healthcare which means they have better resources to handle mentally ill people before they end up in prison, prison is treated more as a &lt;em>last resort&lt;/em>, they don&amp;rsquo;t lock up so many people for victimless crimes and their people are better educated giving them better opportunities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is much to be said about differences in the cultural environment between the US and the Nordics. Certainly poverty, economic inequality and mental illness needs to be taken more seriously in the US if we want to have as much success as Nordic prisons. Some people use that as an excuse for why the US can&amp;rsquo;t have Nordic prisons. I strongly disagree. America is the richest country in the history of the world. We can absolutely fix our social problems, but there needs to be the political will to do so.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Besides even within the social constraints of the US both &lt;a href="https://eu.detroitnews.com/story/news/special-reports/2019/10/11/states-put-norway-style-prison-reforms-to-work/1682876001/">North Dakota and Oregon&lt;/a> have already started implementing the Nordic philosophy in their prisons and seen positive results and &lt;a href="https://amend.us/">Amend.us&lt;/a> is working to import the Nordic prison model into the US. &lt;strong>There&amp;rsquo;s no good excuse not to fix our broken prison system.&lt;/strong> &amp;ldquo;Change is hard&amp;rdquo; is not a good reason. Inmates are hurting and there is a moral imperative to remedy that.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="all-or-nothing-thinking">All or Nothing Thinking&lt;/h4>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;I think when the incident happens down the road they&amp;rsquo;re gonna have to make some changes. Everybodys not going to go along with their treatment plan that we&amp;rsquo;re doing this to help you. Somebodys gonna go against the grain. There&amp;rsquo;s always a case.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; James Conway&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Of course &amp;ldquo;everybody&amp;rdquo; won&amp;rsquo;t go along with the prison changes. But in Norway the recidivism rate is 20% while it&amp;rsquo;s 75% in the US. There&amp;rsquo;s several reasons that&amp;rsquo;s not a perfectly fair comparison. Some of them I mention above when I talked about &lt;a href="#budget">cultural differences&lt;/a>. But as North Dakota and Oregon have shown, it&amp;rsquo;s not &lt;em>all&lt;/em> the fault of the social environment in the US.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mr. Conway is basically saying that 4 out of 20 prisoners reoffending isn&amp;rsquo;t better than 15 out of 20 because it&amp;rsquo;s not 0. His implicit message seems to be &amp;ldquo;If the Nordic system fails even for one inmate then it&amp;rsquo;ll have to revert to being a tough US prison&amp;rdquo;. Only someone who is &lt;em>obsessed&lt;/em> with punishing every slight would fail to appreciate the relative success of the Nordic system. Clearly Mr. Conway &lt;em>is&lt;/em> obsessed with punishing every slight because he thought it was appropriate to force an inmate to stay inside and not walk &lt;em>for a week&lt;/em> just because he didn&amp;rsquo;t want to be on camera.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ll end this post with a quote from Russian novelist and philosopher &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fyodor_Dostoyevsky">Fyodor Dostoyevsky&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;A society should be judged not by how it treats its outstanding citizens but by how it treats its criminals.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; Dostoyevsky&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>[Article] You Should Be Using an Old Computer</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/article-you-should-be-using-an-old-computer/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/article-you-should-be-using-an-old-computer/</guid><description>&lt;p>I was going to write my own post about this subject until I discovered Luke Smith, a GNU/Linux technology Youtuber, already wrote an article about it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Link Below]&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://lukesmith.xyz/articles/oldcomputer">https://lukesmith.xyz/articles/oldcomputer&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>His reasons for recommending an old computer (specifically Thinkpads) are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>New computers are unnecessary for most people&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New computers are expensive&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New computers are slim and break easier&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New computers are impractical to repair yourself&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New computers contain a potential backdoor&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>You can read his article for more details on each point. I have a few comments to make. Smith cites processor-intensive video rendering as a reason you might need a newer computer. There&amp;rsquo;s also training/running neural networks, mining digital currency and some exhaustive search algorithms. But again the average person won&amp;rsquo;t be doing those things.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="intel-management-engine">Intel Management Engine&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Smith also claims the Intel Management Engine (Intel ME), the hidden processor in every modern Intel chip, is a government backdoor. This isn&amp;rsquo;t yet proven but the code in Intel ME is proprietary and secret, so it should be treated as a &lt;em>potential&lt;/em> intentional backdoor. &lt;em>At minimum&lt;/em> it&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2017/05/intels-management-engine-security-hazard-and-users-need-way-disable-it">security hazard&lt;/a>. Smith notes that AMD processors have basically the same problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The potential backdoor is really the crux of the ethical problem. Even if you don&amp;rsquo;t care about the price and you never drop your computer and you never replace any parts there&amp;rsquo;s still the potential backdoor. &lt;strong>Intel ME is always on even when your computer is turned off. It can&amp;rsquo;t be removed. No one knows what it actually does and Intel won&amp;rsquo;t tell us. We know it has full control over system memory and it can connect to the internet.&lt;/strong> If you&amp;rsquo;re at all tempted to use the &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Nothing_to_hide">nothing to hide argument&lt;/a> I only ask that you apply that same logic to Intel. If Intel has nothing to hide, why can&amp;rsquo;t they show us the source code for the ME? Why keep it secret? Why not allay all fears of a backdoor once and for all by releasing the source code? Unless of course it is in fact a backdoor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe you&amp;rsquo;re above nothing to hide though. You understand privacy is a human right. But, you reason, the Intel ME isn&amp;rsquo;t a big deal because an interested government could find out what they wanted to know some other way. Besides even without ME there&amp;rsquo;s other embedded software that, however unlikely it is, could possibly also have backdoors. All that&amp;rsquo;s beyond your &amp;ldquo;threat model&amp;rdquo; anyway. This goes back to a previous post I made. By using the &lt;em>least&lt;/em> potentially backdoored computer possible, you &lt;a href="../../raising-the-bar-on-privacy">raise the bar on privacy&lt;/a> (and freedom!). That&amp;rsquo;s a cause we &lt;em>all&lt;/em> need to be fighting for irrespective of threat models.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="retrofreedom">RetroFreedom&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The next most obvious question is &amp;ldquo;Where do I buy a computer without a backdoor?&amp;rdquo;. I recommend &lt;a href="https://retrofreedom.com/">RetroFreedom&lt;/a> (formerly Minifree). &lt;a href="https://vimuser.org/">Leah Rowe&lt;/a> operates the site. She maintains the &lt;a href="https://libreboot.org/">Libreboot&lt;/a> project, a free as in freedom alternative BIOS that ships with the old Thinkpads she sells. You can purchase products with cryptocurrency and several addons and upgrades are offered. I don&amp;rsquo;t mind the markup in price since I know it goes toward an important free software project. I can personally attest to the quality of the laptops from RetroFreedom. I&amp;rsquo;ve bought several laptops from there running exclusively free software and I&amp;rsquo;m very satisfied.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="free-software">Free Software&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I would never again use a nonfree laptop to do my everyday personal computing. I&amp;rsquo;ve given up videogames since all the popular titles are nonfree requiring me to run the Winblows operating system. &lt;a href="../../why-i-left-its">I quit my job&lt;/a> to avoid promoting proprietary software. &lt;a href="../../the-tipping-point-rejecting-windows-zoom-lockdown-browser-and-the-lockdown-monitor">I dropped out of college&lt;/a> so I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to use invasive proprietary malware. Too many people have told me I&amp;rsquo;m too extreme. I care too much about free software. Life is just too short to be so picky. But to them I would say this:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What does it say about society that the only way to get a non-backdoored laptop is to buy from a specific set of computers that are around 13 years old, replace the WiFi card, use special equipment to flash the BIOS with Libreboot/Coreboot and replace the operating system with GNU/Linux? Or pay someone else to do the procedure.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Further, what you have to realize is there is a war being waged on general-purpose computing. Every year manufacturers come up with new ways to make your computer harder to repair thereby increasing e-waste. Every year software companies make their ecosystems more locked down giving you less and less control over your own devices. To &lt;em>not&lt;/em> use an old Thinkpad is to be on the wrong side of this war. &lt;strong>I do not want to live in a world where I don&amp;rsquo;t have control over what I buy and cannot repair it&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Most people living in 1st world countries today are far too complacent&lt;/strong>. I can&amp;rsquo;t emphasize this enough. So when people ask me why I care so much, why I&amp;rsquo;ve given up &lt;em>so&lt;/em> much, I look at them in bewilderment. Why &lt;em>don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> they? If people like them don&amp;rsquo;t start caring soon we&amp;rsquo;re going to live in a dark world where computer users are totally subjugated. The 13 year old Thinkpads suffice for 95% of use cases for now but that won&amp;rsquo;t always be true. Proprietary threats are looming. Change needs to happen now, not 10 years from now. So use a free laptop even if it&amp;rsquo;s inconvenient because it&amp;rsquo;s not getting any easier.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="privacy">Privacy&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s also the whole privacy issue of having a potentially backdoored laptop. A college professor once told me privacy is dead. As if it were just a fact of the modern era and I hadn&amp;rsquo;t realized it yet. As long as there are people like me are around privacy is &lt;em>not&lt;/em> dead. I will &lt;em>never&lt;/em> accept a world without privacy. I will resist backdoors into my computer. I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you another thing. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t all the free software people that inspired this in me. It was the haters. Those who said it didn&amp;rsquo;t matter, privacy is dead, it&amp;rsquo;s unwinnable, I should just give up so my life is easier, etc. So please tell me any of those things. The naysayers keep me motivated. I don&amp;rsquo;t waste my time wondering whether free software is a fight we can win. It&amp;rsquo;s a fight we &lt;em>must&lt;/em> win. As long as there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>any&lt;/em> chance of winning, and even if it &lt;em>seems like&lt;/em> there&amp;rsquo;s not, we &lt;em>must&lt;/em> try.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You don&amp;rsquo;t need to quit your job and drop out to create change. All you have to do is create a rift. Get people to take notice. Force them to act by being unmoving in your commitment to free software. You won&amp;rsquo;t be popular. And you&amp;rsquo;ll be told you&amp;rsquo;re wrong &lt;em>a lot&lt;/em>. You might even start to doubt yourself. But let others say whatever they want and stay strong anyway. You have an advantage they don&amp;rsquo;t: the knowledge that you&amp;rsquo;re doing the right thing. You do have power. Those in power would like you to think that you don&amp;rsquo;t, but you do. Wield it wisely.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Documentary] Sicko</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/documentary-sicko/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/documentary-sicko/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-failing-american-healthcare-system">The Failing American Healthcare System&lt;/h2>
&lt;h4 id="public-healthcare">Public Healthcare&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The American healthcare system is the most &lt;em>needlessly complicated&lt;/em> healthcare system in the world. If you ask us Americans to explain how the system works, by and large we have no idea. I&amp;rsquo;m not even going to pretend I fully understand it. We have Medicare and Medicaid which both sound the same but Medicare is an insurance program available for seniors (people over 65) paid for by 2 trust fund accounts maintained by the Department of the Treasury and Medicaid a is welfare program for low-income people of any age paid for by federal income taxes. Then there&amp;rsquo;s the children&amp;rsquo;s health program for children whose families earn too much to qualify for Medicaid but aren&amp;rsquo;t covered by private insurance. For veterans we have a nationalized healthcare system operated by the Veteran&amp;rsquo;s Health Administration. But the public health programs don&amp;rsquo;t fully cover healthcare costs because we have copayments that have to be paid out of pocket.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="private-healthcare">Private Healthcare&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>If our government-run healthcare programs aren&amp;rsquo;t needlessly complicated enough with all the bureaucratic red tape then look no further than private health insurance. You can buy that directly or get it from an employer-sponsored group insurance plan. That&amp;rsquo;s right. The healthcare system is unnecessarily entangled with employment in America. If you change jobs you could lose your healthcare plan. Isn&amp;rsquo;t that just brilliant? Even if you directly buy healthcare not through an employer you still have to pay deductibles which can cost thousands. For example if your deductible is $3000 and you need an operation that costs $2500 your insurance won&amp;rsquo;t pay for any of it. The insurance doesn&amp;rsquo;t kick in until you pay over $3000. After the &amp;ldquo;policy period&amp;rdquo; it resets and you have to pay over $3000 again before your private insurance pays a nickel. All that only if you can get the private insurance to pay and of course they try to find any reason not to because it saves them money. And then after that you still might have coinsurance and copayments.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="no-healthcare">No Healthcare&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Also we can&amp;rsquo;t forget the &lt;em>27 million Americans that have no healthcare&lt;/em> of any kind public or private &lt;em>in the middle of a pandemic&lt;/em>. To make matters worse the US has &lt;em>no federally mandated paid sick leave and most states don&amp;rsquo;t have it either&lt;/em>. So if you&amp;rsquo;re poor you get to make the choice between putting food on the table and potentially infecting others with a deadly virus and risking your own health. Being uninsured makes you always financially vulnerable. You&amp;rsquo;re always 1 medical emergency away from bankcruptcy or drowning in medical expenses you&amp;rsquo;ll have to slave away to pay off for the next 2 decades. And that&amp;rsquo;s not even counting the underinsured.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sicko">Sicko&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Every other major country on earth guarantees healthcare access to every citizen. It&amp;rsquo;s morally incomprehensible that in the year 2021 the US &lt;em>still&lt;/em> hasn&amp;rsquo;t universalized healthcare.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the documentary film Sicko Michael Moore does a great job of comparing the US healthcare system with healthcare in the rest of the civilized world by showcasing the wastefulness and cruelty of the US system. You can find criticism of the film &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sicko#Response">on Wikipedia&lt;/a>. Keep in mind health insurance companies with billions of dollars ran a campaign to discredit the film. Given that, I take the criticisms with a grain of salt. The thrust of the film is accurate regardless: America has a broken healthcare system and fixing it is a moral imperative.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Link below]&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://michaelmoore.com/movies/sicko/">Documentary Link&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The only comment I would make is the film (2007) is slightly dated because past president Barack Obama has since passed a major piece of legislation called the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Affordable_Care_Act">Affordable Care Act&lt;/a> (Obamacare) which was designed to address the gaps in America&amp;rsquo;s healthcare system. It has improved healthcare access in the United States. If you want to catch up on American healthcare you should read about it after watching the film. President-elect Joe Biden promoted the public option which offers public healthcare to everyone as a federal program (Bidencare) forcing private insurers to compete with the government. Not as good as Bernie&amp;rsquo;s Medicare for All which would catch us up with the rest of the civilized world but Bidencare would at least be better than what we have now assuming he actually goes forward with it and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t end up being watered down.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Consumer Data Protection is a Distraction</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/consumer-data-protection-is-a-distraction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/consumer-data-protection-is-a-distraction/</guid><description>&lt;p>This post is a public service announcement.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-businesses-collect-data">Why Businesses Collect Data&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Businesses collect data from consumers for a variety of reasons. Data is collected to provide better customer service, provide a personalized customer experience, refine marketing strategy, derive other data, suggest new products, make predictions, recommendations and determine optimal business decisions. But as internationally renowned security technologist and author Bruce Schneier points out, &lt;a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2016/03/data_is_a_toxic.html">data is a toxic asset&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-its-dangerous">Why it&amp;rsquo;s Dangerous&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I recommend reading his &lt;a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2016/03/data_is_a_toxic.html">full blog post&lt;/a>. But from just a consumer perspective, giving companies your data is dangerous for several reasons according to Schneier:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Saving it is dangerous because many people want it. Of course companies want it; that’s why they collect it in the first place. But governments want it, too. In the United States, the National Security Agency and FBI use secret deals, coercion, threats and legal compulsion to get at the data. Foreign governments just come in and steal it. When a company with personal data goes bankrupt, it’s one of the assets that gets sold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Saving it is dangerous because it’s hard for companies to secure. For a lot of reasons, computer and network security is very difficult. Attackers have an inherent advantage over defenders, and a sufficiently skilled, funded and motivated attacker will always get in.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>That last part is important. &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;a sufficiently skilled, funded and motivated attacker will always get in&amp;rdquo;. The problem is you cannot trust corporations to keep your data safe. There aren&amp;rsquo;t exceptions to this that come to mind. Even if we suppose the data is encrypted on the server and only you control the encryption key, that&amp;rsquo;s not the case of a corporation being trustworthy to hold your data. &lt;em>They couldn&amp;rsquo;t leak it if they wanted to&lt;/em>. That&amp;rsquo;s what&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;em>trustless&lt;/em> design. The system is set up so you don&amp;rsquo;t have to trust whoever you&amp;rsquo;re doing business with. The best of systems are set up that way. It&amp;rsquo;s good for the consumer and it minimizes risk for the business.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The central reason you can&amp;rsquo;t trust businesses to keep your data safe is you don&amp;rsquo;t know how it&amp;rsquo;s being handled once it&amp;rsquo;s out of your hands. Even if the business &lt;em>claims&lt;/em> to have reasonable data protection, how can you possibly know that for sure? All it takes is 1 incompetent or malicious employee for your data to be leaked. All it takes is 1 out of date software package or 1 software vulnerability. All it takes is 1 government to steal from or coerce the business for the data. And if there&amp;rsquo;s ever a merger or acquisition then some other business acquires your data as an asset by default.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And let&amp;rsquo;s not forget data is combined with other data by data brokers to derive things about you that you didn&amp;rsquo;t explicitly share. You might think that 5 minute Youtube video of yourself doesn&amp;rsquo;t reveal too much but &lt;a href="https://github.com/daviddao/awful-ai">disturbing uses of AI&lt;/a> can be applied to it to derive information that you didn&amp;rsquo;t intend to include. And AI will only get better over time. You can&amp;rsquo;t predict the capabilities future AI will have to derive new information from your data. Even if it&amp;rsquo;s just &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metadata">metadata&lt;/a>, remember the former CIA and NSA director Michael Hayden&amp;rsquo;s statement concerning NSA bulk surveillance: &amp;ldquo;We kill people based on metadata&amp;rdquo;. &lt;strong>Put simply, consumer data protection is, has always been, and will be for the foreseeable future, a house of cards&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-to-protect-yourself">How to Protect Yourself&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The only foolproof way to protect yourself from data leaks is to &lt;strong>never give data to businesses in the first place&lt;/strong>. &amp;ldquo;Consumer data protection&amp;rdquo; is a distraction campaign. You see, the more businesses talk about &amp;ldquo;consumer data protection&amp;rdquo; the less &amp;ldquo;bandwidth&amp;rdquo; there is in public discourse to talk about &lt;em>outright refusal&lt;/em> to give up your data. Businesses can tout their data security practices all they want but it distracts from the truth which is you can just choose not to give your data to companies. We now live in a culture of &amp;ldquo;I agree&amp;rdquo; to the point that people forget they can say no to these things. Don&amp;rsquo;t consent. Don&amp;rsquo;t click &amp;ldquo;I agree&amp;rdquo; unless you&amp;rsquo;ve actually read the terms. Don&amp;rsquo;t provide identifying information without serious consideration.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And for those of you who say &amp;ldquo;I have to give &lt;a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Goolag">Goolag&lt;/a> my data! Rearranging my life to protect my data would be too hard! I need a Goolag account for my job or university or whatever the case may be.&amp;rdquo; I leave you with a quote from the Roman stoic Seneca:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s not that we don&amp;rsquo;t dare do things because they are difficult; rather, they are difficult because we don&amp;rsquo;t dare&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; Seneca&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>[Video] Fixing Social Media for Good</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-fixing-social-media-for-good/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-fixing-social-media-for-good/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recent events have brought the issue of social media censorship to the forefront:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Facebook bans Trump&amp;rsquo;s account&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Instagram bans Trump&amp;rsquo;s account&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Snapchat bans Trump&amp;rsquo;s account&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Twitch bans Trump&amp;rsquo;s account&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Twitter bans Trump&amp;rsquo;s account&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Amazon removes Parler from its cloud hosting service&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Apple removes Parler from the App Store&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Google removes Parler from the Play Store&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Discord bans TheDonald.win server&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Reddit bans r/DonaldTrump&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pinterest censors Trump related topics&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Shopify removes Trump&amp;rsquo;s merchandise from its platform&lt;/li>
&lt;li>TikTok removes Trump&amp;rsquo;s speeches&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Youtube removes videos claiming widespread voter fraud&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>No informed person is disputing that these are private companies and they have the &lt;em>legal&lt;/em> right to do whatever they want (within the bounds of the law) with their platforms. The 1st amendment &lt;em>doesn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> apply here. Nonetheless it&amp;rsquo;s very alarming that voices coming from the political left are sympathetic to &lt;em>widespread&lt;/em> censorship just because it&amp;rsquo;s Trump. If it were someone within their own ranks being censored they would no doubt be making the same argument I&amp;rsquo;m going to make about the danger of censorship. Voices coming from the political right actually have a saner viewpoint on the censorship problem in the sense that they can actually recognize censorship as a social problem which Trump&amp;rsquo;s situation has only highlighted.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As amusing as it is seeing adult Eric Cartman&amp;rsquo;s megaphone taken away, having a handful of big tech companies control who gets a voice and who doesn&amp;rsquo;t is extremely dangerous. Once a platform is large enough it is a &lt;em>de facto&lt;/em> public forum in the sense that it can be used by anyone to freely spread their ideas. Censorship on it in practice can be as damaging to freedom of speech as censoring a &lt;em>de jure&lt;/em> public forum. The good coming from this censorship is people are waking up to the fact that big tech companies can and do censor whoever they want when it suits them. &lt;a href="https://signal.org">Signal Messenger&lt;/a> has even seen a &lt;a href="https://nitter.snopyta.org/elonmusk/status/1347165127036977153">huge increase&lt;/a> in downloads since the censorship imposed after the capitol riots. Uncensorable platforms are needed. &lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/channel/UC2eYFnH61tmytImy1mTYvhA">Luke Smith&lt;/a> proposes &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federation_%28information_technology%29">federated&lt;/a> platforms as a permanent fix for the censorship issue:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://videos.lukesmith.xyz/videos/watch/0c256439-ec59-4e41-bd40-0ebeca751543?autoplay=1">[Video Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="federation-versus-peer-to-peer">Federation Versus Peer to Peer&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>While federation is better than centralization, in practice federation tends toward centralization anyway. Email is federated but a few big providers (Gmail, Yahoo, Outlook, iCloud, Protonmail) control the market. Worse yet, all the big providers sell user data. But it&amp;rsquo;s not just email. On the federated communication platform &lt;a href="https://www.matrix.org">Matrix&lt;/a> users are still heavily concentrated on the default matrix.org homeserver. So it&amp;rsquo;s not true that federation alone fixes social media for good. A &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peer-to-peer">peer-to-peer&lt;/a> social media platform could fix social media for good. But I&amp;rsquo;d still rather see everyone on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fediverse#Communication_protocols_used_in_the_fediverse">The Fediverse&lt;/a> instead of the centralized social media platforms used today.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Fable] The Fable of the Dragon Tyrant</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/fable-the-fable-of-the-dragon-tyrant/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/fable-the-fable-of-the-dragon-tyrant/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="death">Death&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Death has been an ever-present fact of life since the dawn of humanity. Large parts of human culture have been shaped by the knowledge that one day we will cease to be. In the past our species has had no choice but to come to terms with it. But technological progress is now accelerating so rapidly that a cure for aging is &lt;em>conceivable&lt;/em>. Some even argue it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>inevitable&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The idea of curing death makes many of us uncomfortable, at least initially. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to imagine a society where aging and death no longer pose a threat. So much about our culture would have to change. And yet &lt;a href="https://nickbostrom.com">Nick Bostrom&lt;/a> argues not only is curing death preferable, it&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;em>moral imperative&lt;/em> we should strive to achieve as soon as possible. He goes so far as to argue that &amp;ldquo;deathist&amp;rdquo; ideologies, ideologies that endorse or encourage complacency with death as a part of life, while useful in the past for consoling people, today pose &amp;ldquo;fatal barriers to urgently needed action&amp;rdquo;. Anyone with an interest in philosophy should read his fable about death.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Link below]&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://nickbostrom.com/fable/dragon.html">The Fable of the Dragon-Tyrant&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="morality">Morality&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My own view of death is informed by &lt;a href="../../metaethics">how I see morality&lt;/a>. To give you a taste of it, I&amp;rsquo;ll start by saying this: &lt;strong>Your intrinsic values can never be wrong&lt;/strong>. Another way of expressing that is: &lt;em>If&lt;/em> there are things you value above everything else, those things &lt;em>cannot&lt;/em> be mistaken. They may be highly abstract. They may not fit into words. They may even change over time. But it&amp;rsquo;s incoherent to say you are wrong about your &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intrinsic_value_%28ethics%29">intrinsic values&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In reference to what can your intrinsic values be said to be wrong? For example if you value happiness above all else and you think money (the things you can do with it) makes you happy, money is an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Instrumental_value">instrumental value&lt;/a>. You value money &lt;em>because&lt;/em> you value happiness. If you hit the lottery tomorrow and you&amp;rsquo;re no happier than before, then perhaps you&amp;rsquo;re wrong to value money. But you &lt;em>can&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> be wrong to value happiness. If it ever seems that you are that just means happiness isn&amp;rsquo;t an &lt;em>intrinsic&lt;/em> value for you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So if someone asked me &amp;ldquo;Should we cure death?&amp;rdquo;, my response would be &amp;ldquo;Well what do you value?&amp;rdquo;. If your eventual demise is one of your &lt;em>intrinsic&lt;/em> values then I can&amp;rsquo;t really tell you you&amp;rsquo;re wrong to value death. I can, but if you&amp;rsquo;re a rational agent, it won&amp;rsquo;t convince you. What Bostrom is saying in his fable to &amp;ldquo;deathists&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;You only &lt;em>think&lt;/em> you value death. You don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em>really&lt;/em> want to die&amp;rdquo;. The purpose of his fable is to correct your intuition about death. It&amp;rsquo;s the same as my earlier example where you value money because you value happiness, but then hitting the lottery corrects the intuition that money brings happiness. Bostrom is saying, like money, you only think you value death, but you don&amp;rsquo;t really.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That sums up my perspective on his fable. After reading his fable and his argument I&amp;rsquo;m more sympathetic than before to the cause of curing death. Perhaps he&amp;rsquo;s right that most of us won&amp;rsquo;t realize how much we actually value a cure for aging and death until we&amp;rsquo;re already on the brink of a cure. And by that point we will wish we prioritized a cure much sooner.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Podcast] The Key to Trump's Appeal</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/podcast-the-key-to-trumps-appeal/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/podcast-the-key-to-trumps-appeal/</guid><description>&lt;p>There are many things I don&amp;rsquo;t agree with but I understand the motivation behind them. Religion is an example. I am not a religious person, but I can easily see the &lt;em>appeal&lt;/em> of religion. Religion offers consolation for death anxiety. People need to feel like their lives have meaning. Religion offers purpose. People want to believe there&amp;rsquo;s something more to life than everyday conscious experience because frankly, for lots of people, everyday experience just isn&amp;rsquo;t good enough. Everyday experience is dissatisfaction, disappointment and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dukkha">dukkha&lt;/a>. People need hope that &amp;ldquo;this&amp;rdquo; isn&amp;rsquo;t all there is. Religion gives people that hope. Even if you&amp;rsquo;re nonreligious, it&amp;rsquo;s not hard to see &lt;em>why&lt;/em> religion appeals to people.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Donald Trump&amp;rsquo;s appeal to half of Americans on the other hand is something that has puzzled me for years. It&amp;rsquo;s not that he doesn&amp;rsquo;t appeal to &lt;em>me&lt;/em>. It&amp;rsquo;s that I haven&amp;rsquo;t been able to comprehend how he appeals to &lt;em>anyone&lt;/em>, especially such a large fraction of American voters. I&amp;rsquo;m not alone in the confusion. &lt;a href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris&lt;/a> has also admitted to struggling to understand Trump&amp;rsquo;s appeal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve made many inquiries to Trump supporters about what they find appealing about him. I get a wide variety of answers but none of the answers given, even taken altogether, seem to account for his appeal. Conversations I&amp;rsquo;ve had with Trump supporters have made me disinclined to take their word for why they support him. Here&amp;rsquo;s an example of how one such conversation typically goes:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Myself&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;What makes Trump appeal to you?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Trump Supporter&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;He wants to build a wall.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Myself&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;If he didn&amp;rsquo;t would you still vote for him?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Trump Supporter&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;Yes.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Myself&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;So the wall isn&amp;rsquo;t the reason he appeals to you. At least it&amp;rsquo;s not the only reason. What else makes Trump appeal to you?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Trump Supporter&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;He tells the truth.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Myself&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;Here&amp;rsquo;s concrete examples of him contradicting himself.&amp;rdquo; (I show examples)&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Trump Supporter&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;So? All politicians lie.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Myself&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;So truthtelling isn&amp;rsquo;t the real reason he appeals to you either. What&amp;rsquo;s his strongest appeal?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Trump Supporter&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;He runs the country like a business. He&amp;rsquo;s a businessman, not a politician.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Myself&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;But he routinely blames everyone else for &lt;em>his&lt;/em> failures. In a business setting, doing that gets you fired. So he&amp;rsquo;s not running the country like a business.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Trump Supporter&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t care.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Myself&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;What if he kicked a baby?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br>
&lt;strong>Trump Supporter&lt;/strong>: &amp;ldquo;He wouldn&amp;rsquo;t do that.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip;and so on and so forth. So you can see the reason I&amp;rsquo;m not inclined to take Trump supporters at their word on why Trump is appealing. Even when I remove their stated reasons for supporting him it makes zero difference. They still find him appealing. I don&amp;rsquo;t think they&amp;rsquo;re purposely misdirecting me or being deceptive. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty clear there&amp;rsquo;s something else going on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Studies in the field of psychology have shown that the color of the walls in a room, the temperature of a coffee offered to test subjects, and the wording of a question can all influence the outcome of an experiment. But the test subjects &lt;em>never&lt;/em> cite those things as significant factors in their decision making despite the statistics indicating they &lt;em>were&lt;/em> significant influences. The same sort of phenomenon is occurring when Trump supporters explain why Trump is appealing. The reasons they give are reasons they &lt;em>believe&lt;/em> they find him appealing, but not the &lt;em>actual&lt;/em> reasons. There are underlying psychological influences at play.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sam Harris has a fascinating take on Trump&amp;rsquo;s appeal which suggests what one of those underlying psychological influences might be. I&amp;rsquo;ll let him do the talking:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=j3xBUNIkA_c&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1">[Video Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Podcast] Why Trump is Unfit For Office</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/podcast-why-trump-is-unfit-for-office/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/podcast-why-trump-is-unfit-for-office/</guid><description>&lt;p>In his &lt;a href="https://samharris.org/podcast">Making Sense&lt;/a> podcast &lt;a href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris&lt;/a> talks about why Donald Trump is unfit for public office. For reference, these clips come from Making Sense episodes &lt;a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/the-end-of-faith-sessions-2/">#38&lt;/a> and #45. They were recorded before the 2016 presidential election but the past 4 years have only shown how right Harris was in his judgement of Trump.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen anyone else speak with the same clarity and completeness about Trump as Harris, so that&amp;rsquo;s why I picked these clips.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I had a very similar if not the same opinion of Trump 4 years ago. I immediately recognized him as a narcissistic unintelligent con man unfit for public office. If I had expressed my opinion at the time in writing it probably would have sounded much like these clips from the Making Sense podcast. Although much has happened since 2016, I still find these clips worth sharing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Links Below]&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=jLvabd32jDA&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1&amp;amp;start=544&amp;amp;end=2366">Episode #38&lt;/a> (31 min)&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=3yBGE80covk&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1">Episode #45&lt;/a> (15 min)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Book] Lying</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/book-lying/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/book-lying/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://samharris.org/">Sam Harris&lt;/a> talks about how lying is more harmful than most people imagine. From white lies, Santa Claus and the Tooth Fairy to more serious political deception, Sam makes the case for not lying in any situation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://samharris.org/books/lying/">[Book Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Video] Vengeance</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-vengeance/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-vengeance/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/channel/UCLhtZqdkjshgq8TqwIjMdCQ">Darkmatter2525&lt;/a> explains punitive prison systems&lt;/p>
&lt;p>(5min 43sec - 11min 43sec).&lt;br>
Click &lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=LX2VeWumRQ8&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1&amp;amp;start=343&amp;amp;end=703">this link&lt;/a> to watch only the relevant part of the video.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Privacy Paradox</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/the-privacy-paradox/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/the-privacy-paradox/</guid><description>&lt;p>After the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_surveillance_disclosures_(2013%E2%80%93present)">Snowden revelations of 2013&lt;/a>, we learned that the NSA&amp;rsquo;s global internet surveillance program &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XKeyscore">XKeyscore&lt;/a> was flagging people that read&amp;hellip;&lt;a href="https://www.linuxjournal.com/content/nsa-linux-journal-extremist-forum-and-its-readers-get-flagged-extra-surveillance">Linux Magazine&lt;/a>. That&amp;rsquo;s right. The NSA would place you on a special high-priority surveillance list for taking an interest in one of the only operating systems that isn&amp;rsquo;t known to have a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backdoor_(computing)">backdoor&lt;/a>. But it didn&amp;rsquo;t end there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can see in the &lt;a href="https://daserste.ndr.de/panorama/xkeyscorerules100.txt">XKeyscore rules&lt;/a> people that searched for &lt;a href="https://www.torproject.org/">Tor&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://tails.boum.org/">Tails OS&lt;/a> software were being targeted. These are programs written for the express purpose of anonymity and avoiding the watchful eye of Big Brother.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There seems to be a common theme here. Big Brother programs automatically targeted people that took steps to avoid surveillance. It&amp;rsquo;s a fair bet to make that people that use privacy tools are still targeted more than those who don&amp;rsquo;t. There&amp;rsquo;s one very good reason to suspect this: Big Brother doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to take a special interest in those that don&amp;rsquo;t avoid mass surveillance because mass surveillance is sufficient to build a full portrait of their lives anyway. It&amp;rsquo;s logical that Big Brother would only need to pay special attention to those avoiding mass surveillance since their privacy is harder to violate.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-paradox">The Paradox&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Thus we end up with a paradox: The more you avoid mass surveillance, the more &lt;em>interesting&lt;/em> you become to Big Brother. This increases the likelihood that you&amp;rsquo;ll end up on one of their &amp;ldquo;extra surveillance&amp;rdquo; lists and that more &lt;em>targeted&lt;/em> methods will be used on you. The less you avoid mass surveillance, the less &lt;em>interesting&lt;/em> you become to Big Brother. All else being equal, this decreases the likelihood that you&amp;rsquo;ll get special attention. Blending in with the surveilled masses might give you more anonymity and privacy, in practice. In other words, allowing yourself to be mass surveilled might act as a kind of protection against targeted surveillance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you &lt;a href="../../avoiding-consumer-surveillance">pay for everything in cash&lt;/a> where cash payments are uncommon, if you &lt;a href="../../using-email">use internet services&lt;/a> registered outside of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_Eyes">Five Eyes&lt;/a>, if you use Tor and VPNs for accessing the internet, if you use &lt;a href="../../use-free-software">free as in freedom&lt;/a> software and encrypted communication apps, if you &lt;a href="../../atom-and-rss">avoid social media&lt;/a>, if you drive a &lt;a href="../../avoiding-automobile-surveillance">privacy-friendly vehicle&lt;/a> when you can afford a newer car, you&amp;rsquo;re going to attract attention to yourself. One of these things on its own isn&amp;rsquo;t a red flag, but combined together, there&amp;rsquo;s really only one thing you can be doing: avoiding mass surveillance. One doesn&amp;rsquo;t avoid mass surveillance in today&amp;rsquo;s world by accident unless you&amp;rsquo;re amish or living in a poor country.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Knowing this, what ought you to do about it? Should you try to blend in or should you avoid mass surveillance and just not care how many watchlists you end up on?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-to-do-about-it">What to Do About It&lt;/h2>
&lt;h4 id="short-answer">Short Answer&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Trying to blend in with the surveilled populace is like giving a thief your money so they can&amp;rsquo;t steal it. If you really want to fight mass surveillance, you should take as many steps to avoid mass surveillance as you&amp;rsquo;re willing to take and don&amp;rsquo;t worry about being targeted. If enough people do this, it will &lt;a href="../../raising-the-bar-on-privacy">raise the bar on privacy&lt;/a> so that &lt;em>only&lt;/em> the more expensive targeted surveillance tools will work. Then everyone will collectively have more privacy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="long-answer">Long Answer&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>If you or someone you know is doing something illegal and you don&amp;rsquo;t want Big Brother&amp;rsquo;s attention, especially since Big Brother has been known to do nasty things such as assisting with &lt;a href="../../shining-light-on-the-dark-side-of-law-enforcement">evidence laundering&lt;/a>, you might think it&amp;rsquo;s a good idea to avoid mass surveillance &lt;em>only&lt;/em> when conducting illegal activities to avoid drawing too much attention to yourself. This strategy is ill-advised for at least two reasons:&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="reason-1">Reason #1&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Allowing yourself to be mass surveilled on purpose some of the time is the reason the bar on privacy remains low. If all you care about is not drawing attention to yourself and your illegal activities, then fine. But if you care about wider society, then you should raise the bar on privacy by avoiding mass surveillance at &lt;em>all&lt;/em> times, not only when engaging in illegal activities.&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="reason-2">Reason #2&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>You contribute to the stereotype that a desire for privacy indicates nefarious activity. It empowers the surveillance state in the current iteration of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crypto_Wars">crypto wars&lt;/a> because Big Brother can say that anonymity networks are mainly used for criminal purposes. If it can be shown for instance that 90% of Tor traffic is used for legal activities then it&amp;rsquo;s (theoretically) much harder for the government to make the case that it should be censored because of drug dealers, money launderers, pedophiles and terrorists.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The only long-term winning strategy for all society is to avoid mass surveillance as much as possible with the hope that others will follow suit. This is true whether you&amp;rsquo;re a law-abiding citizen or a criminal mastermind.
To drive this point home, I&amp;rsquo;ll end with a quote by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Snowden">Edward Snowden&lt;/a> from his interview with John Oliver on Last Week Tonight:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You shouldn’t change your behavior because a government agency somewhere is doing the wrong thing. If we sacrifice our values because we’re afraid, we don’t care about those values very much.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This quote was taken from the context of taking dick pics, but it can be equally applied here: Don&amp;rsquo;t accept mass surveillance as reality just because the government might target you for it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Avoiding Automobile Surveillance</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/avoiding-automobile-surveillance/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/avoiding-automobile-surveillance/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="internetification-of-everything">Internetification of Everything&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Over the past few decades, there has been increasing &amp;ldquo;internetification&amp;rdquo; of everything. The &lt;a href="https://stallman.org/articles/internet-of-stings.pdf">Internet of Stings&lt;/a> has infected refrigerators, watches, televisions, and even light bulbs. As it turns out, shoehorning internet connected computer chips with &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/proprietary/">proprietary&lt;/a> code into everything increases their attack surface making society more vulnerable to &lt;a href="https://www.wired.com/2015/07/jeep-hack-chrysler-recalls-1-4m-vehicles-bug-fix/">hacking groups&lt;/a>, foreign governments and Big Brother.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Automobiles are no exception. They&amp;rsquo;ve also seen increased internetification. My own personal opinion is cars don&amp;rsquo;t need wireless enabled computer chips, period. And I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/is-apples-carplay-a-kille_b_4905981">not the&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://blog.1871.com/blogs/howard-a-tullman/tullman-why-smart-cars-are-stupid-2">only person&lt;/a> to think connected cars seem like a bad idea.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For this post, I want to focus on avoiding mass surveillance of automobiles. None of the recommendations in this post apply to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On-board_diagnostics#Vehicle_telematics">work vehicles&lt;/a> or car rentals since you don&amp;rsquo;t own those. This guide is &lt;em>only&lt;/em> for your own personal vehicle.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="dont-buy-a-connected-car">Don&amp;rsquo;t Buy a Connected Car&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My first piece of advice is don&amp;rsquo;t buy a connected car. By connected car I mean a car with wireless capability other than radio. Buy an old car instead. Old cars predate the connected features of new cars. Ideally buy a car that doesn&amp;rsquo;t support wifi, bluetooth or cellular connections. If it has a touchscreen it&amp;rsquo;s probably too new. If you need navigation, you can buy a cheap car phone mount and use your phone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you already own a connected car, the best advice I can give is to trade it in for an old car. Until then read the owner&amp;rsquo;s manual and find out how to deactivate as many of the connected features as you can. &lt;strong>Never pair your phone with your car&lt;/strong>. Disable bluetooth and cellular connections on the car if possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="eliminate-remote-diagnostics">Eliminate Remote Diagnostics&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Unfortunately even some old vehicles have remote diagnostics systems that collect and transmit vehicle sensor data wirelessly to the dealership, insurer, manufacturer or &lt;a href="https://stallman.org/glossary.html#thug">thugs&lt;/a>. I&amp;rsquo;ll cover these by category starting with the dealership.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="dealership-tracking">Dealership Tracking&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Automotive dealerships have &lt;a href="https://www.spireon.com/gps-auto-tracking/">GPS tracking devices&lt;/a> attached to cars primarily to prevent theft. When you buy a car, assume it has one and make the dealership agree to remove it as part of the terms of purchase before you buy the vehicle. Once you&amp;rsquo;ve bought the car from the dealership, there&amp;rsquo;s no reason they need GPS tracking on it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The exception of course is if you bought the car on a loan. Then either the dealership or the lender may require the GPS tracker on the car until it&amp;rsquo;s fully paid for. In that case you can remove the GPS tracker yourself or have it removed after the car is fully paid for.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="insurer-tracking">Insurer Tracking&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Car insurers promote &lt;a href="https://www.carzing.com/blog/car-insurance/car-insurance-tracking-devices/">remote telematics devices&lt;/a> to policyholders in exchange for lower rates. They use the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On-board_diagnostics">OBD interface&lt;/a> in your vehicle to send real-time data to the insurer. Empowering Big Brother in exchange for cheaper rates isn&amp;rsquo;t worth it. Don&amp;rsquo;t let your insurer install tracking devices in your car. If your insurer requires them, find a new insurer.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="manufacturer-tracking">Manufacturer Tracking&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>General Motors includes &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OnStar#Use_as_surveillance_device">OnStar&lt;/a> in its vehicles. OnStar is a telematics device capable of not only remotely surveilling GM vehicles, but also listening to live audio inside the car and remotely shutting the car down. Even if you don&amp;rsquo;t have a subscription, OnStar can still track your GM vehicle. In fact they tracked vehicles that weren&amp;rsquo;t even subscribed to OnStar services until they &lt;a href="https://www.consumerreports.org/cro/news/2011/09/gm-reverses-decision-on-onstar-privacy-policy/index.htm">reversed the decision&lt;/a> due to public outcry from privacy advocates. Luckily there are plenty of guides online for &lt;a href="https://www.wikihow.com/Deactivate-OnStar">how to remove OnStar&lt;/a> so they can&amp;rsquo;t possibly track you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>SiriusXM also collects telematics. Unlike OnStar, there&amp;rsquo;s no way to remove it I&amp;rsquo;m aware of. You can cancel your subscription, but SiriusXM can still collect telematics. The only solution is &lt;strong>don&amp;rsquo;t buy a vehicle that has telematics providers you can&amp;rsquo;t remove&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="thug-tracking">Thug Tracking&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Big Brother can also demand telematics information about your car from any of the above categories. This isn&amp;rsquo;t theoretical. It happened with &lt;a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3295672-SiriusXM-Satellite-Radio-Tech-Turned-Into.html">SiriusXM&lt;/a>. Thugs have used &lt;a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3295668-Coleman-Motion-to-Suppress-Denied.html">OnStar&lt;/a> several times to remotely shutdown car engines. &lt;a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3295666-ATX-Technologies-vs-US-Monitoring-of-in-Car.html">ATX technologies&lt;/a> was forced to provide thugs with a live audio feed from inside a car.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thugs are still allowed to put trackers on cars with a warrant. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to tell you how to spot covert thug GPS trackers. That&amp;rsquo;s avoiding &lt;em>targeted&lt;/em> surveillance which is out of the scope of this post. This post is only about avoiding &lt;em>mass&lt;/em> automobile surveillance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="safeguarding-onboard-diagnostics">Safeguarding Onboard Diagnostics&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Onboard diagnostics systems (OBD) in vehicles were introduced in the 1980s. The USA, EU and other countries have mandated &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On-board_diagnostics#OBD-II">OBD-II&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On-board_diagnostics#EOBD">EOBD&lt;/a> protocols for all vehicles sold.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="emissions-testing">Emissions Testing&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>If you have a gasoline engine and you&amp;rsquo;re in the United States, OBD data is pulled from your vehicle when you get mandatory emissions testing unless you get standard tailpipe emissions testing done. To find out if you can get only standard tailpipe emissions testing, you&amp;rsquo;ll have to call and ask local emissions testing sites and check state regulations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the emissions testing site uses proprietary OBD scanning software, then it&amp;rsquo;s possible that your data gets collected and sold to insurance companies by the OBD software vendor. If the testing site uses a handheld OBD scanner, it&amp;rsquo;s still &lt;em>possible&lt;/em> that the data is eventually pulled off and sold if the handheld scanner connects to vendor software on an internet connected computer. The OBD-II interface has &lt;code>Mode $09&lt;/code> which retrieves uniquely identifiable information like the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vehicle_identification_number">VIN number&lt;/a>. So if the OBD data does get sold, the data brokers know exactly whose vehicle it belongs to.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve never heard of OBD data being involved in a data breach before. I don&amp;rsquo;t have any information about what software is used by emissions testing sites. I&amp;rsquo;m just speculating. The only reason I have for thinking OBD data collection does happen at emissions testing sites through software vendors is because it can and it&amp;rsquo;s profitable. Even if my speculation is true, you still have to get emissions testing done. I only mention emissions testing data collection for completeness and awareness, not because you can do anything besides political activism to prevent it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="auto-repair-shops">Auto Repair Shops&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>When you take your car to a repair shop, one of the first things they&amp;rsquo;re going to do is check the OBD-II interface for error codes. It&amp;rsquo;s the same issue as before with emissions testing. The uniquely identifiable OBD data is exposed to potentially proprietary programs used by the car repair shop.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The difference is you don&amp;rsquo;t have much choice in emissions testing. When it comes to auto repair, you have some choice. There are &lt;a href="https://github.com/fenugrec/freediag">free software diagnostic tools for OBD-II&lt;/a> that don&amp;rsquo;t collect and sell your data. You&amp;rsquo;ll need &lt;a href="http://freediag.sourceforge.net/Supported-Interfaces.html#supported">an adapter&lt;/a> supported by your vehicle to use them. It&amp;rsquo;s up to you to make sure the adapter will work before you buy it. If you want to repair your vehicle yourself, then that&amp;rsquo;s the end of it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you need the auto repair shop to repair your vehicle, you can relay the results retrieved from your free software tools to them while requesting they don&amp;rsquo;t use their own proprietary OBD scanning tools.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="networked-electric-vehicle-charging-stations">Networked Electric Vehicle Charging Stations&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This section only applies to fully electric and hybrid cars. I&amp;rsquo;ve already made a post about &lt;a href="../../networked-ev-charging-stations">networked EV charging stations&lt;/a>. Just so this post is self-contained, I&amp;rsquo;ll reiterate:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>There are two types of EV charging stations: networked and non-networked. The networked ones require you to sign up on the web with your real name, credit card information, address, and car make and model. You have to agree to the terms of service and privacy policy. After signing up, you receive a swipe card in the mail. Because you have to swipe an ID card to use networked charging stations, the network (Chargepoint) knows who you are, where you charged your car, when, and for how long. Non-networked charging stations don’t require you to use an ID card, so they can’t collect any personalized data on you.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Don&amp;rsquo;t use the networked charging stations. Use the non-networked ones or just use your own charging cable instead.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="automatic-license-plate-readers">Automatic License Plate Readers&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Automatic license plate readers or &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/pages/automated-license-plate-readers-alpr">ALPRs&lt;/a> are cameras that capture all license plate numbers that pass by. There isn&amp;rsquo;t anything you can do about these besides political activism against them. Purposely obscuring your plates from these cameras might be illegal or cause you to get tickets. Even if there&amp;rsquo;s nothing you can do, I still think it&amp;rsquo;s important to be aware of ALPRs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="consumer-surveillance">Consumer Surveillance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It may be possible to infer where you drive based on consumer surveillance alone. As a final piece of advice to further improve your vehicle&amp;rsquo;s location privacy, follow the tips in my post on &lt;a href="../../avoiding-consumer-surveillance">avoiding consumer surveillance&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="political-action">Political Action&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When I make posts on how to avoid surveillance, what I&amp;rsquo;m trying to do is build resistance to tools of mass surveillance. At the end of the day there needs to be both technological and political changes to protect drivers' data. I offer temporary workarounds for avoiding surveillance until the dangerous trend of increased surveillance reverses itself. Society needs to start being &lt;em>proactive&lt;/em> rather than &lt;em>reactive&lt;/em> to corporate and government surveillance. I don&amp;rsquo;t know when or how or if the trend of increased surveillance will be reversed, but I&amp;rsquo;ll continue writing about ways to resist surveillance until I no longer need to.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At some point resisting mass surveillance becomes impractical. I understand my advice isn&amp;rsquo;t always easy to follow. Choosing privacy can get expensive and time-consuming. And it&amp;rsquo;s already hard enough to get people to use anti-surveillance tools that are &lt;em>easy&lt;/em> to use, let alone follow a guide like this that requires lots of effort. Part of the function of these posts is to show the ridiculous lengths one must go for privacy in today&amp;rsquo;s world. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to follow all the steps in this guide. My practical advice is just do what you can. Remember, if all you do is cancel your insurance tracking, that&amp;rsquo;s a win for privacy and a blow to Big Brother.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you have any more details or suggestions that I missed send me an &lt;a href="mailto:nicholasjohnson@posteo.org">email&lt;/a>. If you want to help support my site &lt;a href="../../about#donate">send a donation&lt;/a>. I hope you found this post valuable.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Nonlinearity of Intelligence</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/the-nonlinearity-of-intelligence/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/the-nonlinearity-of-intelligence/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="intelligence-is-nonlinear">Intelligence is Nonlinear&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The word &amp;ldquo;sports&amp;rdquo; covers a wide variety of activities. It&amp;rsquo;s so broad that its usefulness as a word is limited. What can you say about sports? &amp;ldquo;I like/dislike sports. I play/don&amp;rsquo;t play sports&amp;rdquo;. If you talk about &amp;ldquo;popular sports&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;contact sports&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;mind sports&amp;rdquo;, there&amp;rsquo;s so much more you can say than if you&amp;rsquo;re just talking about &amp;ldquo;sports&amp;rdquo;. And if you pick a particular sport like basketball then you open up a world of things you can talk about. You can talk about rules of the game, the history, famous players/teams, statistics, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the same way, you can talk about &amp;ldquo;intelligence&amp;rdquo; in a general sense. But when you&amp;rsquo;re just talking about intelligence, it&amp;rsquo;s hard to say much. So instead, to make it more interesting, you can differentiate between mathematical intelligence, social intelligence, historical intelligence, philosophical intelligence, etc. For many people, talking about intelligence in a linear or binary way doesn&amp;rsquo;t accurately describe their situation. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at a few case studies.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="case-study-1-kim-peek">Case Study #1: Kim Peek&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kim_Peek">Laurence Kim Peek&lt;/a> is the perfect example of the abstraction of general intelligence breaking down. Kim is the inspiration for the movie &lt;a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0095953/">Rain Man&lt;/a>. According to Kim&amp;rsquo;s father Francis, Kim learned to read before age 2. Kim read the left page with his left eye and right page with his right eye. He was able to read 1 page per second remembering nearly all of it years later. He was a human encyclopedia.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Kim also didn&amp;rsquo;t learn to walk until age 4. He was diagnosed severely mentally retarded and had an 87 IQ. He couldn&amp;rsquo;t button up his shirt and had great difficulty socializing and performing basic motor tasks.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In one way, Kim was superhuman. In another way, he was cognitively limited. He possessed a skill to a degree that no one else on the planet was known to have it. He also had limitations associated with being severely mentally retarded. He&amp;rsquo;s no genius, but he&amp;rsquo;s no idiot. He&amp;rsquo;s not really of average intelligence either. And so here you can see the word &amp;ldquo;intelligence&amp;rdquo; breaks down. It fails to meaningfully describe Kim. For describing Kim Peek, it&amp;rsquo;s more useful to talk about &amp;ldquo;types of intelligence&amp;rdquo;, not just generalized intelligence.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="case-study-2-daniel-tammet">Case Study #2: Daniel Tammet&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>For the second case study, we&amp;rsquo;ll look at &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Tammet">Daniel Tammet&lt;/a>. He is an &lt;a href="https://autism.wikia.org/wiki/Autistic_savant">autistic savant&lt;/a>. Daniel set the European record reciting pi to 22,514 digits without a single mistake. He knows 10 languages and is able to become conversational in new languages in only a week. Daniel is able to perform huge math calculations in his head.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Perhaps the most unique thing about Daniel is that he has subjective insight on how he can perform huge mental calculations. In our first case study with Kim Peek, Kim could not articulate how he remembered everything. Most savants can&amp;rsquo;t articulate their abilities, but Daniel can. He wrote an entire book on it called &lt;a href="http://www.danieltammet.net/numbers.php">Thinking in Numbers&lt;/a>. In his own words:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;When I multiply numbers together, I see two shapes. The image starts to change and evolve, and a third shape emerges. That&amp;rsquo;s the answer. It&amp;rsquo;s mental imagery. It&amp;rsquo;s like maths without having to think.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>The fact that he is able to introspect on his own savant capabilities is extraordinarily unique and worthy of recognition in and of itself. He also happens to share my feeling about intelligence:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;I know from my own experience that there is much more to &amp;lsquo;intelligence&amp;rsquo; than an IQ number. In fact, I hesitate to believe that any system could really reflect the complexity and uniqueness of one person&amp;rsquo;s mind, or meaningfully describe the nature of his or her potential.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Daniel has no apparent mental disability. But he can&amp;rsquo;t leave his house without counting the number of clothes he&amp;rsquo;s wearing. He can&amp;rsquo;t drive. He has a hard time at the beach because of all the grains of sand. Socializing takes much more mental effort for him than it does for a neurotypical person because he has autism. He&amp;rsquo;s so high-functioning that his mental disability is more or less invisible, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t make his struggles any less real.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="autism-and-savantism">Autism and Savantism&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Less than 1% of the neurotypical population has &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savant_syndrome">savant syndrome&lt;/a> while &lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2677584/">that number is up to 1 in 10 with autistic individuals&lt;/a>. About half of savants are autistic while the other half have some other developmental disorder.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Autism doesn&amp;rsquo;t guarantee you to be intelligent at something else as a trade-off for social intelligence. Instead, you have up to a 10% chance of being a savant if you&amp;rsquo;re autistic. It also isn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily true that autism &lt;em>causes&lt;/em> savantism. But it&amp;rsquo;s clear from the statistics that autism &lt;em>goes with&lt;/em> savantism more than neurotypicality goes with savantism. Savantism seem to defy the conventional notion that intelligence is linear and genius is on one end with mental deficiency on the other. It seems to suggest that treating intelligence as linear is an oversimplification.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="social-consequences">Social Consequences&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Although savantism is a fun research topic, there are interesting social consequences of the nonlinearity of intelligence that have nothing to do with savantism or extraordinary mental ability. I&amp;rsquo;ll give an example of nonlinear intelligence in the context of free software.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="free-software">Free Software&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>There were so many conversations I had about &lt;a href="https://www.fsf.org/philosophy">free software&lt;/a> during my time as a student. For those who don&amp;rsquo;t know, free software is software that respects the user&amp;rsquo;s freedom. It&amp;rsquo;s more ethical than &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/proprietary/">non-free software&lt;/a>. What I came to realize through those conversations is that technological prowess and moral wisdom are two completely separate types of intelligence. But before I explain how I came to realize that, I need to make an important distinction.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are those that understand something has negative effects yet do it anyway and those that don&amp;rsquo;t understand the negative effects. There are more people that believe in being vegan than there are actual vegans.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Likewise, there are more software engineers that believe in free software than software engineers that write free software. When I distinguish the type of intelligence that is &amp;ldquo;technological prowess&amp;rdquo; from the type of intelligence that is &amp;ldquo;moral wisdom&amp;rdquo;, I&amp;rsquo;m talking about skilled software engineers who don&amp;rsquo;t understand the harm of writing non-free software, especially if it has been explained to them before how harmful non-free software is.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There were some students and professors I talked to that fell into that category of possessing the technical prowess to write software while lacking the moral wisdom to see the importance of free software. They were great at programming, but did not understand the social consequences of writing proprietary software even after I explained it and provided several online resources. This is not to say they&amp;rsquo;ll never understand. But the point is I understood why free software is important and how non-free software harms society after watching &lt;a href="https://www.fsf.org/blogs/rms/20140407-geneva-tedx-talk-free-software-free-society">Richard Stallman&amp;rsquo;s TED talk&lt;/a> once.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I don&amp;rsquo;t share that to gloat, but to make a point. It was hard for me to understand how others, especially professors far more knowledgeable about software than I am, could not grasp the social necessity of free software instantly upon hearing a single TED talk even with their sincere effort. Eventually, I realized that technological prowess and moral wisdom are two completely separate types of intelligence.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="moral-wisdom-as-intelligence">Moral Wisdom as Intelligence&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Some readers are going to disagree with me referring to &amp;ldquo;moral wisdom&amp;rdquo; as a form of intelligence. After all, being a good person and being intelligent are two separate things, right?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I agree, but &lt;em>knowing&lt;/em> which actions and policies lead to a better society isn&amp;rsquo;t a matter of being a good person. It&amp;rsquo;s a matter of possessing a certain kind of intelligence that I call &amp;ldquo;moral wisdom&amp;rdquo;. History has shown the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crusades">worst&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/September_11_attacks">atrocities&lt;/a> were carried out by people who thought they were doing good, usually perverted by religious ideology. When I talk about moral wisdom, I don&amp;rsquo;t mean doing the right thing. I mean having the intelligence to know what the right thing is.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When people have technological prowess without moral wisdom, we end up with the negative social consequence of having people with the kind of intelligence necessary to engineer proprietary software but lacking the kind of intelligence necessary to see that they&amp;rsquo;re perpetuating an unjust social system. It would be better if those people had never learned to program in the first place because their work will only subjugate people. Most software engineers don&amp;rsquo;t become software engineers to think about ethics, so there are lots of software engineers out there engineering evil software.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In fact, software engineering isn&amp;rsquo;t even the only endeavor that negatively affects society when people have asymmetric intelligence.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="socially-harmful-combinations-of-intelligence">Socially Harmful Combinations of Intelligence&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Some more examples are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>There are people with the kind of intelligence necessary to fly planes into towers but lacking the kind of intelligence necessary to see past the religious myth motivating them.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There are people with the kind of intelligence necessary to build mass surveillance systems but lacking the kind of intelligence necessary to see how incompatible those systems are with a free society.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There are people with the kind of intelligence necessary to acquire political power but lacking the kind of intelligence necessary to make good, evidence-based policy decisions.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There are people with the kind of intelligence necessary to see the importance of voting but lacking the kind of intelligence necessary to pick a good candidate.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not saying all these instances are &lt;em>only&lt;/em> related to intelligence. Sometimes people &lt;em>are&lt;/em> just malicious or selfish. But lacking certain kinds of intelligence often has far more to do with apparently malicious behavior than is admitted. It&amp;rsquo;s easier to just say someone is a &amp;ldquo;bad person&amp;rdquo; than to consider their intelligence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For instance, the terrorists that flew the planes into the twin towers on 9/11 were &lt;a href="https://thereligionofpeace.com/">motivated by an ideology&lt;/a>. If they had the kind of intelligence related to critical thinking and questioning core beliefs, they may have found out that Islam is a fairytale and never would have carried out the attacks. Believing baseless ideologies is related to critical thinking which is a kind of intelligence. You can blame it on society for never explicitly applying critical thinking to religion, but critical thinking skills are still a form of intelligence regardless of the reason a person may lack them.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="intelligence-is-dynamic">Intelligence is Dynamic&lt;/h2>
&lt;h4 id="learning">Learning&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The last point I want to make is that intelligence is it&amp;rsquo;s highly dynamic. The human brain is capable of creating new patterns of behavior and thought to become better at a skill. Once you learn to ride a bike, that muscle memory stays with you. You don&amp;rsquo;t forget how to do it unless you have some traumatic brain injury.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are other types of intelligence that do require constant reinforcement. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnus_Carlsen">Magnus Carlsen&lt;/a>, the world&amp;rsquo;s greatest chess player, could not quit chess for 5 years, come back, and still expect to be the world&amp;rsquo;s greatest chess player. Brain research suggests that the brain is a &amp;ldquo;use it or lose it&amp;rdquo; organ. You either keep learning or you lose your ability to learn. The brain needs to learn new things to remain plastic and healthy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The takeaway here is that brains are extremely dynamic systems. If you&amp;rsquo;re missing a certain kind of intelligence, you &lt;em>can&lt;/em> learn it. That&amp;rsquo;s one of the most freeing things to learn about yourself. You might never be as intelligent at chess as Magnus Carlsen, but you can improve. You&amp;rsquo;re not confined to things you already know.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="environmental-factors">Environmental Factors&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Intelligence is not only dynamic because you can learn. Intelligence and learning are both dynamic because they&amp;rsquo;re affected by other factors such as your mood, the amount of rest you get, your diet and environmental influences. One of the most important factors for learning is an environment where you feel comfortable making mistakes. Being in an environment where your mistakes are mocked kills motivation to learn.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If there&amp;rsquo;s a professor that mocks a student for asking basic questions, that student will eventually become demotivated and stop asking. They&amp;rsquo;ll accept their ignorance on the subject because nobody likes being put down. Put that student in a different classroom where they feel they can be open about their ignorance and won&amp;rsquo;t be judged or mocked and they might excel beyond what others originally thought them capable of.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="be-open-minded-about-intelligence">Be Open-Minded About Intelligence&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>What I want to promote is a sense of open-mindedness about human intelligence. It&amp;rsquo;s very easy to get frustrated when someone doesn&amp;rsquo;t understand something that comes easily to you. That&amp;rsquo;s the natural thing to do. But perhaps you&amp;rsquo;re the wrong person to explain it or the way you explain it is confusing to them. Perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s just not the right time, environment, or circumstances for them to learn. Everyone has different intelligences and different capacities for acquiring intelligences. That&amp;rsquo;s why it&amp;rsquo;s really important to have patience with others. I don&amp;rsquo;t just say that to be politically correct either. &lt;strong>To call anyone generally intelligent or unintelligent is almost always an oversimplification of intelligence and human potential&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Intelligence is not binary nor linear nor static. It&amp;rsquo;s a multidimensional, highly dynamic human capacity. We should consider that before putting labels on people. I&amp;rsquo;ll end with a quote from &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Nye">Bill Nye&lt;/a>, the science guy:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Everyone you will ever meet knows something you don&amp;rsquo;t.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Pledge of Allegiance</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/the-pledge-of-allegiance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/the-pledge-of-allegiance/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-pledge">The Pledge&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Many foreigners would be surprised to find out that we have something in the US called the Pledge of Allegiance. It&amp;rsquo;s recited in public schools across the whole country every day with students standing facing the flag hand over heart. It goes like this:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America and to the Republic for which it stands, one nation under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>To foreigners, the idea of all students standing up every morning chanting this probably sounds creepy. But since Americans are indoctrinated into chanting it starting in primary school, it goes unquestioned. Most American students don&amp;rsquo;t ever think about what the words mean. It&amp;rsquo;s just a ritual. I don&amp;rsquo;t agree with it, but I&amp;rsquo;m just giving rationale for why students go along with it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="legality">Legality&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>American students aren&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em>legally&lt;/em> required to stand for the Pledge. In &lt;a href="https://supreme.justia.com/cases/federal/us/319/624/case.html">West Virginia State Board of Education v. Barnette&lt;/a>, the Supreme Court ruled that students can&amp;rsquo;t be compelled to stand for or recite the Pledge as that would constitute compulsory speech, violating the First Amendment to the Constitution. Also students can&amp;rsquo;t be required to justify themselves for not standing. So it is well within your rights not to stand as an American student.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You might still be &lt;em>socially expected&lt;/em> to stand depending on where you live. It&amp;rsquo;s likely that most other students stand, so you&amp;rsquo;ll feel uncomfortable the first few times if you choose to sit it out. With time it does get easier to stay sitting though. It&amp;rsquo;s only a few seconds of resisting peer pressure anyway.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="content-of-the-pledge">Content of The Pledge&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s break down what the pledge actually says. For starters, &amp;ldquo;I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;. It seems strange to pledge allegiance to a flag. A flag is a piece of fabric. What does it even mean to pledge your allegiance to a piece of fabric? Try figuring that one out.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The most controversial part of the pledge: &amp;ldquo;one nation under God&amp;rdquo;. The &amp;ldquo;under God&amp;rdquo; part was added in 1954 during the Cold War emphasizing the differences between the US and Soviet Union. Since then, monotheistic religion has been endorsed in public school through the Pledge. What happened to separation of church and state? There have been efforts by secular groups to challenge this.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;indivisible&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s not clear in which sense we are supposed to be indivisible. We are more politically divided than ever.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;with liberty and justice for all&amp;rdquo;. This is a nice thought. But it&amp;rsquo;s just not true. Our nation doesn&amp;rsquo;t have liberty and justice for all. We&amp;rsquo;ve certainly made progress, but still roughly half a million Americans not convicted of a crime are behind bars right now. Is that liberty and justice for all? What about the 1% of our population in prison being deprived of basic human dignity as you read this. Where is their justice? The Pledge says liberty and justice for &lt;em>all&lt;/em>, not liberty and justice for only model citizens. I understand it&amp;rsquo;s a very high standard to meet, but we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t pretend we&amp;rsquo;re there yet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Clearly the content of the Pledge has quite a few big problems. The only part I don&amp;rsquo;t take issue with is the part about the US being a republic. Everything else could be improved upon. I would avoid standing for the Pledge on the basis of its content alone. But there&amp;rsquo;s an even better reason not to stand for the Pledge, even if the problems with the content of the Pledge are resolved.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-pledge-is-a-form-of-brainwashing">The Pledge is a Form of Brainwashing&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When do Americans first learn the Pledge? Not as preteens or teenagers. We learn it from the first day of public school when we are too young to understand the meaning. We are too young to question it, to decide if we should be doing it or not. It&amp;rsquo;s not really presented to us as optional, even though legally it is. It&amp;rsquo;s just something we are all commanded to do. Truth be told, most teachers probably aren&amp;rsquo;t aware that it&amp;rsquo;s optional either.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The thought of a room full of students all standing facing the flag hand over heart chanting allegiance without thinking about it evokes a very uncomfortable feeling. It communicates a certain message even if you don&amp;rsquo;t say the actual words. It&amp;rsquo;s saying &amp;ldquo;You &lt;em>must&lt;/em> love this country! You &lt;em>must&lt;/em> be a sincere patriot!&amp;rdquo;. Any practice that tries to mandate how you feel is repulsive. It leaves students that don&amp;rsquo;t love their country feeling guilty.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Suppose you don&amp;rsquo;t love your country. Are you a terrible citizen because love isn&amp;rsquo;t what you feel? There&amp;rsquo;s this idea among many Americans that they love their country and others &lt;em>ought&lt;/em> to as well. But this doesn&amp;rsquo;t make any sense. Patriotism is involuntary. It can&amp;rsquo;t be forced. Maybe you can be coerced or peer pressured into putting your hand over your heart and looking solemn, but that&amp;rsquo;s not real devotion to your country. It&amp;rsquo;s an empty gesture.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-network-effect">The Network Effect&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re an American student, you accomplish 2 important things by not standing for the morning brainwashing session:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>You cause other students to think critically. Other students will notice you are not standing. This causes them to reflect on their standing which they previously never thought about. They might ask you why you don&amp;rsquo;t stand. That gives you the opportunity to explain the problems with the content of the Pledge and how it&amp;rsquo;s actually a form of brainwashing.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>You make it easier for other students not to stand. If others decide to join you in sitting it out, they won&amp;rsquo;t feel alone in doing so. The more people that sit it out, the more standing students will feel the need to think critically about why they&amp;rsquo;re standing.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="my-story">My Story&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I stopped standing for the Pledge in high school (secondary for international readers). As a nonbeliever, I took issue with the phrase &amp;ldquo;under god&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The most eventful thing to come of my sitting was a teacher confronted me over it before class in front of all the other students. He told me I have to stand and he asked me why I didn&amp;rsquo;t stand. I went to a conservative high school and I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to make an issue since I was surrounded by a class full of students that likely thought the same as he did. If I did say something, students likely would have chimed in to tell me why I was wrong. I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to be shamed by the moral majority, so I just said I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to talk about it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In retrospect, I should have spoken up about why I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to sit even if I got shamed. It&amp;rsquo;s important for one&amp;rsquo;s voice to be heard, even if the message is unpopular.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At that time, I would have been satisfied with the Pledge if &amp;ldquo;under god&amp;rdquo; was removed. Since then, as you can see in this post, I&amp;rsquo;ve found many more objections to it besides violating church state separation. Now I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t support any pledge in public schools, regardless of its content especially if it&amp;rsquo;s performed before students reach the age of reason, it isn&amp;rsquo;t critically examined beforehand, and students aren&amp;rsquo;t explicitly told they don&amp;rsquo;t have to participate. Even then, teachers could still be biased against students that refuse to do it. And students that don&amp;rsquo;t might get bullied for it in conservative schools. It goes against the spirit of education, so better to just abolish it entirely.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Shining Light on the Dark Side of Law Enforcement</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/shining-light-on-the-dark-side-of-law-enforcement/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/shining-light-on-the-dark-side-of-law-enforcement/</guid><description>&lt;p>The US constitution is &lt;em>supposed&lt;/em> to protect citizens from &lt;a href="https://stallman.org/glossary.html#thug">thug&lt;/a> overreach. However, &lt;strong>evidence from the past decade shows that thugs have been stomping all over our civil liberties daily by colluding with intelligence agencies&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The federal government does this by constructing lies about how agents discover information. For example if the government discovers a crime through illegal mass surveillance or another covert surveillance program, it can&amp;rsquo;t use that evidence &lt;em>directly&lt;/em> because that would violate the 4th amendment and expose Big Brother. Instead, &amp;ldquo;hints&amp;rdquo; are passed on to thugs so they can construct a &amp;ldquo;parallel&amp;rdquo; chain of evidence that &lt;em>can&lt;/em> be used in court. This is where it gets the name &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parallel_construction">parallel construction&lt;/a>. Parallel construction sounds like innocuous jargon from an architecture course, so I prefer to call the practice by the more descriptive name, &lt;strong>evidence laundering&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Evidence laundering prevents defendants in criminal cases from knowing about infringements of their rights. It makes challenging thugs' actions in court very difficult, making a mockery of the right to a fair trial. The motivation for thugs to respect a defendant&amp;rsquo;s rights is that evidence obtained illegally cannot be used in court. With evidence laundering, the illegal evidence is converted into legal evidence. Therefore the motivation not to violate citizen&amp;rsquo;s rights goes away, so long as thugs can keep citizens from proving it occurred. Even if a defendant in a criminal trial suspects evidence laundering, it&amp;rsquo;s nigh impossible to prove. This puts minorities and political activists at risk of having their rights violated without even knowing it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Moreover, &lt;strong>evidence laundering undermines the civil liberties of every citizen&lt;/strong>. It is not a technique for enforcing the law. One cannot simultaneously subvert the law and enforce it. It&amp;rsquo;s just a tool for government-aided vigilantism. It will only continue to erode citizens' constitutional rights as government surveillance programs expand. It &lt;em>must&lt;/em> be outlawed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Find more information about evidence laundering at &lt;a href="https://www.hrw.org/report/2018/01/09/dark-side/secret-origins-evidence-us-criminal-cases">hrw.org&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bringing Civility to Public Discourse With the Steel Man Technique</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/bringing-civility-to-public-discourse-with-the-steel-man-technique/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/bringing-civility-to-public-discourse-with-the-steel-man-technique/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-united-states-in-2020">The United States in 2020&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The political situation in the United States right now is &lt;em>tense&lt;/em>, to say the least. President-elect Joe Biden won the 2020 general election. Meanwhile &lt;a href="https://stallman.org/glossary.html#bullshitter">the bullshitter&lt;/a> continues to make baseless claims of massive mail-in voter fraud to discredit the election results. No doubt the tens of millions of Americans duped into his &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cult_of_personality">personality cult&lt;/a> will fall for his lies, with some taking political action as we near &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_presidential_inauguration">inauguration day&lt;/a>. The rest of Americans are bewildered by how &lt;a href="https://stallman.org/glossary.html#troll">the troll&lt;/a> even got elected in the first place. So there is a heavy emotional and ideological divide in America today and I think any American half paying attention senses it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Therefore I feel it my duty as a citizen to do what I can to bring people together in these divided times. I don&amp;rsquo;t think it&amp;rsquo;s good to create consensus for the sake of it by suggesting &lt;a href="https://yourlogicalfallacyis.com/middle-ground">everyone take the middle ground&lt;/a>. No, the goal is to collectively arrive at &lt;strong>truth&lt;/strong>, which may or may not lie somewhere in the middle. So in this post I&amp;rsquo;m going to suggest a technique I think will drastically improve the public discourse which, I feel, is one of America&amp;rsquo;s biggest problems right now.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-steel-man-technique">The Steel Man Technique&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Philosopher and cognitive scientist &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Dennett">Daniel Dennett&lt;/a> described a method for arguing with a person that holds opposing views. If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever heard of the &lt;a href="https://yourlogicalfallacyis.com/strawman">straw man fallacy&lt;/a>, it&amp;rsquo;s just the opposite of that. With the straw man, you misrepresent your opponent&amp;rsquo;s argument to make it easier to take down. With the steel man, you face the most charitable interpretation of your oppenent&amp;rsquo;s argument. There are 4 steps to steelmanning as explained by Dennett:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>You should attempt to re-express your target’s position so clearly, vividly, and fairly that your target says, “Thanks, I wish I’d thought of putting it that way.&amp;quot;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You should list any points of agreement (especially if they are not matters of general or widespread agreement).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You should mention anything you have learned from your target.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Only then are you permitted to say so much as a word of rebuttal or criticism.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h4 id="step-1">Step 1&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The first 3 steps comprise the steel man tactic. What I like about the first step is it forces you to understand your target&amp;rsquo;s position. If you restate your target&amp;rsquo;s position and they don&amp;rsquo;t agree with your summary, then allow them to correct you. Expressing your target&amp;rsquo;s position in your own words in a way they agree with shows that you actually &lt;em>understand&lt;/em> their argument. &lt;strong>You can&amp;rsquo;t argue against a position you don&amp;rsquo;t understand. If you don&amp;rsquo;t understand it, how can you know that you disagree?&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="step-2">Step 2&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Step 2 is the most important step. It gives you credibility. It shows you&amp;rsquo;re interested in arriving at the truth, not just winning the argument. You don&amp;rsquo;t see it in politics because most of the time it&amp;rsquo;s just about winning the argument. Politicians think that if they give their opponent an inch, then they&amp;rsquo;re conceding the entire debate. But by refusing to concede on any points, or at least refusing to validate the reasons behind those points, they lose all credibility. They show themselves uninterested in understanding the other side&amp;rsquo;s point of view.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not saying you should take the &lt;a href="https://yourlogicalfallacyis.com/middle-ground">middle ground&lt;/a>. I absolutely disagree with that. In some cases, your target is just going to be wrong on every point. In those cases, agreeing with your target is inappropriate. What I recommend instead is trying to relate in any other way to what your target is saying. &lt;strong>It&amp;rsquo;s important that you never assume your target&amp;rsquo;s motivation for making an argument.&lt;/strong> Otherwise, you risk creating a straw man, patronizing them and turning them off to what you&amp;rsquo;re about to say. If you do make an assumption about your target&amp;rsquo;s reasons for making an argument, always phrase it as a question leaving open the chance for them to interject. &lt;strong>Whatever you do, don&amp;rsquo;t skip step 2. Without step 2, it&amp;rsquo;s not steelmanning.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="step-3">Step 3&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The third step allows your target to feel good about themselves before you engage them. It shows them that they added value to your life by teaching you something new. For example it could be what makes the argument appeal to them. The point may have already been &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Point_refuted_a_thousand_times">refuted 1,000 times&lt;/a>, but maybe there&amp;rsquo;s something novel that appeals to the person you&amp;rsquo;re talking to about that argument that you never considered. You&amp;rsquo;re not always going to learn something from your target. My advice for this step is to be genuine. If you do learn something, tell the target. If not, don&amp;rsquo;t act like you did. That&amp;rsquo;s disingenuous and could damage your credibility.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="step-4">Step 4&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The step you&amp;rsquo;ve all been waiting for! In step 4 you get to tear down your target&amp;rsquo;s argument. Remember you are tearing down the argument, not the person. &lt;strong>Never tear down the person unless their character is directly relevant to the subject of debate.&lt;/strong> If I&amp;rsquo;m debating with someone about health care in the United States, that person&amp;rsquo;s character is totally irrelevant to the conversation. If I&amp;rsquo;m running for public office, then my character is directly relevant to my campaign. It&amp;rsquo;s not just about the issues. It&amp;rsquo;s about who I am because you can&amp;rsquo;t know that I&amp;rsquo;ll faithfully execute my duties unless you know I&amp;rsquo;m credible. In that case it &lt;em>does&lt;/em> make sense to criticize the person.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-steelmanning-works">Why Steelmanning Works&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Evolution hasn&amp;rsquo;t caught up with modern society. It&amp;rsquo;s a slow process that takes millions of years. Meanwhile society has advanced rapidly, especially since the scientific revolution. A vestige of our caveman past is the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fight-or-flight_response_(in_humans)">fight-or-flight response&lt;/a> in our reptile brains. Back when our species was hunter-gatherer, threats were constant and danger was all around us. Nowadays, especially in civilized societies, we don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about that as much. But when our core beliefs are challenged, it can still trigger the ancient fight-or-flight response. Once that happens, we aren&amp;rsquo;t going to be really listening to our debate opponent. We also subconsciously identify with our beliefs. When those beliefs are challenged, our very identity is called into question.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The reason steelmanning is effective is it lowers a person&amp;rsquo;s psychological barriers to criticism. By making your target feel heard, validating their points, and showing them you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the truth even if you&amp;rsquo;re wrong, you lower their guard so they&amp;rsquo;ll be more willing to hear your opinion. Steelmanning is completely independent of your political affiliation. Anyone with any set of beliefs can practice steelmanning. If more people did this, it could &lt;em>vastly&lt;/em> improve public discourse.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tact">Tact&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>You are going to hear good criticisms of your beliefs from people that have poor tact. It&amp;rsquo;s important not to throw out criticism just because it comes from someone that doesn&amp;rsquo;t use steelmanning. I value diversity in argument techniques. We don&amp;rsquo;t need &lt;em>everyone&lt;/em> steelmanning all the time. &lt;a href="https://christopherhitchens.net/">Christopher Hitchens&lt;/a> was a world renowned debater and he definitely wasn&amp;rsquo;t known for politeness, yet he was &lt;em>far&lt;/em> from ineffective. Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote by him:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;My own opinion is enough for me, and I claim the right to have it defended against any consensus, any majority, anywhere, any place, any time. And anyone who disagrees with this can pick a number, get in line, and kiss my ass.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hitchens was a legend no doubt. He managed to be effective in debates and win an audience even though he enjoyed being rude to people. He had tact. Most of us can&amp;rsquo;t do that. It takes a very witty person to pull it off the way he did. I&amp;rsquo;m grateful that there&amp;rsquo;s a large variety of ways people debate. &lt;strong>There isn&amp;rsquo;t one right way to debate because different tactics appeal to different audiences.&lt;/strong> But there was only one Hitchens. Therefore, our public discourse in the United States would be best served by moving in a more &amp;ldquo;Dennett&amp;rdquo; direction instead of a more &amp;ldquo;Hitchens&amp;rdquo; direction.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With the steel man technique, we stand a better chance at bridging the political divide and having more fruitful conversations with those we disagree with. Every American half paying attention realizes how important it&amp;rsquo;s going to be that we can have those conversations as we near inauguration day.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Stop Amazon's Police State</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/stop-amazons-police-state/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/stop-amazons-police-state/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="amazons-orwellian-surveillance-hellscape">Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Orwellian Surveillance Hellscape&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Amazon is providing police departments with warrantless access to thousands of Ring doorbell cameras&lt;/strong> giving cops unpredecented, persistent surveillance capabilities of private homes and neighborhoods. This is yet another dangerous partnership between &lt;a href="https://stallman.org/amazon.html">the empire of the megacorporations&lt;/a> and the state.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Police don&amp;rsquo;t even need probable cause to request the Ring camera footage. If the &amp;ldquo;owner&amp;rdquo; of the camera refuses to share footage with the police, the real owner (Amazon) can provide the footage anyway. There are no safeguards and there&amp;rsquo;s no accountability in place to protect the footage. &lt;strong>This persistent dragnet neighborhood video surveillance is incompatible with democracy and must be stopped.&lt;/strong> Sign the petition at &lt;a href="https://www.cancelring.com/">www.cancelring.com&lt;/a> and tell your local officials to cancel these partnerships that violate our basic civil liberties.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This petition focuses on ending Amazon+Police partnerships, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t go far enough. Amazon Ring cameras should not be allowed to exist. &lt;strong>Ring doorbell cameras are an instrument of Big Brother whether or not there is a formal partnership between local police departments and Amazon.&lt;/strong> If someone you know uses one of these cameras, show them the petition and ask them to remove the camera from their home. &lt;strong>Good neighbors don&amp;rsquo;t set up persistent, warrantless Big Brother surveillance of their neighborhood.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Avoiding Consumer Surveillance</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/avoiding-consumer-surveillance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/avoiding-consumer-surveillance/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-age-of-surveillance">The Age of Surveillance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We live in the age of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surveillance_capitalism">surveillance capitalism&lt;/a>. Intimate data about us is collected, bought and sold for profit and social control. Intermediaries like banks, payment companies, credit card companies and governments have unprecedented access into our private lives through our purchases. This level of surveillance is tyrannical. &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/surveillance-vs-democracy.en.html">Mass surveillance is dangerous to the health of democracy and must be stopped&lt;/a>. Big Brother should not know what we buy. In this post, I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk about how we avoid consumer surveillance. In a future post, I&amp;rsquo;ll talk about anonymous online shopping and some promising software projects that could be a more permanent remedy to consumer surveillance. Ultimately, there is going to have to be political action to curtail surveillance, not just new technology. But until there is increased awareness of mass surveillance and real political action against it occurs, all we can hope to do is avoid the surveillance. So here&amp;rsquo;s how you do that.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="always-pay-cash">Always Pay Cash&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This is the golden rule. To avoid surveillance, you should always pay in cash. &lt;strong>Never use a credit or debit card. Never use Google Pay, Apple Pay, Cash App, Samsung Pay, Paypal, Circle Pay, Venmo, Square Cash, Zelle, Facebook Messenger, or any other payment app. Reject online shopping unless you can remain anonymous. Don&amp;rsquo;t shop at Amazon, Ebay, or other online marketplaces that require you to identify yourself.&lt;/strong> Is always paying in cash inconvenient? Maybe. That depends on how reliant you are on online shopping. Is it possible? Definitely. Is it worth it? Absolutely. Paying cash even once helps resist surveillance. Even though Big Brother would love to see a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cashless_society">cashless society&lt;/a> where all your purchases are fully transparent, we aren&amp;rsquo;t in that dystopian nightmare yet. If a merchant refuses to accept your cash, then find another merchant that will take cash. You&amp;rsquo;ll be anonymous and you&amp;rsquo;ll create economic pressure against a cashless society. If the story ended there, I&amp;rsquo;d just end this post now. But it&amp;rsquo;s not that easy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="avoid-disloyalty-programs">Avoid Disloyalty Programs&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Paying in cash is &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Necessity_and_sufficiency">necessary but not sufficient&lt;/a> for anonymous purchases. Just because you pay in cash doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you&amp;rsquo;re anonymous. Retailers have come up with clever ways to trick you into deanonymizing yourself even when you pay cash. They&amp;rsquo;re called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loyalty_program">loyalty programs&lt;/a>. Here&amp;rsquo;s how their dirty scheme works: An &amp;ldquo;operator&amp;rdquo; asks you if you&amp;rsquo;re already signed up for the rewards program. If you say no, they ask you if you want to sign up. If you agree, then they begin asking you for personally identifying information about yourself like your name, address, and phone number. Things they have absolutely no business knowing that are irrelevant to the transaction you&amp;rsquo;re performing. Once you cough up your information, they give you a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cashback_reward_program">rewards card&lt;/a>, otherwise known as a points card, advantage card, or club card. On all your future purchases, you use your loyalty card and earn &amp;ldquo;points&amp;rdquo; which gives you future discounts and deals. The catch is they link all your purchases with your identity and then sell that data to data brokers. I call them disloyalty cards because you&amp;rsquo;re being disloyal to your fellow citizens by tacitly approving of consumer surveillance. Disloyalty programs are only loyal to Big Brother. Every time you use them, you make it harder for other people to reject them. You&amp;rsquo;re voting for surveillance with your money. Others that don&amp;rsquo;t submit themselves to the unjust surveillance may have to pay fees of up to 10% for not being signed up. &lt;a href="https://www.samsclub.com/">See Sam&amp;rsquo;s Club&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Even if the disloyalty program doesn&amp;rsquo;t require you to give any personal information to sign up, it can still be used to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linked_data">link&lt;/a> your purchases together. When your &amp;ldquo;buyer profile&amp;rdquo; gets sold and combined with other data, it&amp;rsquo;s trivially easy to deanonymize your purchases. Let&amp;rsquo;s say you sign up for a disloyalty card that doesn&amp;rsquo;t require giving your personal information. The items purchased and time and date of purchase are all linked on your disloyalty card. Useless information on its own. But then the supermarket you buy from sells your &amp;ldquo;buyer profile&amp;rdquo; to &lt;a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Goolag">Goolag&lt;/a> who compares your location history from your phone to the disloyalty card data. The supermarket has 3,000 customers that use a disloyalty card, but only 1 customer has a location history that matches the times and dates that the card made purchases. That&amp;rsquo;s you. And just like that, your purchases are deanonymized. But you&amp;rsquo;re clever. You turn your phone off before you go to the store. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter. Goolag correlates the time at which your phone turns off with the time of the purchases. You&amp;rsquo;re deanonymized again. Let&amp;rsquo;s say you don&amp;rsquo;t even have a mobile phone. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter. You drive a car to the supermarket. A private &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/pages/what-alpr">automatic license plate reader&lt;/a> company records your license plate number as you drive to the store and sells that data to Goolag. Goolag correlates your driving times with the card purchase times and now all your purchases going back years are deanonymized. So you &lt;em>walk&lt;/em> to the supermarket with your disloyalty card instead of driving. That won&amp;rsquo;t help you either. &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/pages/face-recognition">AI-powered facial recognition cameras&lt;/a> all over the supermarket identify you and the times you&amp;rsquo;re there. The company that makes those cameras sells that data to Goolag. Goolag correlates the times again and your purchases are deanonymized. So you go to a &lt;em>different supermarket&lt;/em> with a different disloyalty card. You don&amp;rsquo;t have a phone. You walk there. There are no surveillance cameras inside. How could you possibly be deanonymized now? Your bandwidth usage on your home network is low while you&amp;rsquo;re gone at the store. Your ISP sells this data to Goolag who correlates it with your card and you&amp;rsquo;re deanonymized again.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Just pay a little extra to avoid the disloyalty card.&lt;/strong> Refusing disloyalty cards also protects the anonymity of others. If you use a disloyalty card, then you might shrink the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anonymity">anonymity set&lt;/a> of others not using a card. Whether others have consumer privacy is not your choice to make. You won&amp;rsquo;t get the discount but so what? At least everything you buy won&amp;rsquo;t be in a searchable database.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="dont-identify-yourself-to-merchants">Don&amp;rsquo;t Identify Yourself to Merchants&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Some places of business won&amp;rsquo;t offer you a disloyalty card, but they will ask for &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personally_identifiable_information">personally identifiable information&lt;/a> (PII) like your name and phone number. The crux of the problem with consumer surveillance is identifying yourself to the merchant. Never identify yourself. Yes, disloyalty cards identify you. All payment methods besides cash identify you. But also giving any information about yourself that gets put into a computer system identifies you. &lt;strong>If the merchant demands you identify yourself during a purchase where you would not otherwise be identified, then don&amp;rsquo;t do it.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, it makes more sense to use a credit or debit card for airline tickets and car rentals because they demand ID anyway. I would still recommend paying cash that way your bank and credit card company don&amp;rsquo;t automatically see that you rented a car, the make and model, where and when you rented it and how much it costed. Sure you&amp;rsquo;re already identifying yourself to the rental company. Your purchase is already being recorded in a database, but you can still minimize the &lt;em>number&lt;/em> of databases it&amp;rsquo;s stored in by paying cash. At least all your identified purchases won&amp;rsquo;t be in a single centralized database that&amp;rsquo;s easy to get at. They&amp;rsquo;ll have to be aggregated by data brokers first. So I&amp;rsquo;m going to reiterate the golden rule: &lt;strong>always pay cash.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="resisting-intrusive-surveillance">Resisting Intrusive Surveillance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Despite always paying cash and never explicitly identifying yourself, big retailers can still identify you through more intrusive means of surveillance. I&amp;rsquo;ve already hinted at this in talking about disloyalty programs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="facial-recognition-technology">Facial Recognition Technology&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Surveillance cameras combined with facial recognition technology can uniquely identify you and the items you buy. The best way to combat this is to find smaller stores that don&amp;rsquo;t have surveillance cameras. It&amp;rsquo;s also not a bad idea to let the store owner or management know you choose their store over big retailers because they offer more privacy. If that&amp;rsquo;s not practical for you, then be sure to wear a mask in the big retailers and a hat that covers your face from overhead cameras. One of the few good things that has come from Covid-19 is that it&amp;rsquo;s now socially acceptable to wear masks inside stores. Wearing a mask simultaneously makes you harder to identify by facial recognition technology and prevents the spread of coronavirus.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are other ways you can be deanonymized through video surveillance besides facial recognition, but there&amp;rsquo;s not much you can do about them. For that reason, I&amp;rsquo;m not going to cover them. Just know that they exist and that they have to be addressed through political action, not personal choices.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="wifi-location-tracking">Wifi Location Tracking&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The other way that big retailers have become more invasive is through wifi location tracking of your smartphone. Your phone emits wifi signals to determine which wireless networks are available nearby. The person operating the retailer&amp;rsquo;s wifi network can use those signals to track your movements within the store. It&amp;rsquo;s profitable to collect your movement data, so you should assume that retailers are doing it. Your phone also has a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MAC_address">MAC address&lt;/a> which can &lt;em>uniquely&lt;/em> identify you, especially if your phone doesn&amp;rsquo;t randomize it. Other wireless protocols that you leave activated on your phone might also be able to be misused by the retailer to track your movements. To avoid location tracking altogether, you can fully power down your phone before you enter the store. If that isn&amp;rsquo;t good enough for you, another option is placing your phone inside a &lt;a href="https://privacypros.io/faraday-bags/">faraday bag&lt;/a>. Be sure to test it out before you use it though.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="anonymous-online-shopping">Anonymous Online Shopping&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We have grown accustomed to the luxury of having whatever we want show up at our doorstep with the click of a button. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to say no when you&amp;rsquo;ve gotten so used to it. For those who really don&amp;rsquo;t want to give up online shopping, I&amp;rsquo;m going to write a guide on how to anonymously buy and sell goods online. There&amp;rsquo;s a few different methods for 100% anonymous online shopping. Some of them get very involved, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to save all the details for another post. See ya next time!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Raising the Bar on Privacy</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/raising-the-bar-on-privacy/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/raising-the-bar-on-privacy/</guid><description>&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s a common attitude many people have regarding privacy. I&amp;rsquo;m not talking about &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Nothing_to_hide">nothing to hide&lt;/a>, although that is also a very common attitude. It has been refuted &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ad_nauseam">ad nauseum&lt;/a> by privacy advocates, so I won&amp;rsquo;t do it again here. I&amp;rsquo;m talking about the feeling people have that the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surveillance_state">corporate/government surveillance state&lt;/a> (Big Brother) will collect their data one way or another no matter what, so there&amp;rsquo;s no point in even trying to avoid mass surveillance. Privacy is already dead. Mass surveillance and its &lt;a href="https://www.socialcooling.com/">long-term negative side-effects&lt;/a> are inevitable. That&amp;rsquo;s the attitude of so many people and it&amp;rsquo;s disappointing. So, I&amp;rsquo;m going to offer an alternative way to think about privacy and surveillance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, let&amp;rsquo;s be clear. &lt;strong>Privacy is not just a personal preference. It&amp;rsquo;s not just a social necessity either. It&amp;rsquo;s a biological necessity as basic as breathing. It allows us all to be human. It is the right to be imperfect. Therefore, it &lt;em>must&lt;/em> be protected. There is no point in asking if it&amp;rsquo;s too late to stop mass surveillance because there&amp;rsquo;s no alternative to curtailing it. It must be stopped&lt;/strong>. &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/surveillance-vs-democracy.en.html">Democracy can only withstand so much surveillance&lt;/a>. Mass surveillance in its current form and true democracy &lt;em>cannot&lt;/em> coexist indefinitely. Surveillance tools combined with &lt;a href="https://github.com/daviddao/awful-ai">AI&lt;/a> will only get more powerful as time passes. To put it frankly, we are either going to reign in mass surveillance or democracy will perish. We have to reject the defeatist excuse that we&amp;rsquo;ve already lost to mass surveillance and so we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t even try to restore privacy. That&amp;rsquo;s just a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-fulfilling_prophecy">self-fulfilling prophecy&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The alternative, yet realistic way of thinking (as opposed to defeatism) that I want to introduce is what I call &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;raising the bar on privacy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>. It&amp;rsquo;s a very simple idea. Maybe Big Brother can still get our data even if we take steps to increase our privacy. Even if the defeatist is right that our data can or will be collected anyway, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t make it as difficult as possible. Let&amp;rsquo;s not hand over our data on a silver platter at least, right? If enough of us take steps to increase our privacy, we will make it &lt;em>more difficult and more expensive&lt;/em> for Big Brother to collect our data. We collectively &amp;ldquo;raise the bar on privacy&amp;rdquo;. Even if we can&amp;rsquo;t fully insulate our own lives from Big Brother, if we can force Big Brother to resort to the more powerful means of surveillance (think &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zero-day_(computing)">0-day exploits&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Targeted_surveillance">targeted surveillance&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hardware_backdoor">hardware/firmware backdoors&lt;/a>) more often instead of the low-hanging fruit of collecting our data from big tech companies, then our society will gain several benefits:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>As privacy-friendly tools gain popularity, people that use them won&amp;rsquo;t become especially &amp;ldquo;interesting&amp;rdquo; to Big Brother anymore.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The desire for privacy won&amp;rsquo;t be viewed as a cause for suspicion of wrongdoing, but instead as a basic biological need that everyone is entitled to.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The perception of increased privacy on its own will cause individuals to speak and act more freely, reducing &lt;a href="https://www.socialcooling.com">social cooling&lt;/a> and making it easier to speak out against mass surveillance.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Big Brother will be forced into using more powerful surveillance tools more frequently to collect the same data it already does, thus increasing its public exposure.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html">Free software&lt;/a> will become more widespread since it&amp;rsquo;s a necessary precondition for digital privacy.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/proprietary/proprietary.html">Proprietary software&lt;/a> will become less widespread since people will use free software in its place.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>To sum up this post in a way that makes sense to security-minded people: our minimum acceptable lower bound for a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Threat_model">threat model&lt;/a> should be avoiding mass surveillance so that we raise the bar on privacy.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Legalize All Drugs</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/legalize-all-drugs/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/legalize-all-drugs/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="history-lesson">History Lesson&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A century ago, alcohol prohibition in the United States began with the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eighteenth_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution">18th amendment&lt;/a> prohibiting the production, importation and sale of alcoholic beverages and ended in 1933 with the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twenty-first_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution">21st amendment&lt;/a>. The goal of prohibition was to reduce alcohol consumption. While prohibition succeeded in reducing alcohol consumption somewhat, it resulted in many unintended consequences including public health problems, an increase in organized crime, and corruption of law enforcement. The war on &lt;del>drugs&lt;/del> otherwise peaceful people who choose to ingest intoxicants began in 1971 with Richard Nixon. &lt;del>&lt;del>It&amp;rsquo;s not that he refused to learn from the prohibition era. It was a calculated move with a political purpose. Namely, to target black people and anti-war hippies. Here&amp;rsquo;s a quote from John Ehrlichman, the domestic policy chief for the Nixon administration:&lt;/del>&lt;/del>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;&lt;del>&lt;del>You want to know what this was really all about? The Nixon campaign in 1968, and the Nixon White House after that, had two enemies: the antiwar left and black people. You understand what I&amp;rsquo;m saying? We knew we couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it illegal to be either against the war or black, but by getting the public to associate the hippies with marijuana and blacks with heroin, and then criminalizing both heavily, we could disrupt those communities. We could arrest their leaders, raid their homes, break up their meetings, and vilify them night after night on the evening news. Did we know we were lying about the drugs? Of course we did&lt;/del>&lt;/del>&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Edit (2020/12/05):&lt;/strong> This quote is poorly sourced. Upon further research, it seems Nixon&amp;rsquo;s war on drugs wasn&amp;rsquo;t politically motivated despite still being a disaster.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Still, the war on &amp;ldquo;drugs&amp;rdquo; only played a small part of law enforcement efforts on the whole until Ronald Reagan was inaugurated in 1981. Reagan expanded the drug war with a focus on criminal penalties instead of treatment. His policies resulted in a massive increase in incarcerations of nonviolent drug users. His wife Nancy Reagan started the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Just_Say_No">Just Say No&lt;/a> campaign to teach schoolchildren not to use drugs. It was about as effective at reducing drug use as abstinence-based sex education is at reducing sex. The most popular Just Say No program, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drug_Abuse_Resistance_Education">DARE&lt;/a>, showed zero effect on drug use according to &lt;a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/why-just-say-no-doesnt-work">20 controlled studies&lt;/a>. Perhaps that&amp;rsquo;s because DARE spreads lies and gives children a contorted picture of the war on drugs? In 1986, congress passed the Anti-Drug Abuse Act changing &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal_supervised_release">federal supervised release&lt;/a> programs increasing focus on punishment rather than rehabilitation, prohibiting &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Controlled_substance_analog">analogs of controlled substances&lt;/a> and requiring &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mandatory_sentencing">mandatory minimum sentences&lt;/a> for nonviolent drug users. The sentencing discrepency between crack and powder cocaine resulted in an uneven increase in incarceration rates for black people. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t that sound familiar?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 2020, a whole century since the beginning of prohibition era, there are signs that we are finally learning what history has to teach us: The unintended consequences of drug prohibition are worse than the problem it&amp;rsquo;s meant to solve. As of today, medical cannabis use is legalized in 35 states. The recreational use of cannabis is legalized in 15 states. 16 states have decriminalized cannabis use. Up to &lt;a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2020/01/20/marijuana-legalization-federal-laws-100688">40 states might allow some form of marijuana legalization&lt;/a> by the end of 2020. Just a few days ago Oregon became the first state to legalize magic mushrooms for medical use and decriminalize &amp;ldquo;street drugs&amp;rdquo;. People found in possession of street drugs will face a ticket and a 100 dollar fine rather than a felony. They will optionally be offered treatment. Despite recent progress, the war on &amp;ldquo;drugs&amp;rdquo; is still being waged almost 50 years later and drugs are cheaper and easier to acquire than ever. And that&amp;rsquo;s where we&amp;rsquo;re at today.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I could argue why drugs should be legalized without giving you the history lesson first, but historical context is important. It&amp;rsquo;s important to realize just how much harm the war on &amp;ldquo;drugs&amp;rdquo; has already caused thus far. Millions of people&amp;rsquo;s lives have been destroyed due to the effects of the war on drugs to the point that it is now a pervasive part of our culture including literature, movies and music. Drug addiction ruins people&amp;rsquo;s lives, but the war on drugs has ruined more. I am arguing for legalization of &lt;em>all&lt;/em> drugs. I&amp;rsquo;m going to offer arguments for legalization from several different perspectives.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="arguments-in-favor-of-legalization">Arguments in Favor of Legalization&lt;/h2>
&lt;h4 id="personal-autonomy">Personal Autonomy&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Drugs should be legal because your own body belongs to you, not the government. If I want to chop my finger off so I only have 4 fingers, I should be able to do it. You can say it&amp;rsquo;s the dumbest thing you&amp;rsquo;ve ever heard of, that something&amp;rsquo;s wrong with me, that no one in their right mind would do such a thing, but it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>my&lt;/em> finger. I&amp;rsquo;m not by any means comparing doing drugs to cutting your own finger off. Depending on which drug you do, it can be far less dangerous or far more dangerous than cutting your own finger off. Cutting your own finger off also doesn&amp;rsquo;t have any perceivable benefits whereas drugs do. That&amp;rsquo;s why people do them. Making this argument makes me sound like I lean libertarian, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think personal autonomy is without limits.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With abortion, there is another life (or potential human life) at stake. Whether you are pro-choice or pro-life, there is at least a potential human life there that you have to take into account in your calculation of banning abortion versus legalizing it. With suicide, it is your own life you are taking. It belongs to you. But it might make sense for agents of the state to have the authority to prevent you from committing suicide if you are in a crisis situation. Although it is your own life and belongs to you as far as the government should be concerned, your future self might be glad someone stopped you. Much like abortion, you can make the case that there is a potential happy human life that is being ended. With explicit informed patient consent as in euthenasia, that argument is much harder to make especially when someone is in great pain, terminally ill, and there is no prospect of future happiness. Anyway, the point is that personal autonomy isn&amp;rsquo;t an absolute. However, in general, you should be able to do whatever you want so long as it doesn&amp;rsquo;t infringe upon the rights of others.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You might object that while drug use may not infringe upon others' rights, it may affect them negatively even if you use drugs responsibly. So can watching too much TV, social media, and a million other things we don&amp;rsquo;t criminalize. While watching too much TV is bad for you, to criminalize watching too much TV would be tyrannical because it means the government &lt;em>gains&lt;/em> the right to restrict your viewing. My right to extend my fist ends at your face. Likewise, the right to do drugs, or as I&amp;rsquo;ll call it, the right to access alternative states of body and mind, means the government isn&amp;rsquo;t allowed to close you off from having certain types of experiences. If those states of mind produced by drugs are inconvenient for some government agenda like war, then that&amp;rsquo;s too bad. There is no &amp;ldquo;right for the government to restrict states of consciousness aversive to conflict&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Obviously, children should still be prohibited from doing drugs. Their brains aren&amp;rsquo;t fully developed yet and we have to have some legal cutoff point after which we assume people are intellectually and emotionally mature enough to decide what they want to do with themselves. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what that cutoff point is, but we already use that reasoning for many laws. You have to be 17-18 for an unrestricted driving permit. You have to be 18 to get a tattoo (in most states), marry (except Nebraska) or vote. You have to be 21 to legally buy alcohol, marijuana, or tobacco products. You have to be 25 years old to be a representative in the House of Representatives, 30 to be a senator, and 35 to be president. You gain more privileges only as you get older, and for good reason. The easiest, least costly way for the government to determine maturity is just to use age as a proxy. You can argue all day about what the legal age should be for drugs. But, once that age is met, you should be able to legally do the drugs you want as a matter of personal autonomy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="eliminating-drug-cartels">Eliminating Drug Cartels&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Besides personal autonomy, there are also strong social reasons for legalizing all drugs. Legalizing all drugs would put an end to the drug cartels and their associated violence by taking away their profits and undermining their whole reason for existing. Drug cartels exist for a specific purpose. Any time you have a commercial enterprise, you need some way to enforce rules regarding the manufacture, distribution and sale of the product. For example, if your illegal product is stolen, you can&amp;rsquo;t exactly report it to law enforcement. There is no legal recourse you can take. So you resort to violence, or at least make a credible threat of violence to deter future stealing. If you don&amp;rsquo;t threaten violence, then you have no way to deter stealing and other undesirable behavior. Other competing cartels will use violence to further their operations and you will be &amp;ldquo;outcompeted&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Not only would legalization help the United States, but it would also do a huge favor to Mexico which has been torn apart by the war on &amp;ldquo;drugs&amp;rdquo;. If the United States could legally produce its own drugs without having to import them in illegally from Mexico, then Mexican drug cartels would hemorrhage money. In fact, US border patrol has already seen a decrease in marijuana trafficking due to many states legalizing it. As the US continues to legalize drugs in more states, we can expect to see Mexican drug cartels lose even more market share until their demand completely disappears, replaced by legally operated businesses in the US.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="money">Money&lt;/h4>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Insanity is repeating the same mistakes and expecting different results.&amp;rdquo; (Narcotics Anonymous pamphlet)&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>If you believe that quote, then the war on drugs is the definition of insanity. The US has spent over a trillion dollars waging the war on drugs for about half a century. Despite the cost, drug use has expanded. Economic productivity is sacrificed in favor of mass imprisonment of drug users. Even a single minor offense can cost a lifetime of economic opportunity. It can mean you aren&amp;rsquo;t eligible for certain jobs, health benefits or financial aid. According to the Federal Bureau of Prisons, &lt;a href="https://www.bop.gov/about/statistics/statistics_inmate_offenses.jsp">roughly half of federal inmates are in prison for drug offenses&lt;/a>. In 2018, the Bureau of Prisons reported that the cost for federal inmates was $36,299.25 per year. By legalizing all drugs and pardoning all drug-related offenses, taxpayers could save about 3 billion dollars per year. Not to mention the DEA could be abolished saving tens of billions annually.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Criminalization also burdens the healthcare system dealing with consequences of unsafe, contaminated drug use. Enforcement against drug paraphernalia causes sharing of needles which spreads disease. This wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be as big of a problem if drugs were legalized since they would be regulated and tested for purity. Places that rely on tourism for economic activity are negatively affected when they are seen as dangerous due to drug cartel activity. Money that is spent on unregulated, illegal drugs can&amp;rsquo;t be spent on regulated, taxable and legal parts of the economy. Minorities and low income groups that are already economically vulnerable are more likely to be arrested for drugs, further decreasing future job prospects. Smaller economies are heavily distorted by the drug war. I could go on forever, but you can see that the drug war makes no sense from an economic standpoint.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="reducing-corruption">Reducing Corruption&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Wherever there is an organized illicit drug industry, there is also going to be police corruption. Mexico knows this all too well. In December 2019, &lt;a href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-edny/pr/former-mexican-secretary-public-security-arrested-drug-trafficking-conspiracy-and">Genaro García Luna&lt;/a>, Mexico&amp;rsquo;s former minister in charge of the federal police for 6 years, was arrested for allegedly taking millions from the Sinaloa cartel in return for safe passage of the cartel&amp;rsquo;s drug shipments and information on other rival cartels. Just last month &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/10/16/us/mexico-general-cienfuegos-dea.html">General Salvador Cienfuegos Zepeda&lt;/a>, Mexico&amp;rsquo;s former army chief for 6 years, was arrested on drug trafficking and money laundering charges. The CIA in the US was allegedly involved in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CIA_involvement_in_Contra_cocaine_trafficking">cocaine trafficking&lt;/a> in which several investigations ensued.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bottom line is dealing with the cartels is mutually beneficial for those in power, so long as they don&amp;rsquo;t get caught. Those in government and the police have all the wrong economic incentives when it comes to the drug war. In some government positions in countries with rampant corruption, it&amp;rsquo;s probably an unwritten job requirement to work with the cartels. We&amp;rsquo;ll probably never know which positions those are for sure though. Corruption happens in the shadows and it&amp;rsquo;s always difficult to produce any concrete evidence. Legalizing drugs would eliminate the cartel&amp;rsquo;s source of profit, which means politicians would no longer have any financial incentive to work with them. It follows that drug-related government and police corruption would decrease.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="improved-police-community-relations">Improved Police-Community Relations&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The war on &amp;ldquo;drugs&amp;rdquo; is responsible for police militarization more than anything else. Peaceful protestors and rioters face chemical irritants, armored vehicles and riot gear because the war on &amp;ldquo;drugs&amp;rdquo; has ensured police have military-style gear. Police militarization causes officers to view themselves as a confrontational force instead of community-oriented. In the eyes of the citizenry, this makes police look like an occupying force rather than public servants.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not dumping all the blame on cops either. The job of police officers is to enforce the law. When the law is unjust, the police still have to enforce it. It&amp;rsquo;s not fair on them because it makes them look bad. Ending the war on &amp;ldquo;drugs&amp;rdquo; would do so much for police-community relations. Children wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have to watch their parents hauled off to jail for choosing to engage in a victimless activity. Families wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be torn apart. Drug-related police corruption would end, as I talked about in the above section. Police departments could shift their resources toward stopping murderers and rapists, people causing real harm to society. Without ending the war on &amp;ldquo;drugs&amp;rdquo;, public confidence in policing will continue to erode. In the year 2020 where we have &lt;a href="https://www.commondreams.org/news/2020/06/12/nationwide-protests-over-police-brutality-continue-cities-across-us-cut-and">nationwide demonstrations against police brutality&lt;/a>, the &lt;a href="https://theintercept.com/2020/09/22/anarchist-jurisdictions-portland-new-york-seattle">Justice Department declaring NYC, Portland and Seattle &amp;ldquo;Anarchist Jurisdictions&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a>, and &lt;a href="https://nypost.com/2020/05/29/minneapolis-police-abandon-precinct-after-protesters-set-it-on-fire">police abandoning precincts&lt;/a>, police definitely shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be perpetuating a failed drug war that has lasted half a century and will only further diminish public trust in the police.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="why-not-just-decriminalize">Why not just Decriminalize?&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>In the late 1980&amp;rsquo;s and early 1990&amp;rsquo;s, 1 out of every 10 citizens in Portugal was addicted to heroin. To combat this, Portugal decriminalized all drug use. And it worked. Incarceration rates went down, infectious disease cases of HIV went down, and fatal overdoses went down. Decriminalization wasn&amp;rsquo;t the only thing that changed though. It was accompanied by a culture shift in the public attitude toward drugs and drug addiction. When your country isn&amp;rsquo;t busy locking people up over drugs, it can focus on helpful things like treatment, housing, and employment to help people recover. Several &lt;a href="https://www.inspiremalibu.com/blog/drug-addiction/10-countries-that-ended-their-war-on-drugs">other countries have ended their war on drugs&lt;/a>. So why not &lt;em>just&lt;/em> decriminalize drugs? Why the need to legalize?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First off, I need to explain the difference between the two. In general, decriminalization means that there are no longer &lt;em>criminal&lt;/em> penalties for an action. There may still be fines. Legalization means that the action is fully legal. There is no associated penalty. Drug possession should, without a doubt, at least be decriminalized because drug use isn&amp;rsquo;t a criminal issue. Drug manufacture can be regulated by the &lt;a href="https://www.fda.gov">FDA&lt;/a>, but drug possession should be fully legalized. There is no reason to punish drug users &lt;em>solely&lt;/em> for possessing drugs whether that be fines or jail time. That&amp;rsquo;s why all drug possession should be legalized, not just decriminalized.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you want to deter drug use, then there are better approaches than not fully legalizing drugs. This is where you could get creative. As a single example, turn the idea of a fine on its head. Offer a cash reward to addicts for staying clean. Consider cultural influences and other societal factors that may be causing people to turn toward drugs, such as poverty or mental illness. Perhaps the reason drug use is so high is because society has other problems that aren&amp;rsquo;t being attended to, and drugs are just a symptom of it. This is where policy could be informed by sociological research. If you think criminalizing or not fully legalizing drugs is the only way to deter their use, then I&amp;rsquo;d encourage you to think more creatively.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="drug-regulation">Drug Regulation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s move on to regulation. Regulation of drugs is important for ensuring drug quality, fair pricing, safety and education. But it&amp;rsquo;s also probably a good idea not to regulate drugs so heavily that a sizeable black market continues to exist. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to focus on regulation other than to say deciding on the regulations should be an evidence-based process. Lawmakers have almost 50 years of evidence on how not to treat drugs in society, so maybe they can learn from past mistakes and other countries that have decriminalized drugs and come up with regulations as drugs are legalized.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="drug-education">Drug Education&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As for education, let&amp;rsquo;s talk about some of the things schools shouldn&amp;rsquo;t do. First and foremost, school drug education programs should stop lying to children about drugs. Schools should stop teaching children that every hard drug user is an addict. Schools should stop teaching abstinence as the &lt;em>only&lt;/em> practical way of protecting oneself from harmful drugs. And they should stop using green-tinted goggles to mimic the effects of marijuana. &lt;a href="https://stonerthings.com/do-weed-goggles-work">Yes, they actually did that&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So what should schools do? They should tell the truth. They should teach that the war on &amp;ldquo;drugs&amp;rdquo; has been one of the greatest moral failures of our time, a colossal waste of money, time, resources and human life that could have been better spent on literally anything else. Education programs should provide a fairminded, evidence-based view of the advantages and disadvantages of drug use per each drug. Drug education programs need to instruct young adults which drugs are worth doing, which are not, how often and in what setting, once they are of age. Drug education should come before most young adults are offered drugs. Program instructors could be social workers instead of police officers because drug addiction is not a criminal issue. It&amp;rsquo;s a health issue. As we end the war on drugs, social workers should take responsibility for dealing with drug-related issues. Social workers can be trained based on prior drug research and hear testimony from non-addicted healthy drug users and addicts alike so they can get an accurate sense of the positive and negative effects of different drugs. This would put them in a good position to educate youth about drugs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="post-drug-war-society">Post Drug War Society&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Now that I&amp;rsquo;ve covered a few points on education, how will we convert our current society into a post drug war society? One answer is we need better resources for treating drug addiction. Education can only do so much if there aren&amp;rsquo;t effective resources out there. Drug treatment centers don&amp;rsquo;t even have to abide by federal guidelines and it&amp;rsquo;s debatable if they even work at all. That has to change. They need to be evidence-based and evaluated for effectiveness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Legalization should also be accompanied by a culture shift. Once drugs are legalized, drug users won&amp;rsquo;t necessarily be criminals. That will go a long way in making it easier for society not to demonize them. People that use drugs are not &amp;ldquo;bad people&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s nowhere near that simple. There are as many reasons people use drugs as there are drugs. There are people that use drugs in a healthy, responsible way and people that don&amp;rsquo;t. As I said before, there needs to be more resources for drug users in order to promote responsible use. And it&amp;rsquo;s hard to provide resources for that in a society where drugs are heavily criminalized and stigmatized. In a society where drug use is criminalized and stigmatized, drug users have to hide their drug use from family, friends and strangers for fear of legal and social repercussions. This culture of secrecy causes needless psychological suffering for people that use drugs for the wrong reasons. The social stigma around drug use causes users not to seek out help when they desperately need it. That includes addiction treatment, healthcare and psychiatric help. In a society where drugs are legalized and not stigmatized, none of that would be an issue. Drug users could be more open about their habits and get the resources they need to be responsible without worrying about being shamed or arrested.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The war on &amp;ldquo;drugs&amp;rdquo; seems to be coming to an end, albeit slowly. It&amp;rsquo;s not over yet though. If not for the drug war, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Death_of_Breonna_Taylor">Breonna Taylor&lt;/a> would still be with us. How many more people are going to have to spend years behind bars and forever be labeled felons for engaging in a victimless activity? How many more honest, otherwise law-abiding citizens are going to die for a war that should never have been waged to begin with? When is the needless violence perpetuated by the war on &amp;ldquo;drugs&amp;rdquo; going to finally end? Eventually, there will come a day when the very last person has their life ruined by the war on &lt;del>drugs&lt;/del> human beings. I hope that day comes sooner rather than later.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using Email</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/using-email/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/using-email/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="preface">Preface&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Email is a very old internet standard, predating the world wide web. It was first defined in 1982. It was &lt;a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5321">updated&lt;/a> in 2008 and remains in widespread use. It&amp;rsquo;s not a great protocol by today&amp;rsquo;s standards, but we&amp;rsquo;re all stuck with it. You almost certainly already have an email account. Although everyone has an email account, not everyone understands how email works or how to make the most of their account. Almost everyone with an email account just chose the first free, convenient option available for an email service provider. I know that&amp;rsquo;s what I did at first. Most people just use Gmail, Outlook, Yahoo, AOL, or one of the other top providers. Knowing this has motivated me to write this post because I fear that others are missing out on a better email experience.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="choosing-an-email-service-provider">Choosing an Email Service Provider&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The first step before using email is choosing an email service provider. Email is a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federation_%28information_technology%29">federated&lt;/a> protocol. This means that no single entity &amp;ldquo;owns&amp;rdquo; email. If you want, you can create your own email provider and use it. Instead of &lt;a href="mailto:john@gmail.com">john@gmail.com&lt;/a>, your domain would be something like &lt;a href="mailto:john@johnsdomain.com">john@johnsdomain.com&lt;/a>. But running your own mail server can be expensive and time-consuming. Mail servers also have many moving parts and require maintenance, so I won&amp;rsquo;t be writing about how to set up your own mail server. It&amp;rsquo;s just not a realistic option for non-technical users of email.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The best alternative to self-hosting is to pick an email service provider wisely. This list is obviously subjective, but here are some criteria which a good email service provider will meet:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Only free software&lt;/li>
&lt;li>IMAP/POP3 support&lt;/li>
&lt;li>No logs policy&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Inside a privacy-respecting country&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Transparency reports&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Anonymous sign up&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Anonymous payment methods&lt;/li>
&lt;li>2-factor authentication (TOTP)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Inbound encryption (PGP)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Tor support&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sustainable business model&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Well-established&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Support team / help center&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Migration support&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="free-software">Free Software&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The first and most important requirement is that the email provider uses &lt;em>exclusively&lt;/em> free software. This means their website and webmail portal do &lt;em>not&lt;/em> require &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/javascript-trap.en.html">proprietary Javascript&lt;/a>. Javascript licenses should be included somewhere on the site or it should work without Javascript enabled. Also, all backend software should be free. In other words, if an email provider uses Mac or Windows to host the email server, it&amp;rsquo;s as good as garbage and you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t touch it with a ten foot pole. It should probably run on GNU/Linux or FreeBSD. Good email providers support IMAP and POP3 for accessing email. Those protocols allow you to access emails from your own &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Email_client">email client&lt;/a> on any device. More on that later. Now onto security and privacy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="privacy-and-security">Privacy and Security&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The email provider should have a policy of not keeping logs. This brings me to my next and important point that the email provider needs to reside within a privacy-respecting country. The legal requirements for collecting logs and sharing user data are going to differ depending on which country it&amp;rsquo;s in. Using an email provider based in the US or the UK is a very bad idea. Those countries don&amp;rsquo;t have strong privacy considerations and your email data (and metadata) won&amp;rsquo;t be safe. Email providers in those countries &lt;em>can&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> guarantee safety of your emails. You can get a lot of information about what data is collected just by actually reading the Terms of Service when you sign up. Don&amp;rsquo;t use an email provider like Gmail, Outlook, or Yahoo that logs all your emails and sells them to advertisers. If it&amp;rsquo;s in the Terms of Service that the service shares non-trivial data with third parties, then that email service is garbage and you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t use it. In fact, good email providers will &lt;em>never&lt;/em> share any data without a court order first. In order to take an email provider&amp;rsquo;s claims of protecting your data seriously, the email provider should have a transparency report providing as much detail as is legal about what information they can be forced to turn over, when, and how often it actually happens.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also, email providers can&amp;rsquo;t share information about you they don&amp;rsquo;t have. If the email service provider offers anonymous sign up (they don&amp;rsquo;t request your name, address, phone number or other PII), this is a good sign. They should also offer anonymous payment mechanisms (cash or cryptocurrency). You should not provide personal information just to sign up for an email account. Any email service that requires you to probably doesn&amp;rsquo;t care very much about your privacy. For security, your email provider should use two-factor authentication to prevent your account from being stolen. In your browser, check the email service&amp;rsquo;s website for TLS 1.3. If the email service website doesn&amp;rsquo;t support TLS 1.3, that&amp;rsquo;s a bad sign. Check that they support DANE/TLSA. They should claim to encrypt the hard disks of the email server or the email accounts themselves to prohibit data theft. They shouldn&amp;rsquo;t ever send any email data unencrypted. It should always use TLS. The email service should provide you with &amp;ldquo;inbound encryption&amp;rdquo;. Inbound encryption means you can generate a keypair and provide the email service your public key to encrypt your emails with. This means the email service encrypts your emails, as they are received, on their servers with a key only you have access to. If your emails are later stolen or requested via court order, the service will only be able to provide encrypted versions of your emails unreadable to anyone except you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another good sign is if the email service supports access over Tor. The webmail client should support access over Tor Browser. It shouldn&amp;rsquo;t block tor connections. If it has an onion address, then the email service went through extra trouble for Tor support. As I said, email providers can&amp;rsquo;t share information about you they don&amp;rsquo;t have. If you connect over Tor, you are protecting your IP address. That means you don&amp;rsquo;t have to trust the email service not to log your IP when you access email.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="business-operations">Business Operations&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve gone over some of the technical details, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t mentioned the business model yet. When you sign up for an email service, you need to check how they are supporting the service financially. There&amp;rsquo;s a famous adage about online products: &amp;ldquo;If it&amp;rsquo;s free, you&amp;rsquo;re the product&amp;rdquo;. Unless your email service provider is a subscription service, donation funded or the host is just an altruist, then your emails and metadata are probably being sold to advertisers. Also you&amp;rsquo;ll want to make sure they are &amp;ldquo;well-established&amp;rdquo;. The service provider shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be too obscure. This is subjective but you probably want a few thousand other people to also be using the service. This is an indicator that the service is reliable. People want email to &amp;ldquo;just work&amp;rdquo;. If it has lots of downtime, is slow or it doesn&amp;rsquo;t work well, it won&amp;rsquo;t take long for people to switch to another service. Another indicator of reliability is that it has been around for a few years without major data breaches. If there have been data breaches, was the email service quick to respond? Do they have a dedicated 24/7 support team or help center for answering any questions you might have? If you can&amp;rsquo;t get your emails one day, will you have somebody to contact for support? A highly available, quick-to-reply support team is a good sign that the email service is competent. The email service should also have migration support. Migration support makes it easier to switch email providers if you ever want to use a different one.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nothing I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned gives you a 100% guarantee that the email provider is secure, will stay in operation, doesn&amp;rsquo;t sell your data to advertisers, or is competent. But the more criteria that the email provider meets, the better the chances that it&amp;rsquo;s a good one. At some point you have to say &amp;ldquo;Okay, this email service meets so many criteria of being ethical that it either actually operates ethically &lt;em>or&lt;/em> is so good at faking it I could never hope to tell the difference anyway&amp;rdquo;. Once you do enough research where you can confidently say that, then you should consider using it. There are other features email services provide that I haven&amp;rsquo;t mentioned such as email aliasing and email storage space. Those depend heavily on how you use email and if I listed all possible features of an email service, I&amp;rsquo;d never finish this post. But I think I have covered some of the key features to look for when choosing an email service.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="using-an-email-client">Using an Email Client&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The most common way by far to access email nowadays is using webmail which is a shame. Webmail is when you access your email account in the browser. Remember that email predates the web, so it doesn&amp;rsquo;t rely on the web at all. It&amp;rsquo;s just that people have been spoiled by web apps and never need to leave the browser environment any more. Using an email client, also known as a user agent, is a more satisfying way to use email. It provides functionality such as easy account navigation, email filtering, email flagging, calendaring, contacts, and more. Webmail also provides the same features, but often requires running proprietary Javascript to accomplish the same tasks. Using an email client gives you a single, unified user experience that you can customize to your liking for all email accounts, even if the accounts are on different email services. Using an email client empowers you to use inbound encryption, managing your encryption keys yourself. I just want to quickly mention that &lt;a href="https://protonmail.com">Protonmail&lt;/a> requires installing a proprietary &lt;a href="https://protonmail.com/bridge">bridge application&lt;/a> for IMAP and SMTP support. If you want to use Protonmail with your own email client, you&amp;rsquo;ll have to install their software. I&amp;rsquo;m not trying to pick on them in particular. I just want to point out it&amp;rsquo;s more secure to use email clients that work for &lt;em>any&lt;/em> email provider, not client programs that the specific email service has homebrewed even if they are free software programs. Individualized email clients and client-related programs likely have less code review and less scrutiny which means you&amp;rsquo;re less secure using them. Some good email clients are &lt;a href="https://www.thunderbird.net">Thunderbird&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolution_(software)">Evolution&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="http://www.mutt.org">Mutt&lt;/a> if you prefer a terminal. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft_Outlook">Microsoft Outlook&lt;/a> is common, but it is proprietary. Don&amp;rsquo;t use it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="pop3">POP3&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Since most email users have been totally spoiled by the web, they have never heard the terms POP3 and IMAP. When you use an email client, you will have a choice of which protocol you prefer. POP stands for Post Office Protocol. The first version of POP was created in 1984. POP3 fetches emails from the remote email server, then deletes them from the server. It can be configured not to do that, but that&amp;rsquo;s its main benefit. If you only check email from a single device and you don&amp;rsquo;t want your emails hanging around on someone else&amp;rsquo;s computer, then POP is the way to go. Sent emails are stored in the client you sent them. Deleted emails are only deleted in the client you deleted them in. So POP is not a good protocol if you are using multiple devices to check email. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t try to sync across devices. POP is also good to use if you have very little space allocated to you on the remote server, but you regularly send and receive large email attachments.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="imap">IMAP&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>IMAP stands for Internet Messaging Access Protocol. It was created in 1986. IMAP makes use of the remote email server. All messages are stored on the remote server. When you delete an email, it is deleted on the server. When you send an email, it is stored on the server. When you read an email, the server marks it as read. If you switch devices, your email inbox will look the same. It has a consistent experience across multiple devices. This is probably what you want to use most of the time.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="email-use-cases">Email Use Cases&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Even if you follow this guide on picking an email service and you use an email client and use 2-factor authentication and inbound encrypt all your emails and use POP3, it&amp;rsquo;s likely that your correspondents are using Gmail, Outlook and Yahoo. Even though you could have the most secure email setup short of self-hosting, everyone you email is still using proprietary Javascript with no 2FA unencrypted webmail with every email being parsed and sold to advertisers and mass surveilled. My point is don&amp;rsquo;t use email for personal correspondence. The fact is email is just an old insecure protocol. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t even use end to end encryption because it comes from a different era. You can use PGP to encrypt your emails, but it has &lt;a href="https://secushare.org/PGP">so many problems&lt;/a> that I can&amp;rsquo;t recommend it for regular use. Almost no one uses it, it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to use, and has many downsides. If you have to use email for personal or business correspondence, use PGP to encrypt. But the best advice I can give is just to avoid using email.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="email-privacy">Email Privacy&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The best time to use email is when it&amp;rsquo;s required. When you&amp;rsquo;re signing up for a website that requires email for instance. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to only have 1 email account either. I use several email aliases depending on the purpose. You can use different email accounts for every service you sign up for if you want. There&amp;rsquo;s throwaway email accounts available if you need to send or receive email quickly and then ditch the account. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t recommend using email for receiving newsletters or information that you have another way of accessing. I might make another post talking about RSS, but it&amp;rsquo;s basically a web feed. RSS readers can pull content from all the websites that support RSS that you&amp;rsquo;re interested in without you actually visiting those sites. It&amp;rsquo;s a similar experience to using an email client, but with less of a digital footprint. With email, your email server has a record of which feeds you are subscribed to. With RSS, there is no &amp;ldquo;account&amp;rdquo;. No digital footprint showing you subscribed to that feed is necessarily created. If you anonymize RSS over Tor, then even a passive adversary like your ISP will have a hard time figuring out which news feeds you read. Even if you just visit the news site directly, that&amp;rsquo;s still arguably better for your privacy in terms of minimizing your digital footprint.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="multiple-accounts">Multiple Accounts&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>In summary, the most privacy-preserving way to use email is to avoid using email for anything except website sign ups. Ironic, isn&amp;rsquo;t it? I just wrote paragraphs about the best way to use email and now I&amp;rsquo;m saying that you should avoid using it for most things. If you have the will, you can use a new email account for every site you sign up for to further enhance privacy. Using an email client will make it easier to manage so many accounts at the same time. You won&amp;rsquo;t have to reenter all your passwords every time to check your emails. If you are signed up for lots of services, this could be impractical. You might consider using several email accounts for &amp;ldquo;categories&amp;rdquo; of services instead of a separate email account for every single service you sign up for. The benefit of this is you don&amp;rsquo;t have all your eggs in one basket. If one of your email accounts gets compromised or snooped on, the others remain unaffected. Also keep in mind throwaway email services for one-off sending and receiving of emails.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If and how you segregate out your email accounts is up to you. This is just an optional extra step you can take. Using multiple email accounts doesn&amp;rsquo;t always make your emails more private or your accounts more secure. It just improves &amp;ldquo;unlinkability&amp;rdquo;. A common example of this is having a personal email and a work email. Keeping your personal life and your work life separate is important for many people. You wouldn&amp;rsquo;t want your workplace to know all the services you&amp;rsquo;re signed up for and you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t want to be receiving work emails on your personal email account.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="motivation">Motivation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Those are my tips for getting the most out of email. It&amp;rsquo;s a lot of information to take in, but I wanted to be thorough. My motivation for writing this post as I said in the beginning was seeing the way most people use email. Until we have a widespread protocol that supercedes email, we should at least get the most out of it. And the way most people are using email right now is the absolute worst way to use it. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of things in computing that aren&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em>harder&lt;/em> to do a different way, it&amp;rsquo;s just that people haven&amp;rsquo;t been shown the better way of doing things. Most people don&amp;rsquo;t know anything beyond webmail despite the fact that email predates the web. I wrote this post to promote my preferred way of using email. I hope you have found it useful.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Use Free Software</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/use-free-software/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/use-free-software/</guid><description>&lt;p>In previous posts, I have mentioned a lot about free software versus proprietary software. But I have never dedicated a standalone post to free software, so I&amp;rsquo;m doing that now. While I find the history of &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html">free software&lt;/a> fascinating, I&amp;rsquo;m not going to get into that in this post. This is more of a persuasive post. I want to convince you to use free software wherever possible &lt;em>rather than&lt;/em> &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/proprietary/">proprietary software&lt;/a>. There is a lot to be said on the subject. This post is about why you should use free software, not why you should code it. There &lt;em>are&lt;/em> plenty of incentives to code free software though. The reason I&amp;rsquo;m choosing to focus on the user is that there&amp;rsquo;s already so much free software out there, but it&amp;rsquo;s not getting anywhere near the usage it deserves.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-freelibre-software">What is Free/Libre Software?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The word &amp;ldquo;free&amp;rdquo; in &amp;ldquo;free software&amp;rdquo; means free as in freedom, not free as in price. Price isn&amp;rsquo;t the issue with free software, freedom is. For software to be free, it must have &lt;strong>the 4 essential freedoms&lt;/strong>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol start="0">
&lt;li>The freedom to run the program for any purpose.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The freedom to study how the program works and modify it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The freedom to redistribute copies of the program to others.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The freedom to distribute copies of modified versions of the program to others.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h2 id="why-does-it-matter">Why Does it Matter?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Why are the 4 freedoms important? The most &lt;em>relevant&lt;/em> answer I can give for software users is that it boils down to &lt;strong>social and economic control&lt;/strong>. The 4 freedoms prevent the developer of the software from wielding too much power over its users. I will start with freedom 0 and go one by one explaining how each freedom impacts the social system between developers and users.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="freedom-0">Freedom 0&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Freedom 0 ensures that the user can use the program however they wish. Without freedom 0, the developer of the software can impose rules about how the program may or may not be used. If you use the program in a way that the developer doesn&amp;rsquo;t approve of, then the developer may take legal action against you. This can be done with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/End-user_license_agreement">EULA&lt;/a>s (End-user license agreements). Click-wrap licenses can even prevent users from knowing there are restrictions on the program&amp;rsquo;s use until after starting the installation process. Users may be prevented from publishing performance information about the program to compare it to competitors, trying to reverse engineer the program for learning, developing plugins for the program, or any number of other legitimate uses of the program. Developers telling users what they can and can&amp;rsquo;t do with programs on their own computer gives the developer tremendous control over the users. Freedom 0 prevents this by giving the user the right to do anything with the program that they are able to get it to do (within the bounds of other applicable laws).&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="freedom-1">Freedom 1&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Programs are made up of &amp;ldquo;source code&amp;rdquo;. Source code is the developer-readable format of a program. Your average Joe could look at a program&amp;rsquo;s source code and it would look like gibberish. But a sufficiently skilled programmer could read the source code and make sense of the program. With compiled languages, developers cannot run a program from its source code. It has to be &lt;em>compiled&lt;/em> first. In summary, source code is the format the developer can understand the program and compiled code is the format the machine can actually run the program.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>After the program is compiled, it&amp;rsquo;s prohibitively difficult to make sense of the program even for developers. One strategy developers use to prevent other developers from reverse-engineering their program is to write the source code, then release only the compiled version of the program to the public. This way, only the developer can understand what the program really does and how it works. Not only that, but only they can make changes to the program. These programs are known as proprietary programs. It puts the developer in a position of power over the user and incentivizes the developer to add features that might hurt the user since the user is powerless to remove the bad features. This is also not conjecture. Proprietary programs &lt;em>often&lt;/em> have malicious anti-features that benefit the developer and hurt the users such as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_rights_management">DRM&lt;/a>, surveillance, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backdoor_(computing)">back doors&lt;/a>, censorship, &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/proprietary/proprietary-tethers.html">tethers&lt;/a> and other &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/proprietary/">tyrannical anti-features&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s possible to reverse engineer a compiled program, but it&amp;rsquo;s an extremely arduous process, especially for very large programs. Free software wants &lt;em>practical&lt;/em> freedom to understand and change the program, not freedom &lt;em>in theory&lt;/em>. Therefore, for Freedom 1 to be satisfied, the source code of the program must be distributed alongside the compiled version of the program. This ensures that anyone who uses the program has the opportunity to understand and modify it. This grants users &lt;strong>individual control&lt;/strong> over the program. With Freedom 1, developers have less incentive to add malicious anti-features since other developers might notice them. This could cause people not to use programs made by that developer and for the developer to lose respect.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Freedom 1 is necessary but incomplete. The problem is not everyone is a programmer, so not everyone has the skills to understand and modify their programs to their liking. They are still stuck with whatever the developer gives them. The freedom to study and modify the program means nothing to non-programmers. This is why we need Freedoms 2 and 3.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="freedom-2">Freedom 2&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Freedoms 2 and 3 together grant &lt;strong>collective control&lt;/strong> over the program. Freedom 2 grants the freedom to distribute exact copies of the program. If you enjoy a program, you can share it free of charge with your friends. And they can share it with their friends. Anyone who finds it useful can share it with others. If you have freedoms 0 and 1 but not 2, then you can do whatever you want with the program including studying and modifying it, but others can&amp;rsquo;t benefit because you&amp;rsquo;re not allowed to share the program. What Freedom 2 prevents is the developer having power over the users via controlling program distribution. A developer can&amp;rsquo;t do things to &lt;em>prevent&lt;/em> others from sharing the program. This means the developer is not in sole control over the distribution of the program.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As an example, Windows 10 is a proprietary operating system. An operating system is just a program that acts as a middleman (abstraction layer) between the user and the hardware. It manages system resources. Only Microsoft is allowed to distribute the Windows 10 operating system. You may not distribute it yourself. Secondarily, in order to unlock all the features of Windows 10, you have to buy a Windows 10 license from Microsoft. Microsoft is in control of the distribution of the license keys as well. If I distributed license keys for Windows 10 to others, there could be legal ramifications for me. Microsoft punishes sharing. Freedom 2 protects sharing of software with the idea that sharing is generally a good thing and should be encouraged. Sharing software isn&amp;rsquo;t like sharing physical goods. If 5 people share a pizza, everyone gets less pizza. But if 5 people use the same program, then all 5 get the full benefit of the program. The benefit I get out of using it is not degraded by sharing it with others. Software is not like a pizza. It&amp;rsquo;s more like a pizza recipe.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="freedom-3">Freedom 3&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Continuing with the pizza analogy, Freedom 1 gives you the right to change the &amp;ldquo;recipe&amp;rdquo;. You can make improvements and benefit from them. Freedom 3 lets you share your modified recipe with others so they can also benefit from your improvements. You can imagine a situation in which Freedoms 0, 1, and 2 are granted, but not 3. This would mean users can use the program any way they wish, modify it, and share exact copies, but not share modified copies. This is disastrous for collective control over the program. It would mean only the developer could make updates. &amp;ldquo;Forks&amp;rdquo; couldn&amp;rsquo;t be public. Everyone else is free to make changes, but non-programmers can&amp;rsquo;t benefit from those changes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As I said before, free software is about &lt;em>practical&lt;/em> control over the program, not control &lt;em>in theory&lt;/em>. In reality, non-programmers can&amp;rsquo;t make changes they want to make to the program because they don&amp;rsquo;t know how to code. Even among programmers, one programmer might not have the expertise to modify a program to their liking or they might not be familiar with the programming language used. So unequipped developers and users rely on other developers to make the changes they desire. Without Freedom 3, only the original developer or group of developers is allowed to distribute modified versions of the program. In other words, the original developers retain a monopoly on modifications. They could charge any price for a requested feature. If they decide to stop maintaining the project, then other developers will be powerless to continue program maintenance. Freedom 3 is necessary to enable a healthy ecosystem of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fork_(software_development)">forks&lt;/a> to suit the needs of each type of user.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Since the original developer doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a monopoly on modifications with Freedom 3, other developers can improve upon the code, add features they desire, remove features they don&amp;rsquo;t desire, and collaboratively contribute to the program. This is just not possible without Freedom 3.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="free-software-is-not-a-panacea">Free Software is not a Panacea&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>At the bare minimum of ethical standards for software, programs should be free software. Free software ensures that the social system around the software is just, that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em>automatically&lt;/em> create unjust power differentials between developers and users and between developers and others developers that &lt;em>otherwise&lt;/em> wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be there. Obviously if developer A is more skilled than developer B, developer A will be better able to modify the program to their liking. And obviously if user A is wealthy and wants feature X and user B isn&amp;rsquo;t wealthy and wants feature Y, then user A can pay developers to prioritize feature X over feature Y. Free software is not free from influence by corporate interests. The Mozilla Foundation wrote Firefox to use the Google search engine because Google funds Firefox development in return. Microsoft, the proprietary software giant, is on the Linux Foundation. Linus Torvalds has been responsible for big decisions in the mainline Linux kernel for decades. Free software doesn&amp;rsquo;t even mean development of software is democratic in practice. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benevolent_dictator_for_life">Benevolent dictator for life&lt;/a> is the title given to free software developers that get the final say in development decisions. Since the &amp;ldquo;dictator&amp;rdquo; has the majority of development inertia behind them, any developer that might think of forking the software upon a development dispute would think twice since the inertia for the project already lies behind the dictator&amp;rsquo;s fork. Free software also doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be user friendly. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to have accessibility for those that speak foreign languages or the disabled. It can even be socially harmful and still qualify as free software. Some free software may require expensive hardware that only the wealthy can afford. Accessibility is limited to the rich in that case. Free software doesn&amp;rsquo;t solve everything.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="still-use-it">Still, Use It&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Free software does not solve the problems I mentioned and it&amp;rsquo;s not meant to. The problems I described can possibly be avoided, with great care. With proprietary software, they are downright unavoidable. Proprietary software &lt;em>automatically&lt;/em> sets up an unjust social system around software. It&amp;rsquo;s a non-starter. Doomed before it even starts. There is no way to create proprietary software and have it be as ethical as free software because it doesn&amp;rsquo;t meet the basic requirements for a just social and economic system. It &lt;em>discourages&lt;/em> understanding, sharing, and collaboration. It&amp;rsquo;s no good. If you use proprietary software often, it becomes a habit. And when it becomes a habit, the developer of the software gains influence over you because they control the software you rely on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Developers of proprietary software have a &lt;em>monetary incentive&lt;/em> to mistreat their users. Anti-features can be very profitable. They have no reason not to add anti-features since others can&amp;rsquo;t understand the compiled code and won&amp;rsquo;t necessarily even know about the anti-features and couldn&amp;rsquo;t do anything about them even if they did because they&amp;rsquo;re not allowed to modify the program. Proprietary programs are instruments of unjust control over the users. Proprietary software should not exist. It should all be eradicated and replaced with free software instead. You shouldn&amp;rsquo;t tolerate it if you can at all help it. The best way you can help with the liberation of cyberspace is by switching to using as much free software as possible instead of the proprietary software you might currently be using. Free software is how we stay in control of our own computing. Without it, our devices will cease to be our own. The code we run on our devices will be under the control of developers with incentives to do us harm. We want the developers writing our software to have incentives to write software that only benefits us. If we refuse to use proprietary software and use free software instead, developers will see they can&amp;rsquo;t get away with not giving users their freedoms.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the future I envision, developers will lose all incentive to write proprietary software knowing in advance no one will use it. It won&amp;rsquo;t even cross their minds as a possibility. Right now, getting people to switch to free software is a struggle. Many proprietary programs benefit heavily from the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_effect">network effect&lt;/a>, keeping many people dependent. Free software is not even a well known social issue, &lt;em>yet&lt;/em>. But with enough awareness and with enough people using free software, the network effect will work in favor of a liberated cyberspace, not a divided, controlled, proprietary one. Computers become more integral to our way of life every day. Our devices have become extensions of ourselves. This is why it&amp;rsquo;s critical that they at least run free software. That&amp;rsquo;s the only way we can hope to trust them. Use as much free software as you can and spread the word to others. We need to take back our computing.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Networked EV Charging Stations</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/networked-ev-charging-stations/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/networked-ev-charging-stations/</guid><description>&lt;p>Eventually I want to write a separate post on why mass surveillance is stupid, dangerous, and incompatible with democracy. For those that read my blog, I&amp;rsquo;m probably preaching to the choir though. I&amp;rsquo;m going to write the rest of this post assuming the reader already understands why mass surveillance is bad, or at least sees how it could be. If you don&amp;rsquo;t understand why massive government surveillance is a problem, you think that &amp;ldquo;privacy is dead&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;I have nothing to hide&amp;rdquo; comes to mind, you should do more research on mass surveillance before continuing. With that, I&amp;rsquo;ll continue.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="electric-vehicle-charging-stations">Electric Vehicle Charging Stations&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I want to quickly cover some basics about EV charging stations for those who don&amp;rsquo;t know. There are two types of EV charging stations: networked and non-networked. The networked ones require you to sign up on the web with your real name, credit card information, address, and car make and model. You have to agree to the terms of service and privacy policy. After signing up, you receive a swipe card in the mail. Because you have to swipe an ID card to use networked charging stations, the network (Chargepoint) knows who you are, where you charged your car, when, and for how long. Non-networked charging stations don&amp;rsquo;t require you to use an ID card, so they can&amp;rsquo;t collect any personalized data on you.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="gas-stations">Gas Stations&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>EV charging stations are worse for your privacy than gas stations. With gas stations, you can pay anonymously in cash. No form of ID is necessary. While you can pay with a credit card, it&amp;rsquo;s not necessary. EV charging stations don&amp;rsquo;t allow you to pay in cash. At a minimum, there is a record of your credit card transaction to the charging network. Also, due to the swipe card you have to use for the charging station, every single charge is tied to your real identity. This means the network (Chargepoint) creates an extensive dossier on everywhere you&amp;rsquo;ve been and sells that information to data brokers. You must agree to all this or you can&amp;rsquo;t even use the charging station. You can still charge your electric vehicle at home or at non-networked charging stations, but non-networked stations are far less common than networked ones. So if your EV doesn&amp;rsquo;t have much range or you are in a rural area, you&amp;rsquo;ll definitely be going out of your way to avoid the networked stations. The only way around this is reverting back to using a gas station, if you have a hybrid car. If you have a fully electric vehicle, then you&amp;rsquo;re just out of luck.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-infrastructure-of-surveillance">The Infrastructure of Surveillance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The bad news is the worst is still yet to come. There&amp;rsquo;s not a huge opposition to networked charging stations and the issue is even lesser known than that of mass surveillance. And in the United States, if EVs are the way of the future and demand increases for them, there will need to be many more charging stations than there are now. This is bad because it&amp;rsquo;s almost certain that these new charging stations are going to be proprietary and networked, selling customer data. It will become increasingly difficult to resist the privacy invasion of our location data once the infrastructure is already in place. What are you going to do, not charge your car? Once infrastructure is already paid for, there needs to be a very strong incentive to change it. The best course of action now is to oppose the networked charging stations before they are deployed and avoid using them, even if it&amp;rsquo;s inconvenient. That&amp;rsquo;s because most of the charging stations that are going to be deployed have not yet been deployed. So, there&amp;rsquo;s still time to stop the surveillance infrastructure before it expands.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="how-to-fight-back">How to Fight Back&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>If your school or workplace wants to install a networked charging station, tell them you oppose this decision and would instead be in favor of a more privacy-respecting option such as a non-networked station. If you own an EV yourself, tell them that you will refuse to use the networked charging station because you don&amp;rsquo;t want to encourage proprietary surveillance infrastructure. You could also stick flyers on the networked charging stations calling for EV drivers not to use the networked stations, or at least to become informed about the problem and organize. Chargepoint puts out their own &lt;a href="https://www.chargepoint.com/blog/7-reasons-why-non-networked-charging-non-starter/">propoganda&lt;/a> trying to spin the surveillance off as a good thing, a myth we must dispel. The fact is all of the items on their list are doable with non-networked charging stations running free software. If you want analytics or access controls, you could imagine a cryptographic system that uses secure private tokens to protect EV driver privacy while also making analytics possible without any sign up or extra hassle to the driver. Proprietary charging station phone apps could also be avoided and replaced with free software alternatives.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://amatas.com/news/view/schneider-electric-s-vehicle-charging-station-could-be-hacked">Vulnerabilities&lt;/a> in networked charging stations have been found in the past. As everyone should know, any time there is a database containing personal data, it becomes the target of hackers. The only way to completely prevent data from being stolen or leaked in the long run is by not collecting the data in the first place. Luckily with EV charging stations, storing location data is completely unnecessary. With enough public pressure we can just do away with it entirely. We just have to show that privacy is the priority.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="siue">SIUe&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When I was attending SIUe, I emailed the parking services staff in October of 2019 about the privacy concerns I had about the new Chargepoint stations that were being installed and encouraged them to install a non-networked station instead. The reply explained that while they understood my concerns, Chargepoint is what all the public universities in Illinois are using and they determined that it would be in the best interest of their constituents to install it. I was not able to change their decision, but I got the parking services staff to at least think about the issue because a well thought-out critique demands a well thought-out response. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to see the United States turning into a nightmarish big brother surveillance hellscape where privacy is impossible and the government has such strong surveillance capability on everyone that it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;turnkey tyranny&amp;rdquo;, as Snowden would say. Networked charging stations are one step closer to that bleak reality. Don&amp;rsquo;t doubt for a second that the government can access EV charging station location data from networked charging stations. They absolutely can. Collecting the locations on millions of law-abiding citizens is a capability no government or private entity should be allowed have. Of course companies and governments get the same location data through smartphones anyway, but that must end too. One injustice doesn&amp;rsquo;t justify another. That just means we have more work to do.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="national-security-and-privacy">National Security and Privacy&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In a democracy, the people have the power to self-govern. Democracy is incompatible with mass government surveillance in the long term. What you have to realize is mass corporate surveillance &lt;em>is&lt;/em> mass government surveillance. In the United States, the federal government has the authority to force companies to turn over customer data and then not tell customers about it. The data collection and analysis often happens automatically. It is impossible to meaningfully oppose a government that has near omniscience about the entire population. All it takes is one competent, evil politician to convert a heavily surveilled democracy into a dictatorship. Obviously, networked charging stations aren&amp;rsquo;t going to do that on their own. But they are a stepping stone on a path whose destination is nigh-impossible to pull back from. Worse, foreign governments can purchase and use this location information on high-profile individuals driving electric vehicles to gain influence. Massive data collection of Americans' location is not only incompatible with American democracy by giving government far too much power (knowledge is power), but it&amp;rsquo;s also a national security threat. The very existence of a database with real-time location data points on millions of Americans is a national security threat because foreign governments and hackers will find a way to get access. The only full solution is to make sure the data is never collected in the first place, by opposing networked charging stations and organizing and informing EV drivers around the issue.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Back Up Your Data</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/back-up-your-data/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/back-up-your-data/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="losing-my-data">Losing My Data&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My motivation for writing this post is I accidentally deleted another unpublished post I put a lot of effort into. It probably had 6+ hours of work invested in it at least. And now, it&amp;rsquo;s gone forever. Perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s best put into the 5 stages of grief. At first, I denied it. I was sure I had it copied to my clipboard, saved in my text editor cache or history, but it wasn&amp;rsquo;t. After that, I got angry that I could have accidentally deleted something I put so much work into. How could I make such a dumb mistake? I skipped bargaining. I was sad about it for a while. Then I reached acceptance, and decided to write this post instead.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This post is a public service announcement about backups inspired by the one that got lost. I&amp;rsquo;ve had my own backups for over 5 years, and never have I lost any data from those backups. So I have a little bit of experience making backups. The following advice is meant for individuals, not a corporate or business setting.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-to-backup">Why to Backup?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Backups are important because hard drives fail and get corrupted, phones break and get lost, and physical media degrade. Backups can help protect your important data.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-to-backup">What to Backup?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>How do you know which data should go into your backups? Here are two quick rules of thumb:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>You would want the data back if you lost it or it corrupted (&lt;em>it&amp;rsquo;s worth something to you&lt;/em>)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Using a backup would take less time than recreating the data yourself (&lt;em>it&amp;rsquo;s worth the trouble to back up&lt;/em>)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ll use this blog as an example. It uses the Hugo software to generate the site pages. I can &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/getting-started/installing/">install Hugo&lt;/a> on any platform with a few simple commands. The cost of retrieving Hugo is &lt;em>very&lt;/em> low. If I lost it, I could recreate it by just reinstalling. I would get the latest version and it would work on whatever platform I happen to be using. If I made a standard backup, I would be stuck with the same version and the way it is packaged may not work across platforms. So, making a backup of Hugo would break rule #2 because it would take &lt;em>more time&lt;/em> to recover it from a backup than just reinstalling it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I could almost say the same about the template I&amp;rsquo;m using. Except I&amp;rsquo;ve made modifications to it to not include Goo-lag analytics and other things. I have it backed up because &lt;strong>#1&lt;/strong> I would need it back if I lost it and &lt;strong>#2&lt;/strong> making those modifications again would take longer than just restoring the template from a backup. The same goes for my site content. Rewriting it all would be a huge effort. As I write more posts, the effort only increases. So, obviously, I back up my site content because it satisfies rules #1 and #2.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For most people, data that satisfies both of these rules are going to be old home videos, vacation pictures, resumés, portfolios, financial records, contact lists and password manager files. Those are generally data that are valuable and either can&amp;rsquo;t be recreated or would be cumbersome to recreate.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="when-to-backup">When to Backup?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you don&amp;rsquo;t already have a backup, create one right now. Don&amp;rsquo;t wait. Your data could become corrupted at any time. If you don&amp;rsquo;t have copies of it elsewhere, then you&amp;rsquo;re just waiting for the inevitable to happen. Your digital media (hard drive, flash drive, SD card, CD/DVD) will eventually fail and you will lose your important data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Once you have your data backed up for the first time, you will need to create a backup schedule. A backup schedule is how often you want to back up your data. It can be weekly, monthly, yearly, etc. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be at regular intervals, but that&amp;rsquo;s good practice. This decision should be based on how frequently you acquire important data and how important the new data is. If you record your daughter or son&amp;rsquo;s first steps on video, you will want to back that up the same day or week probably. If you don&amp;rsquo;t acquire important data often, you may want a yearly backup schedule.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In my case, I have a blog. So far, I have averaged 2-3 posts per month. I put a lot of thought into my posts. Since losing just 1 post motivated me to write all of this, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to even think about losing 2-3 posts at once. Therefore I should, at minimum, perform monthly backups so that I never lose more than 2-3 posts. Redundant copies of my posts are stored on web servers and Zeronet, but those are only posts that I have deemed worthy to publish. The ones I haven&amp;rsquo;t published don&amp;rsquo;t have redundant copies, so I should still perform monthly backups. That&amp;rsquo;s an example of how to think about a backup schedule. It will be different for everyone since everyone has different backup needs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="where-to-backup">Where to Backup?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Where you back up your data is crucial. This gets into what is widely known as the 3-2-1 rule of data backups. You need 3 copies of your data, 2 types of storage media, and 1 offsite copy. You &lt;strong>must&lt;/strong> have an offsite copy in case of a disaster. If a fire breaks out in your home and you&amp;rsquo;re gone, it will destroy your computer &lt;em>and&lt;/em> your external drive. So it&amp;rsquo;s no good to only have data stored locally. Yes, you need local copies, but you must have a remote copy as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also, having 2 copies of your data on the same media does not count as 2 copies. It counts as 1 copy. One computer science student I talked to in the past did not understand that &lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RAID">RAID&lt;/a> is not a backup&lt;/strong>. One power spike and all your drives in your RAID system can fail simultaneously. It could get stolen. Do you trust yourself to never delete anything important by accident? You need &lt;em>physically&lt;/em> separate media for backups, not just &lt;em>logically&lt;/em> separate. This reduces the chance you will delete important data without catching the error first. Physically separate drives don&amp;rsquo;t count if they are connected to the same system. For example, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter if you have copies of your data on multiple cloud instances if those instances are through the same cloud provider. What if that cloud provider gets compromised and you lose both backups? So, use separate systems as well as separate drives.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And finally, you need at least one air-gapped backup. If all your accounts and machines get compromised, you need a way to recover your data. Without that, your data could be stolen and held for ransom. To avoid this scenario, set up an offline backup in a different city, state, or country. The farther, the better. Your offline backup will probably be local since you can&amp;rsquo;t access it remotely. Having a remote offline backup is inconvenient because it will be hard to maintain a frequent backup schedule. You could keep your offline backup as a micro SD card stashed between your phone and its case, or in your purse so it&amp;rsquo;s always with you. This way, your offline backup, local backup, and remote backup are in 3 physically separate locations.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="who-to-backup">Who to Backup?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s important to know who is in control of the computer your backup is sitting on. If you use a cloud service provider to back up your data remotely, there are significant caveats. The caveats apply any time you are using hardware that is not under your control.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For one, you have to trust the cloud service&amp;rsquo;s security practices. If they get compromised, your data will be at risk. Are you willing to accept that risk? What if their database gets compromised? To eliminate this risk, you should &lt;strong>always&lt;/strong> encrypt your data before uploading it. I&amp;rsquo;ll get to this topic in the next section.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another risk is that the data is modified either intentionally or by error. Encrypting the data will not prevent it from being modified maliciously. For that, you need authenticated encryption. Also, you may be limited on monthly bandwidth or file storage capacity. If you store a lot of data, that could quickly become expensive.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Using a cloud service provider, you can only access your data at their leasure. Hopefully their system has good uptime. This usually isn&amp;rsquo;t a big problem. But they will also have full control over how you access your data. They might only allow you to access it over a web portal. You&amp;rsquo;ll want to make sure they run a service you can access using only free software such as &lt;a href="https://nextcloud.com/">Nextcloud&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://www.etesync.com/">Etesync&lt;/a>. Preferably, they give you many ways to access it so you aren&amp;rsquo;t locked in to a particular client program.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-to-backup">How to Backup?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Now that I&amp;rsquo;ve covered the 5 W&amp;rsquo;s (why, what, when, where, who), I&amp;rsquo;ll cover the most important aspect of backups: How to do them. There is an endless list of software that can help with backups. One good rule is you should &lt;em>always&lt;/em> use &lt;a href="https://www.fsf.org/about/what-is-free-software">free software&lt;/a> for your backups. &lt;em>Never&lt;/em> use &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/proprietary/">proprietary software&lt;/a> for any part of the backup process. There&amp;rsquo;s no reason for it and it will compromise your backup security.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="offsite-backup">Offsite Backup&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The first part of the backup process is to decide which data you want to store. Then, you should decide how you want to handle the remote backup. If you use a VPS, you control &lt;em>how&lt;/em> you access your data, but all other caveats still apply. On a VPS, you can host your own service for the remote backup. As I said, there are a thousand ways to do this depending on your needs. If you like to keep it barebones, you can run a simple ssh server. If you are hosting a backup for more than just yourself, you may want to use an actual backup platform such as Nextcloud. There are several OS&amp;rsquo;s that are built for the express purpose of backups from &lt;a href="https://www.freenas.org/">FreeNAS&lt;/a> to &lt;a href="https://www.openmediavault.org/">OpenMediaVault&lt;/a>. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter which you choose as long as it&amp;rsquo;s meets your needs and runs free software.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="encryption">Encryption&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Once you have your offsite service set up, it&amp;rsquo;s time to perform the backup. The first thing you&amp;rsquo;ll want to do before anything else is &lt;strong>encrypt your data&lt;/strong>. For most people, you&amp;rsquo;ll want to use &lt;a href="https://www.veracrypt.fr">Veracrypt&lt;/a>. It&amp;rsquo;s user friendly and cross-platform. For a guide on how to use Veracrypt, follow the &lt;a href="https://www.veracrypt.fr/en/Beginner%27s%20Tutorial.html">beginner&amp;rsquo;s tutorial&lt;/a>. Other encryption programs require using the command-line, decrypting the data to disk before reading it, or only work on GNU/Linux. For those reasons I won&amp;rsquo;t use them in this tutorial. However, if you feel comfortable using LUKS or GPG, go ahead. Just know the trade-offs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This next step is optional, but I recommend it. Veracrypt does not perform authenticated encryption. Your data is still encrypted, but it could be maliciously changed by an attacker and Veracrypt won&amp;rsquo;t know about it. The best way to prevent this is with an HMAC. On GNU/Linux, you can do this with a single command as long as you have openssl installed. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem as easy to perform on other platforms. For your HMAC password, you can reuse your Veracrypt volume password. Copy the resulting HMAC value, then save it to a text file next to your Veracrypt container file. It should also go into your backups. When you retrieve your backups later, you can perform the HMAC operation on the downloaded container file checking that the result matches the value you saved before. This provides you file integrity. At this point, I recommend deleting unencrypted copies of your data on disk since there&amp;rsquo;s no good reason to have them around.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="finishing-up">Finishing Up&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Now your data is finally ready to go into storage. Upload the Veracrypt container file along with the HMAC text file to your remote backup system. Then copy your data onto external media such as a USB flash drive, external hard drive, or SD card. This will serve as your offline backup. You can store your third backup on the same computer you use to access and modify the data, or you can choose a different one so it&amp;rsquo;s not taking up space. That&amp;rsquo;s up to you. Just be sure to have at least 3 copies of your data, one of them at a remote location and one of them air-gapped. You could write a script to do the backups and check the HMAC for you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, you&amp;rsquo;ll want to decide on your backup schedule. To add to your backup, you can simply mount your Veracrypt container and add more files. If you ever run out of space, you can always create a larger container and transfer all your data there. I hope you found this guide useful. I didn&amp;rsquo;t go into as much detail as I could have about remote backup solutions, but I think I covered what needed to be covered.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;ve made it this far, thank you for reading. If you find my ideas valuable, then please consider making a donation. Details are on my &lt;a href="../../about#donate">about page&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>