<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>privacy on Nicholas Johnson</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/privacy/</link><description>Recent content in privacy on Nicholas Johnson</description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/privacy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>[Video] You Should Delete Your Whatsapp ASAP</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-you-should-delete-your-whatsapp-asap/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-you-should-delete-your-whatsapp-asap/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/channel/UCjr2bPAyPV7t35MvcgT3W8Q">TheHatedOne&lt;/a> tells us why no one should be using Whatsapp.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=shpiVm1qpnw&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1">[Video Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="matrix">Matrix&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The only gripe I have about the video is the same one I had in &lt;a href="../../video-fixing-social-media-for-good">Fixing Social Media for Good&lt;/a>. While &lt;a href="https://matrix.org/">Matrix&lt;/a> is &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federation_%28information_technology%29">federated&lt;/a> and infinitely better than Whatsapp, federation still tends toward centralization. Also Matrix &lt;em>doesn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> protect metadata either and as TheHatedOne mentions, leaking metadata is really bad for a communications platform even if data is protected.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="signal">Signal&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.signal.org/">Signal&lt;/a> says it protects metadata, but there&amp;rsquo;s no way for users to verify that besides taking Signal&amp;rsquo;s word for it &lt;em>and&lt;/em> Signal is centralized. So neither Signal nor Matrix are the &lt;em>final&lt;/em> solution to secure communications.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="cwtch">Cwtch&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peer-to-peer">Peer to peer&lt;/a> is the best solution because there&amp;rsquo;s no way for it to tend towards centralization. Once &lt;a href="https://cwtch.im/">cwtch.im&lt;/a> (Cwtch is Welsh for hug/cuddle) is stable it will probably be the best peer to peer instant messaging solution since it can &lt;em>verifiably&lt;/em> protect metadata and have encrypted group conversations. It&amp;rsquo;s also built on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tor_%28anonymity_network%29">Tor&lt;/a> which is the most tested, most researched and most used anonymity network out there.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Consumer Data Protection is a Distraction</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/consumer-data-protection-is-a-distraction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/consumer-data-protection-is-a-distraction/</guid><description>&lt;p>This post is a public service announcement.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-businesses-collect-data">Why Businesses Collect Data&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Businesses collect data from consumers for a variety of reasons. Data is collected to provide better customer service, provide a personalized customer experience, refine marketing strategy, derive other data, suggest new products, make predictions, recommendations and determine optimal business decisions. But as internationally renowned security technologist and author Bruce Schneier points out, &lt;a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2016/03/data_is_a_toxic.html">data is a toxic asset&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-its-dangerous">Why it&amp;rsquo;s Dangerous&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I recommend reading his &lt;a href="https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2016/03/data_is_a_toxic.html">full blog post&lt;/a>. But from just a consumer perspective, giving companies your data is dangerous for several reasons according to Schneier:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Saving it is dangerous because many people want it. Of course companies want it; that’s why they collect it in the first place. But governments want it, too. In the United States, the National Security Agency and FBI use secret deals, coercion, threats and legal compulsion to get at the data. Foreign governments just come in and steal it. When a company with personal data goes bankrupt, it’s one of the assets that gets sold.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Saving it is dangerous because it’s hard for companies to secure. For a lot of reasons, computer and network security is very difficult. Attackers have an inherent advantage over defenders, and a sufficiently skilled, funded and motivated attacker will always get in.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>That last part is important. &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;a sufficiently skilled, funded and motivated attacker will always get in&amp;rdquo;. The problem is you cannot trust corporations to keep your data safe. There aren&amp;rsquo;t exceptions to this that come to mind. Even if we suppose the data is encrypted on the server and only you control the encryption key, that&amp;rsquo;s not the case of a corporation being trustworthy to hold your data. &lt;em>They couldn&amp;rsquo;t leak it if they wanted to&lt;/em>. That&amp;rsquo;s what&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;em>trustless&lt;/em> design. The system is set up so you don&amp;rsquo;t have to trust whoever you&amp;rsquo;re doing business with. The best of systems are set up that way. It&amp;rsquo;s good for the consumer and it minimizes risk for the business.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The central reason you can&amp;rsquo;t trust businesses to keep your data safe is you don&amp;rsquo;t know how it&amp;rsquo;s being handled once it&amp;rsquo;s out of your hands. Even if the business &lt;em>claims&lt;/em> to have reasonable data protection, how can you possibly know that for sure? All it takes is 1 incompetent or malicious employee for your data to be leaked. All it takes is 1 out of date software package or 1 software vulnerability. All it takes is 1 government to steal from or coerce the business for the data. And if there&amp;rsquo;s ever a merger or acquisition then some other business acquires your data as an asset by default.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And let&amp;rsquo;s not forget data is combined with other data by data brokers to derive things about you that you didn&amp;rsquo;t explicitly share. You might think that 5 minute Youtube video of yourself doesn&amp;rsquo;t reveal too much but &lt;a href="https://github.com/daviddao/awful-ai">disturbing uses of AI&lt;/a> can be applied to it to derive information that you didn&amp;rsquo;t intend to include. And AI will only get better over time. You can&amp;rsquo;t predict the capabilities future AI will have to derive new information from your data. Even if it&amp;rsquo;s just &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metadata">metadata&lt;/a>, remember the former CIA and NSA director Michael Hayden&amp;rsquo;s statement concerning NSA bulk surveillance: &amp;ldquo;We kill people based on metadata&amp;rdquo;. &lt;strong>Put simply, consumer data protection is, has always been, and will be for the foreseeable future, a house of cards&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-to-protect-yourself">How to Protect Yourself&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The only foolproof way to protect yourself from data leaks is to &lt;strong>never give data to businesses in the first place&lt;/strong>. &amp;ldquo;Consumer data protection&amp;rdquo; is a distraction campaign. You see, the more businesses talk about &amp;ldquo;consumer data protection&amp;rdquo; the less &amp;ldquo;bandwidth&amp;rdquo; there is in public discourse to talk about &lt;em>outright refusal&lt;/em> to give up your data. Businesses can tout their data security practices all they want but it distracts from the truth which is you can just choose not to give your data to companies. We now live in a culture of &amp;ldquo;I agree&amp;rdquo; to the point that people forget they can say no to these things. Don&amp;rsquo;t consent. Don&amp;rsquo;t click &amp;ldquo;I agree&amp;rdquo; unless you&amp;rsquo;ve actually read the terms. Don&amp;rsquo;t provide identifying information without serious consideration.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And for those of you who say &amp;ldquo;I have to give &lt;a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Goolag">Goolag&lt;/a> my data! Rearranging my life to protect my data would be too hard! I need a Goolag account for my job or university or whatever the case may be.&amp;rdquo; I leave you with a quote from the Roman stoic Seneca:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s not that we don&amp;rsquo;t dare do things because they are difficult; rather, they are difficult because we don&amp;rsquo;t dare&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; Seneca&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>[Video] TikTok - a Trojan Horse into China's Dystopia</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-tiktok-a-trojan-horse-into-chinas-dystopia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-tiktok-a-trojan-horse-into-chinas-dystopia/</guid><description>&lt;p>TikTok is a national security risk and yet people are still using it &lt;em>by the millions&lt;/em>. President Trump signed an &lt;a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/executive-order-addressing-threat-posed-tiktok/">executive order&lt;/a> to ban TikTok by prohibiting United States citizens from doing business with the Chinese company ByteDance that owns TikTok. However the restrictions have been stalled in court since last August. At the time of the &lt;a href="https://newsroom.tiktok.com/en-us/tiktok-files-lawsuit">TikTok lawsuit&lt;/a> ByteDance claimed they had &lt;strong>100 million active users in the United States&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The main concern in the executive order seems to be TikTok allows the CCP to collect Americans' personal information including federal employees and it can be used for disinformation and blackmail. But as &lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/channel/UCjr2bPAyPV7t35MvcgT3W8Q">TheHatedOne&lt;/a> points out, US-based social media platforms already do the same thing. Facecrook has collected personal user data &lt;em>way&lt;/em> before TikTok was around and it has more than twice as many users today as TikTok did in August. A consequence of Facecrook&amp;rsquo;s data collection is it enabled &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facebook%E2%80%93Cambridge_Analytica_data_scandal">Cambridge analytica&lt;/a> to manipulate the US presidential election in 2016 and yet the Federal Trade Commission only fined Bookface $5 billion dollars. Bookface made $15 billion in just the first quarter of 2019. The fine was &lt;em>barely&lt;/em> a slap on the wrist.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The moral is if you&amp;rsquo;re a US-based company that endangers national security through personal data collection and manipulation of public opinion through propoganda you get a slap on the wrist from the FTC while the NSA pats you on the back. If you&amp;rsquo;re a Chinese-based company doing more or less the same you get an executive order banning you from doing business in the United States. And the 2 core issues of &lt;strong>centralization of power&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>proprietary software&lt;/strong> of which the other issues are a symptom never even get so much as a mention in the mainstream media or the government.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I recommend TheHatedOne&amp;rsquo;s commentary on TikTok because he actually addresses the proprietariness and centralization of power in the case of TikTok. Have a listen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=5UooWpC4yJs&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1">[Video Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Privacy Paradox</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/the-privacy-paradox/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/the-privacy-paradox/</guid><description>&lt;p>After the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_surveillance_disclosures_(2013%E2%80%93present)">Snowden revelations of 2013&lt;/a>, we learned that the NSA&amp;rsquo;s global internet surveillance program &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XKeyscore">XKeyscore&lt;/a> was flagging people that read&amp;hellip;&lt;a href="https://www.linuxjournal.com/content/nsa-linux-journal-extremist-forum-and-its-readers-get-flagged-extra-surveillance">Linux Magazine&lt;/a>. That&amp;rsquo;s right. The NSA would place you on a special high-priority surveillance list for taking an interest in one of the only operating systems that isn&amp;rsquo;t known to have a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backdoor_(computing)">backdoor&lt;/a>. But it didn&amp;rsquo;t end there.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can see in the &lt;a href="https://daserste.ndr.de/panorama/xkeyscorerules100.txt">XKeyscore rules&lt;/a> people that searched for &lt;a href="https://www.torproject.org/">Tor&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://tails.boum.org/">Tails OS&lt;/a> software were being targeted. These are programs written for the express purpose of anonymity and avoiding the watchful eye of Big Brother.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There seems to be a common theme here. Big Brother programs automatically targeted people that took steps to avoid surveillance. It&amp;rsquo;s a fair bet to make that people that use privacy tools are still targeted more than those who don&amp;rsquo;t. There&amp;rsquo;s one very good reason to suspect this: Big Brother doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to take a special interest in those that don&amp;rsquo;t avoid mass surveillance because mass surveillance is sufficient to build a full portrait of their lives anyway. It&amp;rsquo;s logical that Big Brother would only need to pay special attention to those avoiding mass surveillance since their privacy is harder to violate.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-paradox">The Paradox&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Thus we end up with a paradox: The more you avoid mass surveillance, the more &lt;em>interesting&lt;/em> you become to Big Brother. This increases the likelihood that you&amp;rsquo;ll end up on one of their &amp;ldquo;extra surveillance&amp;rdquo; lists and that more &lt;em>targeted&lt;/em> methods will be used on you. The less you avoid mass surveillance, the less &lt;em>interesting&lt;/em> you become to Big Brother. All else being equal, this decreases the likelihood that you&amp;rsquo;ll get special attention. Blending in with the surveilled masses might give you more anonymity and privacy, in practice. In other words, allowing yourself to be mass surveilled might act as a kind of protection against targeted surveillance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you &lt;a href="../../avoiding-consumer-surveillance">pay for everything in cash&lt;/a> where cash payments are uncommon, if you &lt;a href="../../using-email">use internet services&lt;/a> registered outside of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_Eyes">Five Eyes&lt;/a>, if you use Tor and VPNs for accessing the internet, if you use &lt;a href="../../use-free-software">free as in freedom&lt;/a> software and encrypted communication apps, if you &lt;a href="../../atom-and-rss">avoid social media&lt;/a>, if you drive a &lt;a href="../../avoiding-automobile-surveillance">privacy-friendly vehicle&lt;/a> when you can afford a newer car, you&amp;rsquo;re going to attract attention to yourself. One of these things on its own isn&amp;rsquo;t a red flag, but combined together, there&amp;rsquo;s really only one thing you can be doing: avoiding mass surveillance. One doesn&amp;rsquo;t avoid mass surveillance in today&amp;rsquo;s world by accident unless you&amp;rsquo;re amish or living in a poor country.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Knowing this, what ought you to do about it? Should you try to blend in or should you avoid mass surveillance and just not care how many watchlists you end up on?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-to-do-about-it">What to Do About It&lt;/h2>
&lt;h4 id="short-answer">Short Answer&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Trying to blend in with the surveilled populace is like giving a thief your money so they can&amp;rsquo;t steal it. If you really want to fight mass surveillance, you should take as many steps to avoid mass surveillance as you&amp;rsquo;re willing to take and don&amp;rsquo;t worry about being targeted. If enough people do this, it will &lt;a href="../../raising-the-bar-on-privacy">raise the bar on privacy&lt;/a> so that &lt;em>only&lt;/em> the more expensive targeted surveillance tools will work. Then everyone will collectively have more privacy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="long-answer">Long Answer&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>If you or someone you know is doing something illegal and you don&amp;rsquo;t want Big Brother&amp;rsquo;s attention, especially since Big Brother has been known to do nasty things such as assisting with &lt;a href="../../shining-light-on-the-dark-side-of-law-enforcement">evidence laundering&lt;/a>, you might think it&amp;rsquo;s a good idea to avoid mass surveillance &lt;em>only&lt;/em> when conducting illegal activities to avoid drawing too much attention to yourself. This strategy is ill-advised for at least two reasons:&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="reason-1">Reason #1&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>Allowing yourself to be mass surveilled on purpose some of the time is the reason the bar on privacy remains low. If all you care about is not drawing attention to yourself and your illegal activities, then fine. But if you care about wider society, then you should raise the bar on privacy by avoiding mass surveillance at &lt;em>all&lt;/em> times, not only when engaging in illegal activities.&lt;/p>
&lt;h5 id="reason-2">Reason #2&lt;/h5>
&lt;p>You contribute to the stereotype that a desire for privacy indicates nefarious activity. It empowers the surveillance state in the current iteration of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crypto_Wars">crypto wars&lt;/a> because Big Brother can say that anonymity networks are mainly used for criminal purposes. If it can be shown for instance that 90% of Tor traffic is used for legal activities then it&amp;rsquo;s (theoretically) much harder for the government to make the case that it should be censored because of drug dealers, money launderers, pedophiles and terrorists.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The only long-term winning strategy for all society is to avoid mass surveillance as much as possible with the hope that others will follow suit. This is true whether you&amp;rsquo;re a law-abiding citizen or a criminal mastermind.
To drive this point home, I&amp;rsquo;ll end with a quote by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Snowden">Edward Snowden&lt;/a> from his interview with John Oliver on Last Week Tonight:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;You shouldn’t change your behavior because a government agency somewhere is doing the wrong thing. If we sacrifice our values because we’re afraid, we don’t care about those values very much.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>This quote was taken from the context of taking dick pics, but it can be equally applied here: Don&amp;rsquo;t accept mass surveillance as reality just because the government might target you for it.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Avoiding Automobile Surveillance</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/avoiding-automobile-surveillance/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/avoiding-automobile-surveillance/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="internetification-of-everything">Internetification of Everything&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Over the past few decades, there has been increasing &amp;ldquo;internetification&amp;rdquo; of everything. The &lt;a href="https://stallman.org/articles/internet-of-stings.pdf">Internet of Stings&lt;/a> has infected refrigerators, watches, televisions, and even light bulbs. As it turns out, shoehorning internet connected computer chips with &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/proprietary/">proprietary&lt;/a> code into everything increases their attack surface making society more vulnerable to &lt;a href="https://www.wired.com/2015/07/jeep-hack-chrysler-recalls-1-4m-vehicles-bug-fix/">hacking groups&lt;/a>, foreign governments and Big Brother.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Automobiles are no exception. They&amp;rsquo;ve also seen increased internetification. My own personal opinion is cars don&amp;rsquo;t need wireless enabled computer chips, period. And I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/is-apples-carplay-a-kille_b_4905981">not the&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://blog.1871.com/blogs/howard-a-tullman/tullman-why-smart-cars-are-stupid-2">only person&lt;/a> to think connected cars seem like a bad idea.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For this post, I want to focus on avoiding mass surveillance of automobiles. None of the recommendations in this post apply to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On-board_diagnostics#Vehicle_telematics">work vehicles&lt;/a> or car rentals since you don&amp;rsquo;t own those. This guide is &lt;em>only&lt;/em> for your own personal vehicle.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="dont-buy-a-connected-car">Don&amp;rsquo;t Buy a Connected Car&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>My first piece of advice is don&amp;rsquo;t buy a connected car. By connected car I mean a car with wireless capability other than radio. Buy an old car instead. Old cars predate the connected features of new cars. Ideally buy a car that doesn&amp;rsquo;t support wifi, bluetooth or cellular connections. If it has a touchscreen it&amp;rsquo;s probably too new. If you need navigation, you can buy a cheap car phone mount and use your phone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you already own a connected car, the best advice I can give is to trade it in for an old car. Until then read the owner&amp;rsquo;s manual and find out how to deactivate as many of the connected features as you can. &lt;strong>Never pair your phone with your car&lt;/strong>. Disable bluetooth and cellular connections on the car if possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="eliminate-remote-diagnostics">Eliminate Remote Diagnostics&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Unfortunately even some old vehicles have remote diagnostics systems that collect and transmit vehicle sensor data wirelessly to the dealership, insurer, manufacturer or &lt;a href="https://stallman.org/glossary.html#thug">thugs&lt;/a>. I&amp;rsquo;ll cover these by category starting with the dealership.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="dealership-tracking">Dealership Tracking&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Automotive dealerships have &lt;a href="https://www.spireon.com/gps-auto-tracking/">GPS tracking devices&lt;/a> attached to cars primarily to prevent theft. When you buy a car, assume it has one and make the dealership agree to remove it as part of the terms of purchase before you buy the vehicle. Once you&amp;rsquo;ve bought the car from the dealership, there&amp;rsquo;s no reason they need GPS tracking on it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The exception of course is if you bought the car on a loan. Then either the dealership or the lender may require the GPS tracker on the car until it&amp;rsquo;s fully paid for. In that case you can remove the GPS tracker yourself or have it removed after the car is fully paid for.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="insurer-tracking">Insurer Tracking&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Car insurers promote &lt;a href="https://www.carzing.com/blog/car-insurance/car-insurance-tracking-devices/">remote telematics devices&lt;/a> to policyholders in exchange for lower rates. They use the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On-board_diagnostics">OBD interface&lt;/a> in your vehicle to send real-time data to the insurer. Empowering Big Brother in exchange for cheaper rates isn&amp;rsquo;t worth it. Don&amp;rsquo;t let your insurer install tracking devices in your car. If your insurer requires them, find a new insurer.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="manufacturer-tracking">Manufacturer Tracking&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>General Motors includes &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OnStar#Use_as_surveillance_device">OnStar&lt;/a> in its vehicles. OnStar is a telematics device capable of not only remotely surveilling GM vehicles, but also listening to live audio inside the car and remotely shutting the car down. Even if you don&amp;rsquo;t have a subscription, OnStar can still track your GM vehicle. In fact they tracked vehicles that weren&amp;rsquo;t even subscribed to OnStar services until they &lt;a href="https://www.consumerreports.org/cro/news/2011/09/gm-reverses-decision-on-onstar-privacy-policy/index.htm">reversed the decision&lt;/a> due to public outcry from privacy advocates. Luckily there are plenty of guides online for &lt;a href="https://www.wikihow.com/Deactivate-OnStar">how to remove OnStar&lt;/a> so they can&amp;rsquo;t possibly track you.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>SiriusXM also collects telematics. Unlike OnStar, there&amp;rsquo;s no way to remove it I&amp;rsquo;m aware of. You can cancel your subscription, but SiriusXM can still collect telematics. The only solution is &lt;strong>don&amp;rsquo;t buy a vehicle that has telematics providers you can&amp;rsquo;t remove&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="thug-tracking">Thug Tracking&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Big Brother can also demand telematics information about your car from any of the above categories. This isn&amp;rsquo;t theoretical. It happened with &lt;a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3295672-SiriusXM-Satellite-Radio-Tech-Turned-Into.html">SiriusXM&lt;/a>. Thugs have used &lt;a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3295668-Coleman-Motion-to-Suppress-Denied.html">OnStar&lt;/a> several times to remotely shutdown car engines. &lt;a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/3295666-ATX-Technologies-vs-US-Monitoring-of-in-Car.html">ATX technologies&lt;/a> was forced to provide thugs with a live audio feed from inside a car.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Thugs are still allowed to put trackers on cars with a warrant. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to tell you how to spot covert thug GPS trackers. That&amp;rsquo;s avoiding &lt;em>targeted&lt;/em> surveillance which is out of the scope of this post. This post is only about avoiding &lt;em>mass&lt;/em> automobile surveillance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="safeguarding-onboard-diagnostics">Safeguarding Onboard Diagnostics&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Onboard diagnostics systems (OBD) in vehicles were introduced in the 1980s. The USA, EU and other countries have mandated &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On-board_diagnostics#OBD-II">OBD-II&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On-board_diagnostics#EOBD">EOBD&lt;/a> protocols for all vehicles sold.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="emissions-testing">Emissions Testing&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>If you have a gasoline engine and you&amp;rsquo;re in the United States, OBD data is pulled from your vehicle when you get mandatory emissions testing unless you get standard tailpipe emissions testing done. To find out if you can get only standard tailpipe emissions testing, you&amp;rsquo;ll have to call and ask local emissions testing sites and check state regulations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the emissions testing site uses proprietary OBD scanning software, then it&amp;rsquo;s possible that your data gets collected and sold to insurance companies by the OBD software vendor. If the testing site uses a handheld OBD scanner, it&amp;rsquo;s still &lt;em>possible&lt;/em> that the data is eventually pulled off and sold if the handheld scanner connects to vendor software on an internet connected computer. The OBD-II interface has &lt;code>Mode $09&lt;/code> which retrieves uniquely identifiable information like the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vehicle_identification_number">VIN number&lt;/a>. So if the OBD data does get sold, the data brokers know exactly whose vehicle it belongs to.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve never heard of OBD data being involved in a data breach before. I don&amp;rsquo;t have any information about what software is used by emissions testing sites. I&amp;rsquo;m just speculating. The only reason I have for thinking OBD data collection does happen at emissions testing sites through software vendors is because it can and it&amp;rsquo;s profitable. Even if my speculation is true, you still have to get emissions testing done. I only mention emissions testing data collection for completeness and awareness, not because you can do anything besides political activism to prevent it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="auto-repair-shops">Auto Repair Shops&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>When you take your car to a repair shop, one of the first things they&amp;rsquo;re going to do is check the OBD-II interface for error codes. It&amp;rsquo;s the same issue as before with emissions testing. The uniquely identifiable OBD data is exposed to potentially proprietary programs used by the car repair shop.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The difference is you don&amp;rsquo;t have much choice in emissions testing. When it comes to auto repair, you have some choice. There are &lt;a href="https://github.com/fenugrec/freediag">free software diagnostic tools for OBD-II&lt;/a> that don&amp;rsquo;t collect and sell your data. You&amp;rsquo;ll need &lt;a href="http://freediag.sourceforge.net/Supported-Interfaces.html#supported">an adapter&lt;/a> supported by your vehicle to use them. It&amp;rsquo;s up to you to make sure the adapter will work before you buy it. If you want to repair your vehicle yourself, then that&amp;rsquo;s the end of it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you need the auto repair shop to repair your vehicle, you can relay the results retrieved from your free software tools to them while requesting they don&amp;rsquo;t use their own proprietary OBD scanning tools.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="networked-electric-vehicle-charging-stations">Networked Electric Vehicle Charging Stations&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This section only applies to fully electric and hybrid cars. I&amp;rsquo;ve already made a post about &lt;a href="../../networked-ev-charging-stations">networked EV charging stations&lt;/a>. Just so this post is self-contained, I&amp;rsquo;ll reiterate:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>There are two types of EV charging stations: networked and non-networked. The networked ones require you to sign up on the web with your real name, credit card information, address, and car make and model. You have to agree to the terms of service and privacy policy. After signing up, you receive a swipe card in the mail. Because you have to swipe an ID card to use networked charging stations, the network (Chargepoint) knows who you are, where you charged your car, when, and for how long. Non-networked charging stations don’t require you to use an ID card, so they can’t collect any personalized data on you.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Don&amp;rsquo;t use the networked charging stations. Use the non-networked ones or just use your own charging cable instead.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="automatic-license-plate-readers">Automatic License Plate Readers&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Automatic license plate readers or &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/pages/automated-license-plate-readers-alpr">ALPRs&lt;/a> are cameras that capture all license plate numbers that pass by. There isn&amp;rsquo;t anything you can do about these besides political activism against them. Purposely obscuring your plates from these cameras might be illegal or cause you to get tickets. Even if there&amp;rsquo;s nothing you can do, I still think it&amp;rsquo;s important to be aware of ALPRs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="consumer-surveillance">Consumer Surveillance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It may be possible to infer where you drive based on consumer surveillance alone. As a final piece of advice to further improve your vehicle&amp;rsquo;s location privacy, follow the tips in my post on &lt;a href="../../avoiding-consumer-surveillance">avoiding consumer surveillance&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="political-action">Political Action&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When I make posts on how to avoid surveillance, what I&amp;rsquo;m trying to do is build resistance to tools of mass surveillance. At the end of the day there needs to be both technological and political changes to protect drivers' data. I offer temporary workarounds for avoiding surveillance until the dangerous trend of increased surveillance reverses itself. Society needs to start being &lt;em>proactive&lt;/em> rather than &lt;em>reactive&lt;/em> to corporate and government surveillance. I don&amp;rsquo;t know when or how or if the trend of increased surveillance will be reversed, but I&amp;rsquo;ll continue writing about ways to resist surveillance until I no longer need to.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At some point resisting mass surveillance becomes impractical. I understand my advice isn&amp;rsquo;t always easy to follow. Choosing privacy can get expensive and time-consuming. And it&amp;rsquo;s already hard enough to get people to use anti-surveillance tools that are &lt;em>easy&lt;/em> to use, let alone follow a guide like this that requires lots of effort. Part of the function of these posts is to show the ridiculous lengths one must go for privacy in today&amp;rsquo;s world. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to follow all the steps in this guide. My practical advice is just do what you can. Remember, if all you do is cancel your insurance tracking, that&amp;rsquo;s a win for privacy and a blow to Big Brother.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you have any more details or suggestions that I missed send me an &lt;a href="mailto:nicholasjohnson@posteo.org">email&lt;/a>. If you want to help support my site &lt;a href="../../about#donate">send a donation&lt;/a>. I hope you found this post valuable.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Shining Light on the Dark Side of Law Enforcement</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/shining-light-on-the-dark-side-of-law-enforcement/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/shining-light-on-the-dark-side-of-law-enforcement/</guid><description>&lt;p>The US constitution is &lt;em>supposed&lt;/em> to protect citizens from &lt;a href="https://stallman.org/glossary.html#thug">thug&lt;/a> overreach. However, &lt;strong>evidence from the past decade shows that thugs have been stomping all over our civil liberties daily by colluding with intelligence agencies&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The federal government does this by constructing lies about how agents discover information. For example if the government discovers a crime through illegal mass surveillance or another covert surveillance program, it can&amp;rsquo;t use that evidence &lt;em>directly&lt;/em> because that would violate the 4th amendment and expose Big Brother. Instead, &amp;ldquo;hints&amp;rdquo; are passed on to thugs so they can construct a &amp;ldquo;parallel&amp;rdquo; chain of evidence that &lt;em>can&lt;/em> be used in court. This is where it gets the name &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parallel_construction">parallel construction&lt;/a>. Parallel construction sounds like innocuous jargon from an architecture course, so I prefer to call the practice by the more descriptive name, &lt;strong>evidence laundering&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Evidence laundering prevents defendants in criminal cases from knowing about infringements of their rights. It makes challenging thugs' actions in court very difficult, making a mockery of the right to a fair trial. The motivation for thugs to respect a defendant&amp;rsquo;s rights is that evidence obtained illegally cannot be used in court. With evidence laundering, the illegal evidence is converted into legal evidence. Therefore the motivation not to violate citizen&amp;rsquo;s rights goes away, so long as thugs can keep citizens from proving it occurred. Even if a defendant in a criminal trial suspects evidence laundering, it&amp;rsquo;s nigh impossible to prove. This puts minorities and political activists at risk of having their rights violated without even knowing it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Moreover, &lt;strong>evidence laundering undermines the civil liberties of every citizen&lt;/strong>. It is not a technique for enforcing the law. One cannot simultaneously subvert the law and enforce it. It&amp;rsquo;s just a tool for government-aided vigilantism. It will only continue to erode citizens' constitutional rights as government surveillance programs expand. It &lt;em>must&lt;/em> be outlawed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Find more information about evidence laundering at &lt;a href="https://www.hrw.org/report/2018/01/09/dark-side/secret-origins-evidence-us-criminal-cases">hrw.org&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Get an Anonymous Phone Number with DTMF.io</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/get-an-anonymous-phone-number-with-dtmf.io/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/get-an-anonymous-phone-number-with-dtmf.io/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I am not in any way affiliated with &lt;a href="https://dtmf.io/">DTMF.io&lt;/a>. I was not paid to write this (I wish). If I am paid to write about something, I will always disclose it. I will never write things I do not agree with for money. I just happen to think &lt;a href="https://dtmf.io/">DTMF.io&lt;/a> is a good service and people ought to know about it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="purpose">Purpose&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>One reason I feel compelled to write about privacy and anonymity is there are so many poorly researched guides out there that don&amp;rsquo;t offer real anonymity, but advertise that they do. Existing guides either have a &lt;a href="../../use-free-software">freedom&lt;/a> issue, privacy issue, or other issue which makes them less than ideal. &lt;a href="https://dtmf.io/">DTMF.io&lt;/a> really impressed me, so I decided to share it with all of you. Also, I plan on writing a guide on anonymous ecommerce in the future. When I do that, this post will make a good reference since a phone number is required in many cases when doing ecommerce.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sometimes I get asked why I insist on such high standards of anonymity, privacy and freedom in everything. What on earth kind of threat model do I have to insist on such high standards? No, I don&amp;rsquo;t possess state secrets or anything of that level. If I did, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be blogging about Big Brother since Big Brother is probably on the list of keywords that gets flagged by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_federal_agencies_in_the_United_States">3 letter agencies&lt;/a>. My philosophy on this actually aligns pretty closely with &lt;a href="https://stallman.org/">Richard Stallman&lt;/a>. I&amp;rsquo;m just very ethically motivated. Specifically, it&amp;rsquo;s a matter of preserving my &lt;a href="../../use-free-software">freedom&lt;/a> and resisting Big Brother. It&amp;rsquo;s not just that &lt;em>I&lt;/em> want to resist Big Brother. I think &lt;em>everyone&lt;/em> ought to hold high standards like I do in order to &lt;a href="../../raising-the-bar-on-privacy">raise the bar on privacy&lt;/a> and protect democracy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="problems-with-existing-anonymous-phone-number-guides">Problems with Existing Anonymous Phone Number Guides&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ll begin by pointing out a few problems with existing guides out there for obtaining an anonymous phone number. Let&amp;rsquo;s take a look at &lt;a href="https://www.appsverse.com/blog/heres-how-to-get-an-untraceable-phone-number/">appsverse&lt;/a> as a case study. Their first method for getting an untraceable phone number is a burner phone.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="why-not-use-burner-phones">Why Not Use Burner Phones?&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>There are 3 major problems that come to mind with burner phones:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>They are &lt;a href="https://www.androidauthority.com/owning-smartphone-human-environment-cost-656030/">materially wasteful&lt;/a>. All the effort that went into manufacturing the burner phone and it&amp;rsquo;s just going to be used temporarily, perhaps just once, then become e-waste. They&amp;rsquo;re bad for the environment.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>They run &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/proprietary/">proprietary&lt;/a> operating systems and software. This is bad for your freedom. Because of their freedom issues, there&amp;rsquo;s no way to ensure they don&amp;rsquo;t covertly surveil you. The whole point is that they&amp;rsquo;re supposed to be anonymous, so this is kind of self-defeating.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You&amp;rsquo;ll need to remove the batteries or put the phone in a faraday bag when you aren&amp;rsquo;t using it. Turning it off isn&amp;rsquo;t effective since you might accidentally hit the power button. Since we&amp;rsquo;re trying to preserve the number&amp;rsquo;s anonymity against Big Brother, it can&amp;rsquo;t ping nearby cell towers at places you&amp;rsquo;re associated with. You can&amp;rsquo;t send or receive sms or calls unless you take it out of the bag, so you&amp;rsquo;ll have to only use it at a remote location. Going to a remote location just to make a call or check your messages is very inconvenient.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h4 id="just-hide-my-caller-id">Just Hide My Caller ID?&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The second method appsverse suggests is hiding your caller ID. This isn&amp;rsquo;t anonymous against Big Brother so we can disregard it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="what-about-apps">What About Apps?&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Method 3 is phone apps. Appsverse recommends phoner, which is a proprietary app that give you burner phone numbers. The problem is &lt;em>most&lt;/em> of these apps are proprietary and you should never install them. Don&amp;rsquo;t go through the Goo-lag Play Store or crApple App Store looking for burner phone number apps. Almost all of them are proprietary garbage. Another example is &lt;a href="https://www.burnerapp.com">Burnerapp.com&lt;/a>. It&amp;rsquo;s proprietary and requires your name, email and phone number tied to your real identity. Also, there&amp;rsquo;s no way to pay anonymously. How can your phone number be truly anonymous if you have to identify yourself to get it?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sms-privacy">SMS Privacy&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://smsprivacy.org/">SMSPrivacy.org&lt;/a> is worth a mention. You can send and receive sms messages over a web interface. The sign up process doesn&amp;rsquo;t require providing any personal information. It has a &lt;a href="http://smspriv6fynj23u6.onion/">v2 onion address&lt;/a> and doesn&amp;rsquo;t require Javascript which is always a plus. The only gripe I have is the price. 0.0015 BTC per day per phone number is asking too much for most people. It&amp;rsquo;s even more expensive for a physical phone number that you can use to sign up for websites.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="introducing-dtmfio">Introducing DTMF.io&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://dtmf.io/">DTMF.io&lt;/a> is the best service I&amp;rsquo;ve come across for an anonymous phone number. Like SMS Privacy, it can be accessed over a web portal. There is no third party Javascript. The web portal is available in several languages. It requires no &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personally_identifiable_information">personally identifiable information&lt;/a> (PII) to sign up and supports 2-factor authentication. Unlike SMS Privacy, it has a more reasonable price tag. It has a &lt;a href="http://dtmfiovjh42uviqez6qn75igbagtiyo724hy3rdxm77dy2m5tt7lbaqd.onion/">v3 onion address&lt;/a> for Tor. It supplies landline, mobile, SIM mobile and toll-free phone numbers from all over the world. You can pay with Bitcoin, Lightning, Ethereum, Litecoin, Monero and Perfect Money. Monero support is a huge plus since it&amp;rsquo;s the only cryptocurrency with private payments by default. You can also make calls using SIP or your web browser. SIP is convenient because it allows you to bypass &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/javascript-trap.html">the Javascript trap&lt;/a> of using the web portal. Like SMS Privacy, it does not &lt;em>require&lt;/em> you to enable Javascript in the browser for sign up or sms, although calling won&amp;rsquo;t work without it. DTMF.io has an API available to pro and business customers allowing automated account control, sms and calling. Their &lt;a href="https://dtmf.io/terms">terms of service&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://dtmf.io/privacy">privacy policy&lt;/a> seem reasonable enough. You can&amp;rsquo;t expect much privacy using sms anyway, which is why I can&amp;rsquo;t recommend using it for very much except maybe website sign up and only if it&amp;rsquo;s required. I also recommend you avoid sharing PII using your anonymous number. Keep in mind a social graph could still be constructed of which numbers you&amp;rsquo;re contacting and at what time. To reduce linkability, you should use a different number for each website you sign up for, if you can afford it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I know I criticized using apps for an anonymous number before, but that&amp;rsquo;s because they are proprietary. DTMF.io supports SIP. So, you can use free (as in freedom) SIP calling apps to make calls or you can use the official free (as in freedom) &lt;a href="https://dtmf.io/app">DTMF.io app&lt;/a> for sms and calling currently available on Android. You can build it from source for Android, iOS, Windows, Mac and GNU/Linux. Voice calls aren&amp;rsquo;t currently supported in Windows or GNU/Linux though. It does not require Goolag Play Services and only asks for permissions it needs. It will even work without camera, microphone or contacts permissions enabled.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The only recommendation I&amp;rsquo;d make if you plan on using it is that you pay anonymously and don&amp;rsquo;t provide an identifying email address on sign up. Also, if you use the Android app, you should proxy the connection over a VPN or Tor (with &lt;a href="https://guardianproject.info/apps/org.torproject.android/">Orbot&lt;/a>) that way the service never gets your real IP address. Use Tor Browser with the onion address to access it over the web. Other than that I don&amp;rsquo;t know what more you can ask for. The other anonymous phone number services (except for SMS Privacy) either don&amp;rsquo;t allow you to pay anonymously, require identifying information, have proprietary Javascript, or some other problem that makes them unsuitable. As far as I can tell, DTMF.io is the only game in town for a cheap, ethical, anonymous phone number. If you&amp;rsquo;re using anything else, you should definitely make the switch.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Stop Amazon's Police State</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/stop-amazons-police-state/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/stop-amazons-police-state/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="amazons-orwellian-surveillance-hellscape">Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Orwellian Surveillance Hellscape&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Amazon is providing police departments with warrantless access to thousands of Ring doorbell cameras&lt;/strong> giving cops unpredecented, persistent surveillance capabilities of private homes and neighborhoods. This is yet another dangerous partnership between &lt;a href="https://stallman.org/amazon.html">the empire of the megacorporations&lt;/a> and the state.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Police don&amp;rsquo;t even need probable cause to request the Ring camera footage. If the &amp;ldquo;owner&amp;rdquo; of the camera refuses to share footage with the police, the real owner (Amazon) can provide the footage anyway. There are no safeguards and there&amp;rsquo;s no accountability in place to protect the footage. &lt;strong>This persistent dragnet neighborhood video surveillance is incompatible with democracy and must be stopped.&lt;/strong> Sign the petition at &lt;a href="https://www.cancelring.com/">www.cancelring.com&lt;/a> and tell your local officials to cancel these partnerships that violate our basic civil liberties.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This petition focuses on ending Amazon+Police partnerships, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t go far enough. Amazon Ring cameras should not be allowed to exist. &lt;strong>Ring doorbell cameras are an instrument of Big Brother whether or not there is a formal partnership between local police departments and Amazon.&lt;/strong> If someone you know uses one of these cameras, show them the petition and ask them to remove the camera from their home. &lt;strong>Good neighbors don&amp;rsquo;t set up persistent, warrantless Big Brother surveillance of their neighborhood.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Avoiding Consumer Surveillance</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/avoiding-consumer-surveillance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/avoiding-consumer-surveillance/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-age-of-surveillance">The Age of Surveillance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We live in the age of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surveillance_capitalism">surveillance capitalism&lt;/a>. Intimate data about us is collected, bought and sold for profit and social control. Intermediaries like banks, payment companies, credit card companies and governments have unprecedented access into our private lives through our purchases. This level of surveillance is tyrannical. &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/surveillance-vs-democracy.en.html">Mass surveillance is dangerous to the health of democracy and must be stopped&lt;/a>. Big Brother should not know what we buy. In this post, I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk about how we avoid consumer surveillance. In a future post, I&amp;rsquo;ll talk about anonymous online shopping and some promising software projects that could be a more permanent remedy to consumer surveillance. Ultimately, there is going to have to be political action to curtail surveillance, not just new technology. But until there is increased awareness of mass surveillance and real political action against it occurs, all we can hope to do is avoid the surveillance. So here&amp;rsquo;s how you do that.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="always-pay-cash">Always Pay Cash&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This is the golden rule. To avoid surveillance, you should always pay in cash. &lt;strong>Never use a credit or debit card. Never use Google Pay, Apple Pay, Cash App, Samsung Pay, Paypal, Circle Pay, Venmo, Square Cash, Zelle, Facebook Messenger, or any other payment app. Reject online shopping unless you can remain anonymous. Don&amp;rsquo;t shop at Amazon, Ebay, or other online marketplaces that require you to identify yourself.&lt;/strong> Is always paying in cash inconvenient? Maybe. That depends on how reliant you are on online shopping. Is it possible? Definitely. Is it worth it? Absolutely. Paying cash even once helps resist surveillance. Even though Big Brother would love to see a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cashless_society">cashless society&lt;/a> where all your purchases are fully transparent, we aren&amp;rsquo;t in that dystopian nightmare yet. If a merchant refuses to accept your cash, then find another merchant that will take cash. You&amp;rsquo;ll be anonymous and you&amp;rsquo;ll create economic pressure against a cashless society. If the story ended there, I&amp;rsquo;d just end this post now. But it&amp;rsquo;s not that easy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="avoid-disloyalty-programs">Avoid Disloyalty Programs&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Paying in cash is &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Necessity_and_sufficiency">necessary but not sufficient&lt;/a> for anonymous purchases. Just because you pay in cash doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you&amp;rsquo;re anonymous. Retailers have come up with clever ways to trick you into deanonymizing yourself even when you pay cash. They&amp;rsquo;re called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loyalty_program">loyalty programs&lt;/a>. Here&amp;rsquo;s how their dirty scheme works: An &amp;ldquo;operator&amp;rdquo; asks you if you&amp;rsquo;re already signed up for the rewards program. If you say no, they ask you if you want to sign up. If you agree, then they begin asking you for personally identifying information about yourself like your name, address, and phone number. Things they have absolutely no business knowing that are irrelevant to the transaction you&amp;rsquo;re performing. Once you cough up your information, they give you a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cashback_reward_program">rewards card&lt;/a>, otherwise known as a points card, advantage card, or club card. On all your future purchases, you use your loyalty card and earn &amp;ldquo;points&amp;rdquo; which gives you future discounts and deals. The catch is they link all your purchases with your identity and then sell that data to data brokers. I call them disloyalty cards because you&amp;rsquo;re being disloyal to your fellow citizens by tacitly approving of consumer surveillance. Disloyalty programs are only loyal to Big Brother. Every time you use them, you make it harder for other people to reject them. You&amp;rsquo;re voting for surveillance with your money. Others that don&amp;rsquo;t submit themselves to the unjust surveillance may have to pay fees of up to 10% for not being signed up. &lt;a href="https://www.samsclub.com/">See Sam&amp;rsquo;s Club&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Even if the disloyalty program doesn&amp;rsquo;t require you to give any personal information to sign up, it can still be used to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linked_data">link&lt;/a> your purchases together. When your &amp;ldquo;buyer profile&amp;rdquo; gets sold and combined with other data, it&amp;rsquo;s trivially easy to deanonymize your purchases. Let&amp;rsquo;s say you sign up for a disloyalty card that doesn&amp;rsquo;t require giving your personal information. The items purchased and time and date of purchase are all linked on your disloyalty card. Useless information on its own. But then the supermarket you buy from sells your &amp;ldquo;buyer profile&amp;rdquo; to &lt;a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Goolag">Goolag&lt;/a> who compares your location history from your phone to the disloyalty card data. The supermarket has 3,000 customers that use a disloyalty card, but only 1 customer has a location history that matches the times and dates that the card made purchases. That&amp;rsquo;s you. And just like that, your purchases are deanonymized. But you&amp;rsquo;re clever. You turn your phone off before you go to the store. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter. Goolag correlates the time at which your phone turns off with the time of the purchases. You&amp;rsquo;re deanonymized again. Let&amp;rsquo;s say you don&amp;rsquo;t even have a mobile phone. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter. You drive a car to the supermarket. A private &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/pages/what-alpr">automatic license plate reader&lt;/a> company records your license plate number as you drive to the store and sells that data to Goolag. Goolag correlates your driving times with the card purchase times and now all your purchases going back years are deanonymized. So you &lt;em>walk&lt;/em> to the supermarket with your disloyalty card instead of driving. That won&amp;rsquo;t help you either. &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/pages/face-recognition">AI-powered facial recognition cameras&lt;/a> all over the supermarket identify you and the times you&amp;rsquo;re there. The company that makes those cameras sells that data to Goolag. Goolag correlates the times again and your purchases are deanonymized. So you go to a &lt;em>different supermarket&lt;/em> with a different disloyalty card. You don&amp;rsquo;t have a phone. You walk there. There are no surveillance cameras inside. How could you possibly be deanonymized now? Your bandwidth usage on your home network is low while you&amp;rsquo;re gone at the store. Your ISP sells this data to Goolag who correlates it with your card and you&amp;rsquo;re deanonymized again.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Just pay a little extra to avoid the disloyalty card.&lt;/strong> Refusing disloyalty cards also protects the anonymity of others. If you use a disloyalty card, then you might shrink the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anonymity">anonymity set&lt;/a> of others not using a card. Whether others have consumer privacy is not your choice to make. You won&amp;rsquo;t get the discount but so what? At least everything you buy won&amp;rsquo;t be in a searchable database.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="dont-identify-yourself-to-merchants">Don&amp;rsquo;t Identify Yourself to Merchants&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Some places of business won&amp;rsquo;t offer you a disloyalty card, but they will ask for &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personally_identifiable_information">personally identifiable information&lt;/a> (PII) like your name and phone number. The crux of the problem with consumer surveillance is identifying yourself to the merchant. Never identify yourself. Yes, disloyalty cards identify you. All payment methods besides cash identify you. But also giving any information about yourself that gets put into a computer system identifies you. &lt;strong>If the merchant demands you identify yourself during a purchase where you would not otherwise be identified, then don&amp;rsquo;t do it.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, it makes more sense to use a credit or debit card for airline tickets and car rentals because they demand ID anyway. I would still recommend paying cash that way your bank and credit card company don&amp;rsquo;t automatically see that you rented a car, the make and model, where and when you rented it and how much it costed. Sure you&amp;rsquo;re already identifying yourself to the rental company. Your purchase is already being recorded in a database, but you can still minimize the &lt;em>number&lt;/em> of databases it&amp;rsquo;s stored in by paying cash. At least all your identified purchases won&amp;rsquo;t be in a single centralized database that&amp;rsquo;s easy to get at. They&amp;rsquo;ll have to be aggregated by data brokers first. So I&amp;rsquo;m going to reiterate the golden rule: &lt;strong>always pay cash.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="resisting-intrusive-surveillance">Resisting Intrusive Surveillance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Despite always paying cash and never explicitly identifying yourself, big retailers can still identify you through more intrusive means of surveillance. I&amp;rsquo;ve already hinted at this in talking about disloyalty programs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="facial-recognition-technology">Facial Recognition Technology&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Surveillance cameras combined with facial recognition technology can uniquely identify you and the items you buy. The best way to combat this is to find smaller stores that don&amp;rsquo;t have surveillance cameras. It&amp;rsquo;s also not a bad idea to let the store owner or management know you choose their store over big retailers because they offer more privacy. If that&amp;rsquo;s not practical for you, then be sure to wear a mask in the big retailers and a hat that covers your face from overhead cameras. One of the few good things that has come from Covid-19 is that it&amp;rsquo;s now socially acceptable to wear masks inside stores. Wearing a mask simultaneously makes you harder to identify by facial recognition technology and prevents the spread of coronavirus.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are other ways you can be deanonymized through video surveillance besides facial recognition, but there&amp;rsquo;s not much you can do about them. For that reason, I&amp;rsquo;m not going to cover them. Just know that they exist and that they have to be addressed through political action, not personal choices.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="wifi-location-tracking">Wifi Location Tracking&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The other way that big retailers have become more invasive is through wifi location tracking of your smartphone. Your phone emits wifi signals to determine which wireless networks are available nearby. The person operating the retailer&amp;rsquo;s wifi network can use those signals to track your movements within the store. It&amp;rsquo;s profitable to collect your movement data, so you should assume that retailers are doing it. Your phone also has a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MAC_address">MAC address&lt;/a> which can &lt;em>uniquely&lt;/em> identify you, especially if your phone doesn&amp;rsquo;t randomize it. Other wireless protocols that you leave activated on your phone might also be able to be misused by the retailer to track your movements. To avoid location tracking altogether, you can fully power down your phone before you enter the store. If that isn&amp;rsquo;t good enough for you, another option is placing your phone inside a &lt;a href="https://privacypros.io/faraday-bags/">faraday bag&lt;/a>. Be sure to test it out before you use it though.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="anonymous-online-shopping">Anonymous Online Shopping&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We have grown accustomed to the luxury of having whatever we want show up at our doorstep with the click of a button. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to say no when you&amp;rsquo;ve gotten so used to it. For those who really don&amp;rsquo;t want to give up online shopping, I&amp;rsquo;m going to write a guide on how to anonymously buy and sell goods online. There&amp;rsquo;s a few different methods for 100% anonymous online shopping. Some of them get very involved, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to save all the details for another post. See ya next time!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Raising the Bar on Privacy</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/raising-the-bar-on-privacy/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/raising-the-bar-on-privacy/</guid><description>&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s a common attitude many people have regarding privacy. I&amp;rsquo;m not talking about &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Nothing_to_hide">nothing to hide&lt;/a>, although that is also a very common attitude. It has been refuted &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ad_nauseam">ad nauseum&lt;/a> by privacy advocates, so I won&amp;rsquo;t do it again here. I&amp;rsquo;m talking about the feeling people have that the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surveillance_state">corporate/government surveillance state&lt;/a> (Big Brother) will collect their data one way or another no matter what, so there&amp;rsquo;s no point in even trying to avoid mass surveillance. Privacy is already dead. Mass surveillance and its &lt;a href="https://www.socialcooling.com/">long-term negative side-effects&lt;/a> are inevitable. That&amp;rsquo;s the attitude of so many people and it&amp;rsquo;s disappointing. So, I&amp;rsquo;m going to offer an alternative way to think about privacy and surveillance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, let&amp;rsquo;s be clear. &lt;strong>Privacy is not just a personal preference. It&amp;rsquo;s not just a social necessity either. It&amp;rsquo;s a biological necessity as basic as breathing. It allows us all to be human. It is the right to be imperfect. Therefore, it &lt;em>must&lt;/em> be protected. There is no point in asking if it&amp;rsquo;s too late to stop mass surveillance because there&amp;rsquo;s no alternative to curtailing it. It must be stopped&lt;/strong>. &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/surveillance-vs-democracy.en.html">Democracy can only withstand so much surveillance&lt;/a>. Mass surveillance in its current form and true democracy &lt;em>cannot&lt;/em> coexist indefinitely. Surveillance tools combined with &lt;a href="https://github.com/daviddao/awful-ai">AI&lt;/a> will only get more powerful as time passes. To put it frankly, we are either going to reign in mass surveillance or democracy will perish. We have to reject the defeatist excuse that we&amp;rsquo;ve already lost to mass surveillance and so we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t even try to restore privacy. That&amp;rsquo;s just a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-fulfilling_prophecy">self-fulfilling prophecy&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The alternative, yet realistic way of thinking (as opposed to defeatism) that I want to introduce is what I call &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;raising the bar on privacy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>. It&amp;rsquo;s a very simple idea. Maybe Big Brother can still get our data even if we take steps to increase our privacy. Even if the defeatist is right that our data can or will be collected anyway, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t make it as difficult as possible. Let&amp;rsquo;s not hand over our data on a silver platter at least, right? If enough of us take steps to increase our privacy, we will make it &lt;em>more difficult and more expensive&lt;/em> for Big Brother to collect our data. We collectively &amp;ldquo;raise the bar on privacy&amp;rdquo;. Even if we can&amp;rsquo;t fully insulate our own lives from Big Brother, if we can force Big Brother to resort to the more powerful means of surveillance (think &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zero-day_(computing)">0-day exploits&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Targeted_surveillance">targeted surveillance&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hardware_backdoor">hardware/firmware backdoors&lt;/a>) more often instead of the low-hanging fruit of collecting our data from big tech companies, then our society will gain several benefits:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>As privacy-friendly tools gain popularity, people that use them won&amp;rsquo;t become especially &amp;ldquo;interesting&amp;rdquo; to Big Brother anymore.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The desire for privacy won&amp;rsquo;t be viewed as a cause for suspicion of wrongdoing, but instead as a basic biological need that everyone is entitled to.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The perception of increased privacy on its own will cause individuals to speak and act more freely, reducing &lt;a href="https://www.socialcooling.com">social cooling&lt;/a> and making it easier to speak out against mass surveillance.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Big Brother will be forced into using more powerful surveillance tools more frequently to collect the same data it already does, thus increasing its public exposure.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.html">Free software&lt;/a> will become more widespread since it&amp;rsquo;s a necessary precondition for digital privacy.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/proprietary/proprietary.html">Proprietary software&lt;/a> will become less widespread since people will use free software in its place.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>To sum up this post in a way that makes sense to security-minded people: our minimum acceptable lower bound for a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Threat_model">threat model&lt;/a> should be avoiding mass surveillance so that we raise the bar on privacy.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Networked EV Charging Stations</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/networked-ev-charging-stations/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/networked-ev-charging-stations/</guid><description>&lt;p>Eventually I want to write a separate post on why mass surveillance is stupid, dangerous, and incompatible with democracy. For those that read my blog, I&amp;rsquo;m probably preaching to the choir though. I&amp;rsquo;m going to write the rest of this post assuming the reader already understands why mass surveillance is bad, or at least sees how it could be. If you don&amp;rsquo;t understand why massive government surveillance is a problem, you think that &amp;ldquo;privacy is dead&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;I have nothing to hide&amp;rdquo; comes to mind, you should do more research on mass surveillance before continuing. With that, I&amp;rsquo;ll continue.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="electric-vehicle-charging-stations">Electric Vehicle Charging Stations&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I want to quickly cover some basics about EV charging stations for those who don&amp;rsquo;t know. There are two types of EV charging stations: networked and non-networked. The networked ones require you to sign up on the web with your real name, credit card information, address, and car make and model. You have to agree to the terms of service and privacy policy. After signing up, you receive a swipe card in the mail. Because you have to swipe an ID card to use networked charging stations, the network (Chargepoint) knows who you are, where you charged your car, when, and for how long. Non-networked charging stations don&amp;rsquo;t require you to use an ID card, so they can&amp;rsquo;t collect any personalized data on you.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="gas-stations">Gas Stations&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>EV charging stations are worse for your privacy than gas stations. With gas stations, you can pay anonymously in cash. No form of ID is necessary. While you can pay with a credit card, it&amp;rsquo;s not necessary. EV charging stations don&amp;rsquo;t allow you to pay in cash. At a minimum, there is a record of your credit card transaction to the charging network. Also, due to the swipe card you have to use for the charging station, every single charge is tied to your real identity. This means the network (Chargepoint) creates an extensive dossier on everywhere you&amp;rsquo;ve been and sells that information to data brokers. You must agree to all this or you can&amp;rsquo;t even use the charging station. You can still charge your electric vehicle at home or at non-networked charging stations, but non-networked stations are far less common than networked ones. So if your EV doesn&amp;rsquo;t have much range or you are in a rural area, you&amp;rsquo;ll definitely be going out of your way to avoid the networked stations. The only way around this is reverting back to using a gas station, if you have a hybrid car. If you have a fully electric vehicle, then you&amp;rsquo;re just out of luck.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-infrastructure-of-surveillance">The Infrastructure of Surveillance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The bad news is the worst is still yet to come. There&amp;rsquo;s not a huge opposition to networked charging stations and the issue is even lesser known than that of mass surveillance. And in the United States, if EVs are the way of the future and demand increases for them, there will need to be many more charging stations than there are now. This is bad because it&amp;rsquo;s almost certain that these new charging stations are going to be proprietary and networked, selling customer data. It will become increasingly difficult to resist the privacy invasion of our location data once the infrastructure is already in place. What are you going to do, not charge your car? Once infrastructure is already paid for, there needs to be a very strong incentive to change it. The best course of action now is to oppose the networked charging stations before they are deployed and avoid using them, even if it&amp;rsquo;s inconvenient. That&amp;rsquo;s because most of the charging stations that are going to be deployed have not yet been deployed. So, there&amp;rsquo;s still time to stop the surveillance infrastructure before it expands.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="how-to-fight-back">How to Fight Back&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>If your school or workplace wants to install a networked charging station, tell them you oppose this decision and would instead be in favor of a more privacy-respecting option such as a non-networked station. If you own an EV yourself, tell them that you will refuse to use the networked charging station because you don&amp;rsquo;t want to encourage proprietary surveillance infrastructure. You could also stick flyers on the networked charging stations calling for EV drivers not to use the networked stations, or at least to become informed about the problem and organize. Chargepoint puts out their own &lt;a href="https://www.chargepoint.com/blog/7-reasons-why-non-networked-charging-non-starter/">propoganda&lt;/a> trying to spin the surveillance off as a good thing, a myth we must dispel. The fact is all of the items on their list are doable with non-networked charging stations running free software. If you want analytics or access controls, you could imagine a cryptographic system that uses secure private tokens to protect EV driver privacy while also making analytics possible without any sign up or extra hassle to the driver. Proprietary charging station phone apps could also be avoided and replaced with free software alternatives.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://amatas.com/news/view/schneider-electric-s-vehicle-charging-station-could-be-hacked">Vulnerabilities&lt;/a> in networked charging stations have been found in the past. As everyone should know, any time there is a database containing personal data, it becomes the target of hackers. The only way to completely prevent data from being stolen or leaked in the long run is by not collecting the data in the first place. Luckily with EV charging stations, storing location data is completely unnecessary. With enough public pressure we can just do away with it entirely. We just have to show that privacy is the priority.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="siue">SIUe&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When I was attending SIUe, I emailed the parking services staff in October of 2019 about the privacy concerns I had about the new Chargepoint stations that were being installed and encouraged them to install a non-networked station instead. The reply explained that while they understood my concerns, Chargepoint is what all the public universities in Illinois are using and they determined that it would be in the best interest of their constituents to install it. I was not able to change their decision, but I got the parking services staff to at least think about the issue because a well thought-out critique demands a well thought-out response. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to see the United States turning into a nightmarish big brother surveillance hellscape where privacy is impossible and the government has such strong surveillance capability on everyone that it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;turnkey tyranny&amp;rdquo;, as Snowden would say. Networked charging stations are one step closer to that bleak reality. Don&amp;rsquo;t doubt for a second that the government can access EV charging station location data from networked charging stations. They absolutely can. Collecting the locations on millions of law-abiding citizens is a capability no government or private entity should be allowed have. Of course companies and governments get the same location data through smartphones anyway, but that must end too. One injustice doesn&amp;rsquo;t justify another. That just means we have more work to do.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="national-security-and-privacy">National Security and Privacy&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In a democracy, the people have the power to self-govern. Democracy is incompatible with mass government surveillance in the long term. What you have to realize is mass corporate surveillance &lt;em>is&lt;/em> mass government surveillance. In the United States, the federal government has the authority to force companies to turn over customer data and then not tell customers about it. The data collection and analysis often happens automatically. It is impossible to meaningfully oppose a government that has near omniscience about the entire population. All it takes is one competent, evil politician to convert a heavily surveilled democracy into a dictatorship. Obviously, networked charging stations aren&amp;rsquo;t going to do that on their own. But they are a stepping stone on a path whose destination is nigh-impossible to pull back from. Worse, foreign governments can purchase and use this location information on high-profile individuals driving electric vehicles to gain influence. Massive data collection of Americans' location is not only incompatible with American democracy by giving government far too much power (knowledge is power), but it&amp;rsquo;s also a national security threat. The very existence of a database with real-time location data points on millions of Americans is a national security threat because foreign governments and hackers will find a way to get access. The only full solution is to make sure the data is never collected in the first place, by opposing networked charging stations and organizing and informing EV drivers around the issue.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>SIUe Cyberstalking Feature</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/siue-cyberstalking-feature/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/siue-cyberstalking-feature/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.siue.edu/search/people.shtml">https://www.siue.edu/search/people.shtml&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This lesser-known feature has existed for at least 2 years and probably much longer than that. I emailed their &lt;a href="mailto:help@siue.edu">helpdesk&lt;/a> several times pointing out the search feature could be abused by cyberstalkers and data mined. I pointed out that it should require authentication and not be open to the public internet. It&amp;rsquo;s a huge risk for student privacy and safety. Anyone can find any student&amp;rsquo;s full name, area of study, rank, home address, phone number and university email. A week later, I still have no response.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A quick search reveals that other university&amp;rsquo;s student directories generally don&amp;rsquo;t include the student&amp;rsquo;s rank, home address, or phone number. SIUe should at least remove the home address and phone number fields from public view.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Exposing Zoom</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/exposing-zoom/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/exposing-zoom/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="foreword">Foreword&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>I often feel like my posts can come off as preachy. So this post is going to be a different than usual. This time, I want to include more facts. This post is for the people that don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily share my opinion that all software should be free (as in freedom). My hope is that this will speak to a wider audience.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="scale-and-growth">Scale and Growth&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>To start off, I want to give you an idea of the scale of Zoom. Zoom is a video and audio conferencing platform for desktop and mobile devices. According to &lt;a href="https://blog.zoom.us/wordpress/2020/04/22/90-day-security-plan-progress-report-april-22/">Zoom&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a> from 22 April 2020, Zoom CEO Eric S. Yuan said in a webinar that Zoom has surpassed 300 million daily Zoom meeting participants. This does not mean that Zoom has 300 million active daily users, but 300 million participants in Zoom calls daily. For example, one user may participate in several Zoom meetings and be double-counted. So the 300 million does not correspond to the number of users. Nonetheless, 300 million is no small number. For comparison, the U.S. population is estimated to be &lt;a href="https://www.census.gov/popclock/">about 329 million&lt;/a> during the time of this writing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But Zoom didn&amp;rsquo;t always have such a huge user base. The Coronavirus pandemic causing people to work from home is what skyrocketed their numbers. According to Zoom&amp;rsquo;s Blog post, &amp;ldquo;Usage of Zoom has ballooned overnight - far surpassing what we expected when we first announced our desire to help in late February. This includes over 90,000 schools across 20 countries that have taken us up on our offer to help children continue their education remotely. To put this growth in context, as of the end of December last year, the maximum number of daily meeting participants, both free and paid, conducted on Zoom was approximately 10 million. In March this year, we reached more than 200 million daily meeting participants, both free and paid. We have been working around the clock to ensure that all of our users new and old, large and small can stay in touch and operational&amp;hellip;our platform was built primarily for enterprise customers large institutions with full IT support. These range from the world’s largest financial services companies to leading telecommunications providers, government agencies, universities, healthcare organizations, and telemedicine practices&amp;rdquo;. Eric S. Yuan. (2020, April 1). Retrieved May 24, 2020 from Zoom, Zoom blog, &lt;a href="https://blog.zoom.us/wordpress/2020/04/01/a-message-to-our-users/">https://blog.zoom.us/wordpress/2020/04/01/a-message-to-our-users/&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="terms-of-service">Terms of Service&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;ACCESSING THE ZOOM WEBSITE OR BY UTILIZING THE ZOOM SERVICES YOU AGREE TO BE BOUND BY THESE TERMS OF SERVICE AND ALL EXHIBITS, ORDER FORMS, AND INCORPORATED POLICIES&amp;rdquo; &lt;em>Terms of Service&lt;/em>. (2020, April 13). Retrieved May 23, 2020 from Zoom, Zoom terms of service website, &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/terms">https://zoom.us/terms&lt;/a>. This means that even using the Zoom website or web app instantly binds you to the terms of service of Zoom whether you know about it or not. Section 2d.i states that you are prohibited from reverse engineering Zoom services. Since Zoom is proprietary, you can&amp;rsquo;t investigate the source code to figure out what it&amp;rsquo;s doing. Worse than that, the terms of services denies you to even try to figure out how Zoom works or what it does behind the scenes or help anyone else do so. This means that independent security audits of Zoom software are not possible unless Zoom gives up their source code. Therefore, any of the claims Zoom makes about security, encryption, data protection or privacy are impossible to verify without breaking the law. You just have to take their word on it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>According to section 2d.iv, you may not transmit materials that infringe intellectual property. This means if you have music playing in the background of a Zoom call or a movie playing on your television on in the background, you could be breaking Zoom&amp;rsquo;s terms of service without even trying. Section 2d.vi says you cannot &amp;ldquo;use the Services to communicate any message or material that is harassing, libelous, threatening, obscene, indecent, would violate the intellectual property rights of any party or is otherwise unlawful, that would give rise to civil liability, or that constitutes or encourages conduct that could constitute a criminal offense, under any applicable law or regulation&amp;rdquo; &lt;em>Terms of Service&lt;/em>. (2020, April 13). Retrieved May 23, 2020 from Zoom, Zoom terms of service website, &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/terms">https://zoom.us/terms&lt;/a>. I&amp;rsquo;m not a lawyer so I can&amp;rsquo;t interpret this, but the language seems to place broad restrictions on what you are allowed to say over Zoom. Section 15 also says you cannot use Zoom while in a &amp;ldquo;high-risk&amp;rdquo; environment.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In section 7d, the terms say that Zoom &amp;ldquo;content&amp;rdquo; can be turned over to law enforcement. Section 2b seems to define content as anything that is transmitted from you to Zoom. For example, audio, video, text messages, etc. including metadata is all accessible to law enforcement at any time.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="privacy-policy">Privacy Policy&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/privacy">privacy policy&lt;/a> is always where it gets interesting for tech behemoths. So let&amp;rsquo;s dive in. Here is a list of data Zoom collects: account owner name, billing name, address, payment method, phone number, language, password, title, department, cloud recordings, instant messages, files, whiteboards, voice mails, and &amp;ldquo;other information shared while using the service&amp;rdquo;. This is mostly data that you explicitly give to Zoom. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at the technical data that you may not even know you are giving Zoom: IP address (who you are online), MAC address (unique to your device), &amp;ldquo;other device ID&amp;rdquo;, device type, operating system type and version, client version, type of camera, microphone or speakers, connection type, the nearest city you are in, whether you use VoIP, mobile or desktop client, whether you join with video on or off, if your meeting has a password or waiting room or allows screen sharing, how long the meeting was, your email or other identifying information, join and leave time, name of the meeting, date and time of the meeting, chat status, and call data records. For a service that claims to protect user privacy and not sell data to advertisers, that&amp;rsquo;s a lot of non-essential data being collected.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="recordings">Recordings&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The recordings section is explaining that anyone in a Zoom call can record a meeting on their local device and save it and that Zoom acknowledges they have no control over this. Despite this, Zoom Phone makes it easier for customers to record calls. &amp;ldquo;Zoom Phone allows customers to record phone calls, receive voice mail recordings, and obtain transcripts of voicemail, all which may contain personal information and also be stored in our cloud&amp;rdquo;. &lt;em>Privacy Policy&lt;/em>. (2020, March 29). Retrieved May 23, 2020 from Zoom, Zoom privacy policy website, &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/privacy">https://zoom.us/privacy&lt;/a>. Creating the transcripts happens automatically which means that the audio data of a call is fed into some automated system which has to listen to the call to create the transcript.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="attention-tracking">Attention Tracking&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The section on attention tracking in the Privacy Policy explains that if the host of the meeting is sharing their screen, they can activate a feature called &amp;ldquo;attention tracking&amp;rdquo;. This means the host can see whether or not the participants have the Zoom window open or are doing something else. This gives whoever the host might be (employers, teachers, etc.) power to invade the participants' computers (employees, students, etc.) to check if they are paying attention or not. Zoom does not give participants any kind of forewarning that what they are doing on their own computers is being monitored and sent to the host other than it being buried in the Privacy Policy which, let&amp;rsquo;s be real, nobody reads. And even if people did read it, they still are not in a position to understand the significance of some of the data collected on them like IP address, MAC address, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s peculiar how Zoom website obviously tries to give the overwhelming impression that you can trust the software, yet it&amp;rsquo;s against their terms of service to reverse engineer it and their own privacy policy shows they collect enormous amounts of data that isn&amp;rsquo;t strictly necessary or relevant to video conferencing. Do they really need your MAC address or know which OS you&amp;rsquo;re using? But not only does Zoom obtain data when you are using Zoom. They obtain data from you even when you are not using their service.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Their own privacy policy says they collect data about you from Google Analytics and Google Ads. Google analytics can run in your browser as Javascript that watches what you do and collects data on you as you browse the web. If you don&amp;rsquo;t know how to block Javascript, Google Analytics could be watching you in the background on any website without you even knowing it&amp;rsquo;s there. Zoom also collects data from &amp;ldquo;Data Enrichment Services&amp;rdquo;, and public sources. This could be just about anything from your social media accounts to arrest records. One way this is done is through tracking cookies.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="cookies-policy">Cookies Policy&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>On the &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/cookie-policy">Cookie Policy page&lt;/a>, it starts off explaining how cookies work. Essentially, cookies are any data a site can store in the browser. They can persist across browsing sessions and unfortunately they are used to track you across the web. I want to pay special attention on the Cookie Policy page to the analytics subtype under functional cookies. &amp;ldquo;Zoom uses cookies and other identifiers to gather usage and performance data&amp;hellip;This includes cookies from Zoom and from third-party analytics providers&amp;rdquo;. &lt;em>Cookie Policy&lt;/em>. (2020, January 1). Retrieved May 23, 2020 from Zoom, Zoom cookie policy website, &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/cookie-policy">https://zoom.us/cookie-policy&lt;/a>. Notice the important line about how they use third-party analytics providers. How is it possible for Zoom to ensure your data is protected if they use third party analytics providers of which they don&amp;rsquo;t control the data? It&amp;rsquo;s not. We know Zoom uses Google Analytics, and we know that Google&amp;rsquo;s business model is centered around collecting data on its users and selling it for profit.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Despite claiming they protect your data, they have advertising cookies. The interest-based advertising section states &amp;ldquo;Zoom uses cookies to collect data about your online activity and identify your interests so that we can provide advertising that is most relevant to you. You can opt out of receiving interest-based advertising from Zoom as described in the How to Control Cookies section of this cookie policy and in our Privacy Policy. Users who opt out of the “sale” of their personal information won’t receive interest-based advertising from us on their device. Note: If you opt out of interest-based advertising, we store your opt-out preference in a cookie on your device&amp;rdquo;. Retrieved May 23, 2020 from Zoom, Zoom cookie policy website, &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/cookie-policy">https://zoom.us/cookie-policy&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is a lot there. They collect interest-based data on you automatically. That is, unless you opt-out. Notice it&amp;rsquo;s not opt-in. The default is collecting your data. You have to know it&amp;rsquo;s happening and then choose to opt out which a lot of the more non-technical users of Zoom aren&amp;rsquo;t going to figure out how to do. I personally find it condescending how they put &amp;ldquo;sale&amp;rdquo; in quotes like that&amp;rsquo;s not exactly what they&amp;rsquo;re doing. Further, when you opt out, the fact that you want opted out is stored in a cookie. So if you try to clear tracking cookies from your browser, you might accidentally clear the cookie which says you don&amp;rsquo;t want to be tracked. This also means if you switch browsers or devices, or ever clear your browser cookies, the preference is forgotten and you have to remember to reactivate it every single time. And until you do, you are being tracked by Zoom cookies. Even if you opt-out, there&amp;rsquo;s no guarantee that Zoom doesn&amp;rsquo;t enable a feature to get the same information out of you a different way without using cookies. Again, it&amp;rsquo;s impossible to know because it&amp;rsquo;s against terms of service to reverse engineer Zoom.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Some of our websites and Products include code snippets provided by social media companies that can sense if you are already logged into a given social media account so you can easily share Zoom content with other social media users via that account&amp;rdquo;. Retrieved May 23, 2020 from Zoom, Zoom cookie policy website, &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/cookie-policy">https://zoom.us/cookie-policy&lt;/a>. This means sites like Facebook and Google know you are using Zoom services and what page you are on. Social media sites use tracking cookies to track what websites you visit. Social media sites shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be allowed to know that. Nevertheless, they are found on Zoom&amp;rsquo;s website and services, the videoconferencing platform that &amp;ldquo;cares about your privacy&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="third-parties">Third Parties&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Zoom gives your data to third parties. On their &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/subprocessors">subprocessors page&lt;/a>, they list the following third parties which they give your data to: People.ai, Zendesk, Wootric, Totango, Answerforce, Rocket Science Group LLC, Five9, EPS Ventures, WKJ Consultancy, Salesforce, CyberSource, Adyen, Zuora, Amazon Web Services, Oracle America Inc, and Bandwidth. We will ignore the 3 third parties related to billing (CyberSource, Adyen, and Zuora) since if you&amp;rsquo;re not paying Zoom it probably doesn&amp;rsquo;t apply to you. That still leaves 13 subprocessors each with their own privacy policies and their own third parties. You can see very quickly how the amount of third parties your data is being shared with grows exponentially. 11 of the 13 relevant third parties are under US jurisdiction. Since the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Snowden#Global_surveillance_disclosures">2013 Snowden leaks&lt;/a>, We know that the U.S. government performs massive dragnet surveillance on US-based companies without any oversight, so it&amp;rsquo;s probably safe to say that the U.S. government is collecting Zoom data from either Zoom itself or Zoom subprocessors.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="weasel-words">Weasel Words&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Here, Zoom is trying to weasel out of the fact that they are selling your data: &amp;ldquo;As described in the Zoom marketing sites section, Zoom does use certain standard advertising tools on our marketing sites which, provided you have allowed it in your cookie preferences, sends personal data to the tool providers, such as Google. This is not a “sale” of your data in the sense that most of us use the word sale&amp;hellip;It is only with the recent developments in data privacy laws that such activities may fall within the definition of a “sale”&amp;rdquo;. Retrieved May 23, 2020 from Zoom, Zoom Privacy Policy website, &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/privacy">https://zoom.us/privacy&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sadly, Zoom&amp;rsquo;s privacy policy is right. When Zoom gives your data to Google, they are not &amp;ldquo;selling&amp;rdquo; your data in the traditional sense that most people understand the word sale to mean. The part Zoom left out is this. Most people wouldn&amp;rsquo;t understand it as a sale because you&amp;rsquo;re not paying for the service with money. You&amp;rsquo;re paying with your data which is far worse. Zoom &lt;em>allows&lt;/em> Google to collect and sell your data and in return, Zoom receives services from Google such as analytics without &lt;em>explicitly&lt;/em> paying Google for it. Put simply, Zoom pays for Google services with your data. You are the product. Google gets the valuable data to sell, and in return they process it and make it available to Zoom to improve their software or whatever else. This has been Google&amp;rsquo;s business model for a very long time now and just because most customers don&amp;rsquo;t think of the word &amp;ldquo;sale&amp;rdquo; that way doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t expand their definition if they understood the business model.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is tantamount to saying &amp;ldquo;Zoom isn&amp;rsquo;t really selling customer data because customers don&amp;rsquo;t understand Zoom&amp;rsquo;s business model&amp;rdquo;. That way Zoom can confidently say they aren&amp;rsquo;t selling customer data misleading customers to think that their data is safe. It&amp;rsquo;s absurd. The &lt;em>essence&lt;/em> of what Zoom is doing is a sale. It&amp;rsquo;s a value transaction of customer data for service. If that isn&amp;rsquo;t a sale I don&amp;rsquo;t know what is. They also use the word &amp;ldquo;standard&amp;rdquo; to make you feel safer. Standard doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean secure. Google analytics and social media tracking cookies may be standard, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean they are good, or even acceptable. It&amp;rsquo;s an example of the bandwagon fallacy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="citizen-lab-findings">Citizen Lab Findings&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>I already mentioned how Zoom must provide data to the U.S. government, a member of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Five_Eyes">the Five Eyes&lt;/a>. But Zoom provides data to China as well. &lt;a href="https://citizenlab.ca/2020/04/move-fast-roll-your-own-crypto-a-quick-look-at-the-confidentiality-of-zoom-meetings/">Citizen Lab&lt;/a>, an interdisciplinary laboratory at the University of Toronto, reported several troubling findings on 3 April 2020. I&amp;rsquo;ll just go over the key findings and expand on them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Zoom claimed to use AES-256 in their &lt;a href="https://zoom.us/docs/doc/Zoom-Security-White-Paper.pdf">security whitepaper&lt;/a>, however Citizenlab found that they actually use AES-128 in ECB mode. Anyone that knows about block cipher modes knows that ECB mode is not suitable for video conferencing. Citizen Lab included the classic example of the &lt;a href="https://citizenlab.ca/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/image1.png">ECB penguin&lt;/a>, which is why you don&amp;rsquo;t use ECB mode for large files. Any audio or video conferencing over ECB would be as secure as the penguin image on the right, not very secure. Worse yet, the encryption keys were found to be generated by Zoom servers in China even when all meeting participants were outside of China. So the Chinese authorities could get the keys and decrypt Zoom communications of children in K-12 classrooms, U.S. courts using Zoom, meetings between government officials, college students, and everyday Americans as well as non-Americans and other countries that used Zoom.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Citizen Lab also shows Zoom advertising their use of &lt;a href="https://citizenlab.ca/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/image4.png">end-to-end encryption&lt;/a>. End-to-end encryption means only the communicating parties are able to decrypt the communication. Clearly, with the encryption keys generated on the Zoom server itself, that&amp;rsquo;s not possible. Zoom can decrypt your communications. Citizen Lab also claims that they found a &amp;ldquo;serious security issue&amp;rdquo; with Zoom&amp;rsquo;s waiting room feature, advising users not to use waiting rooms if they care about meeting confidentiality.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="fbi-warnings">FBI Warnings&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>On 30 March 2020, &lt;a href="https://www.fbi.gov/contact-us/field-offices/boston/news/press-releases/fbi-warns-of-teleconferencing-and-online-classroom-hijacking-during-covid-19-pandemic">Boston FBI&lt;/a> issued a warning about using Zoom. According to the warning by Setera (30 March 2020) &amp;ldquo;The FBI has received multiple reports of conferences being disrupted by pornographic and/or hate images and threatening language&amp;rdquo;. This is followed by advice of what to do to prevent Zoom-bombing. But Zoom is not innocent in this because it was possible to scan for random meetings to join. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t strike me as a very useful or necessary feature. Zoom is for teleconferencing. Most meetings will have a specific purpose and the participants don&amp;rsquo;t want random people joining in to disrupt the meeting. So it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense to me why this was a feature in the first place. To make matters worse, the FBI report explains Zoom didn&amp;rsquo;t have passwords enabled by default for meetings until January 2020.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="zooms-response">Zoom&amp;rsquo;s Response&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>It wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be fair for me to criticise Zoom without also pointing out steps they have taken to address the platform&amp;rsquo;s many problems. First, I want to focus on their April 1st &lt;a href="https://blog.zoom.us/wordpress/2020/04/01/a-message-to-our-users/">blog post&lt;/a>. Eric S. Yuan claims (April 1, 2020) &amp;ldquo;Thousands of enterprises around the world have done exhaustive security reviews of our user, network, and data center layers and confidently selected Zoom for complete deployment&amp;rdquo;. I would like a full list of these enterprises so I know not to trust their &amp;ldquo;security reviews&amp;rdquo;. Frankly, 128-bit AES in ECB mode is an embarrassing rookie mistake. It basically only happens when you don&amp;rsquo;t know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing. Just looking at Zoom&amp;rsquo;s track record of horrible security and privacy that I&amp;rsquo;ve outlined above, I don&amp;rsquo;t see how thousands of &amp;ldquo;exhaustive security reviews&amp;rdquo; could miss so much.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In that blog post, Yuan mentions the increased outreach and video tutorials. But security mistakes caused by user error are not really in the scope of this post. One of the first things the post mentions is that on March 27th, the &lt;a href="https://blog.zoom.us/wordpress/2020/03/27/zoom-use-of-facebook-sdk-in-ios-client/">Facebook SDK&lt;/a> was removed from the Zoom app on iOS. It&amp;rsquo;s astounding to me that Yuan can claim in the same blog post detailing the removal of the Facebook SDK that (March 27, 2020) &amp;ldquo;Our customers’ privacy is incredibly important to us&amp;rdquo;. This is insane. If customer privacy was important then the Facebook SDK would never ever have been in the Zoom app. Facebook is an absolute surveillance monster. The SDK spies on people that don&amp;rsquo;t even use Facebook. Apps that really care about privacy don&amp;rsquo;t touch anything Facebook or Google with a ten foot pole. Some information sent by the Facebook SDK was: Application bundle identifier, application instance ID, application version, device carrier, iOS advertiser ID (gross), iOS device CPU cores, iOS disk space available (why???), iOS device disk space remaining, iOS device display dimensions, iOS device model, iOS language, iOS timezone, and iOS version. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen by accident. At some point, a developer for Zoom wrote some code for the iOS app to make it send that device information to Facebook on purpose. For a teleconferencing app, the Facebook SDK is absolutely unnecessary. Zoom only remove the SDK after being &lt;a href="https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/z3b745/zoom-removes-code-that-sends-data-to-facebook">called out&lt;/a>. for it. This is an example of being reactive to security and privacy issues, not proactive.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="reactive-not-proactive">Reactive, Not Proactive&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The Facebook SDK isn&amp;rsquo;t an isolated case either. Zoom didn&amp;rsquo;t start caring about user privacy until they had to start caring about it due to increased media pressure. Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href="https://blog.zoom.us/wordpress/2020/04/01/facts-around-zoom-encryption-for-meetings-webinars/">Zoom blog post&lt;/a> on April 1st about Zoom encryption practices. In the following quote, we can see Zoom trying to weasel their way around not having end-to-end encryption by redefining words again. Oded gal posted (April 1, 2020) &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;we used the term end-to-end encryption. While we never intended to deceive any of our customers, we recognize that there is a discrepancy between the commonly accepted definition of end-to-end encryption and how we were using it&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;. When in doubt, just change the meanings of words so you don&amp;rsquo;t look bad. In Zoom&amp;rsquo;s defense, they don&amp;rsquo;t use end-to-end encryption that way legacy protocols can be supported. Protocols such as H.323, SIP, and PSTN don&amp;rsquo;t work with end-to-end encryption. In my personal opinion, these are good reasons to abandon the PSTN (public switched telephone network) and other legacy protocols that don&amp;rsquo;t support end-to-end encryption. In the year 2020, end-to-end encryption should be ubiquitous and we should reject any applications not using it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another absolutely disgusting thing is that Zoom lied to customers again about not selling their data: &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;we do not sell our users’ data, we have never sold user data in the past, and have no intention of selling users’ data going forward&amp;rdquo; Eric S. Yuan. (2020, April 1). Retrieved May 24, 2020 from Zoom, Zoom blog, &lt;a href="https://blog.zoom.us/wordpress/2020/04/01/a-message-to-our-users/">https://blog.zoom.us/wordpress/2020/04/01/a-message-to-our-users/&lt;/a>. They did permanently removed the attention tracking feature which never should have existed to begin with. There is no mention of removing Google Analytics though.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="90-day-plan">90-Day Plan&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To play devil&amp;rsquo;s advocate, I can go through &lt;a href="https://blog.zoom.us/wordpress/2020/05/22/zoom-publishes-draft-design-of-end-to-end-encryption-offering/">Zoom&amp;rsquo;s 90-day plan&lt;/a> focusing all their resources on security and privacy to fix their platform. A few things they have done so far: only the host can screen share by default, participants need consent to be unmuted, audio indication for the waiting rooms, removing Giphy, and giving the host more control over the meeting. They also published a &lt;a href="https://blog.zoom.us/wordpress/2020/05/22/zoom-publishes-draft-design-of-end-to-end-encryption-offering/">draft crypto design&lt;/a> to redo their cryptography. It is apparently available for peer review on &lt;a href="https://github.com/zoom/zoom-e2e-whitepaper/blob/master/zoom_e2e.pdf">Github&lt;/a>. It&amp;rsquo;s still early to see where all this goes. But given that Zoom hasn&amp;rsquo;t ever owned up to selling user data in exchange for service, I don&amp;rsquo;t have my hopes high.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="use-jitsi-instead">Use Jitsi Instead&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Zoom is a &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/proprietary/">proprietary&lt;/a> platform. This means it is essentially a black box. As I mentioned earlier, this means it will always be less trustworthy than free software video conferencing solutions such as &lt;a href="https://jitsi.org/security">Jitsi&lt;/a>. The &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/torproject/status/1244986986278072322">Tor Project&lt;/a> recommended using Jitsi instead of Zoom. I haven&amp;rsquo;t done much research on Jitsi yet, but if the Tor Project is saying to try Jitsi, I would use it over Zoom any day. It&amp;rsquo;s also cross-platform and features actual end-to-end encryption. Even if Zoom implements end-to-end encryption, how can you trust it if it can&amp;rsquo;t be independently reviewed by anyone and no one outside of Zoom can see the source code? How can you trust the implementation on desktop or mobile platforms? In short, you can&amp;rsquo;t. No platform is perfect, however there are more secure and less secure solutions out there. And in general, you want to avoid proprietary programs because they cause the incentives to be aligned in such a way that Zoom will always have reasons to insert privacy-corroding features into their platform.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When no one except you or your organization can see the source code, there are incentives to insert malicious pieces of code that benefit you at the user&amp;rsquo;s expense. Jitsi does not have the same incentive structure because it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/free-sw.en.html">free software&lt;/a>. Anyone with the know-how can look over the code and see if something fishy is going on. This will never be true of Zoom. Zoom has no reason to ever give away their source code and make their program trusted free software. Part of the reason I dropped out of my classes at my university was because Zoom because being forced on us students and &lt;a href="../../the-tipping-point-rejecting-windows-zoom-lockdown-browser-and-the-lockdown-monitor/">I refused to use it&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="call-to-action">Call to Action&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not saying you, the reader, should go as far as I did. I&amp;rsquo;m just saying if we, as a society, want to live in a world where we are given more privacy and security in our digital lives, then we have to say no to platforms like Zoom. If we don&amp;rsquo;t, we will move ever closer to some kind of dystopian surveillance hell, assuming we aren&amp;rsquo;t already there. Ask yourself this question: If you don&amp;rsquo;t reject these untrusted proprietary platforms with a horrible track record, then who will? How many people do you know that would reject Zoom if their boss or professor told them to use it? The demand for our digital rights back has to start somewhere, before it&amp;rsquo;s too late.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>