<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>videos on Nicholas Johnson</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/videos/</link><description>Recent content in videos on Nicholas Johnson</description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/videos/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>[Video] Is Your Keyboard Spying on You?</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-is-your-keyboard-spying-on-you/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-is-your-keyboard-spying-on-you/</guid><description>&lt;p>Your keyboard is one of the most important things to secure in desktop &lt;em>and&lt;/em> mobile environments, yet it is often overlooked.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="mobile">Mobile&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re on a mobile device, chances are you&amp;rsquo;re using a &amp;ldquo;virtual&amp;rdquo; keyboard. A virtual keyboard is just an on-screen keyboard instead of a physical one. The problem is many available keyboards send your keystrokes to a remote server by default. Even the stock keyboard may do this. Even if you&amp;rsquo;re using the secure messaging app Signal, some big company could still be collecting everything you type through your keyboard app. Watch TheHatedOne&amp;rsquo;s video to find out how to secure your Android keyboard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=vCRX0MZm2KI">[Video Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The same advice goes for custom keyboards on iOS: If you&amp;rsquo;re using a custom keyboard, &lt;strong>use free software!&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="desktop">Desktop&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>TheHatedOne does not mention &lt;em>physical&lt;/em> keyboards. I have two pieces of advice for those:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Do not use a wireless keyboard (or mouse).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do not use a programmable keyboard.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h4 id="wireless-keyboards">Wireless Keyboards&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The problem with &lt;em>wireless&lt;/em> keyboards is in the name; they send keystrokes wirelessly to the USB receiver. It&amp;rsquo;s often impossible to &lt;em>verify&lt;/em> that wireless keyboards securely encrypt traffic. Even the keyboards with strong encryption are vulnerable to replay attacks which could be used to exploit the target machine. Even if a strong encrypted wireless keyboard is immune to replay attacks, it could be vulnerable to spoofing. Even with strong encryption, replay immunity and spoofing immunity, it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>still&lt;/em> possible to log the &lt;em>frequency&lt;/em> and &lt;em>timing&lt;/em> of keystrokes using statistical analysis to determine which keys are being pressed at which times. As a final very &lt;em>minor&lt;/em> issue, if AES is ever broken you&amp;rsquo;ll need a new keyboard.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This isn&amp;rsquo;t conjecture. Replay attacks and keystroke logging have already been demonstrated. It&amp;rsquo;s best just to have a wired physical keyboard (and mouse) to avoid all these problems.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="programmable-keyboards">Programmable Keyboards&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The second concern is &lt;em>programmable&lt;/em> keyboards. The problem with them is also in the name; they are programmable. If your computer can upgrade your keyboard firmware, then an attacker could embed viruses in your keyboard if your operating system is ever compromised. Then every time you reinstall your OS the virus could be reinstalled via your keyboard. If you have a fancy RGB keyboard controlled by drivers on your machine &lt;em>or&lt;/em> you have G-series keyboard macros (G1, G2, G3, etc.) you might consider using a different keyboard that &lt;em>isn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> programmable. You don&amp;rsquo;t want a keylogger embedded into your keyboard itself. So just use a non-programmable keyboard and program macros inside the actual program where you want to use them. There&amp;rsquo;s no reason I can think of that a keyboard would need to have embedded macros anyway. Just embed your macros in the program or OS configuration itself.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>For the vast majority of computer users, these measures should be enough to secure your keyboard.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Video] Don't Talk to the Police</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-dont-talk-to-the-police/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-dont-talk-to-the-police/</guid><description>&lt;p>American law professor at Regent University School of Law and former criminal defense attorney James Duane explains why you should never talk to police without an attorney present, especially if you&amp;rsquo;re innocent.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=d-7o9xYp7eE&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1">[Video Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;There is no one in the United States over the age of 18 who cannot be indicted for some federal crime. That is not an exaggeration&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; retired LSU Law Professor John Baker.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>[Video] You Should Delete Your Whatsapp ASAP</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-you-should-delete-your-whatsapp-asap/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-you-should-delete-your-whatsapp-asap/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/channel/UCjr2bPAyPV7t35MvcgT3W8Q">TheHatedOne&lt;/a> tells us why no one should be using Whatsapp.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=shpiVm1qpnw&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1">[Video Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="matrix">Matrix&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The only gripe I have about the video is the same one I had in &lt;a href="../../video-fixing-social-media-for-good">Fixing Social Media for Good&lt;/a>. While &lt;a href="https://matrix.org/">Matrix&lt;/a> is &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federation_%28information_technology%29">federated&lt;/a> and infinitely better than Whatsapp, federation still tends toward centralization. Also Matrix &lt;em>doesn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> protect metadata either and as TheHatedOne mentions, leaking metadata is really bad for a communications platform even if data is protected.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="signal">Signal&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.signal.org/">Signal&lt;/a> says it protects metadata, but there&amp;rsquo;s no way for users to verify that besides taking Signal&amp;rsquo;s word for it &lt;em>and&lt;/em> Signal is centralized. So neither Signal nor Matrix are the &lt;em>final&lt;/em> solution to secure communications.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="cwtch">Cwtch&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peer-to-peer">Peer to peer&lt;/a> is the best solution because there&amp;rsquo;s no way for it to tend towards centralization. Once &lt;a href="https://cwtch.im/">cwtch.im&lt;/a> (Cwtch is Welsh for hug/cuddle) is stable it will probably be the best peer to peer instant messaging solution since it can &lt;em>verifiably&lt;/em> protect metadata and have encrypted group conversations. It&amp;rsquo;s also built on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tor_%28anonymity_network%29">Tor&lt;/a> which is the most tested, most researched and most used anonymity network out there.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Video] Atheist Debates - Argument From Design, Part 1: Order and Purpose</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-atheist-debates-argument-from-design-part-1-order-and-purpose/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-atheist-debates-argument-from-design-part-1-order-and-purpose/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matt_Dillahunty">Matt Dillahunty&lt;/a> refutes the argument that a god must exist because the universe requires a designer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=RTJS1UHIj6k&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1">[Video Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Video] Atheist Debates - Argument From Design, Part 2: What Are the Odds?</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-atheist-debates-argument-from-design-part-2-what-are-the-odds/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-atheist-debates-argument-from-design-part-2-what-are-the-odds/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matt_Dillahunty">Matt Dillahunty&lt;/a> refutes the argument that natural explanations are improbable, so god must&amp;rsquo;ve created everything.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=fsw8VXAcHz4&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1">[Video Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Video] Atheist Debates - Pascal's Wager</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-atheist-debates-pascals-wager/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-atheist-debates-pascals-wager/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matt_Dillahunty">Matt Dillahunty&lt;/a> thoroughly refutes Pascal&amp;rsquo;s Wager.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He mentions the idea of &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Fractal_wrongness">fractal wrongness&lt;/a> which means that a worldview is wrong at every scale of resolution. Many theistic arguments are fractally wrong, not just Pascal&amp;rsquo;s Wager. But I&amp;rsquo;m really glad Matt brings it up in this video.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=YBCDGohZT70&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1">[Video Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Video] Atheist Debates - Supernatural Causation</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-atheist-debates-supernatural-causation/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-atheist-debates-supernatural-causation/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matt_Dillahunty">Matt Dillahunty&lt;/a> discusses the difficulty of demonstrating the supernatural.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=AwG7LJTTZFc&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1">[Video Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Video] Fixing Social Media for Good</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-fixing-social-media-for-good/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-fixing-social-media-for-good/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recent events have brought the issue of social media censorship to the forefront:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Facebook bans Trump&amp;rsquo;s account&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Instagram bans Trump&amp;rsquo;s account&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Snapchat bans Trump&amp;rsquo;s account&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Twitch bans Trump&amp;rsquo;s account&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Twitter bans Trump&amp;rsquo;s account&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Amazon removes Parler from its cloud hosting service&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Apple removes Parler from the App Store&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Google removes Parler from the Play Store&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Discord bans TheDonald.win server&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Reddit bans r/DonaldTrump&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pinterest censors Trump related topics&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Shopify removes Trump&amp;rsquo;s merchandise from its platform&lt;/li>
&lt;li>TikTok removes Trump&amp;rsquo;s speeches&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Youtube removes videos claiming widespread voter fraud&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>No informed person is disputing that these are private companies and they have the &lt;em>legal&lt;/em> right to do whatever they want (within the bounds of the law) with their platforms. The 1st amendment &lt;em>doesn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> apply here. Nonetheless it&amp;rsquo;s very alarming that voices coming from the political left are sympathetic to &lt;em>widespread&lt;/em> censorship just because it&amp;rsquo;s Trump. If it were someone within their own ranks being censored they would no doubt be making the same argument I&amp;rsquo;m going to make about the danger of censorship. Voices coming from the political right actually have a saner viewpoint on the censorship problem in the sense that they can actually recognize censorship as a social problem which Trump&amp;rsquo;s situation has only highlighted.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As amusing as it is seeing adult Eric Cartman&amp;rsquo;s megaphone taken away, having a handful of big tech companies control who gets a voice and who doesn&amp;rsquo;t is extremely dangerous. Once a platform is large enough it is a &lt;em>de facto&lt;/em> public forum in the sense that it can be used by anyone to freely spread their ideas. Censorship on it in practice can be as damaging to freedom of speech as censoring a &lt;em>de jure&lt;/em> public forum. The good coming from this censorship is people are waking up to the fact that big tech companies can and do censor whoever they want when it suits them. &lt;a href="https://signal.org">Signal Messenger&lt;/a> has even seen a &lt;a href="https://nitter.snopyta.org/elonmusk/status/1347165127036977153">huge increase&lt;/a> in downloads since the censorship imposed after the capitol riots. Uncensorable platforms are needed. &lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/channel/UC2eYFnH61tmytImy1mTYvhA">Luke Smith&lt;/a> proposes &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federation_%28information_technology%29">federated&lt;/a> platforms as a permanent fix for the censorship issue:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://videos.lukesmith.xyz/videos/watch/0c256439-ec59-4e41-bd40-0ebeca751543?autoplay=1">[Video Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="federation-versus-peer-to-peer">Federation Versus Peer to Peer&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>While federation is better than centralization, in practice federation tends toward centralization anyway. Email is federated but a few big providers (Gmail, Yahoo, Outlook, iCloud, Protonmail) control the market. Worse yet, all the big providers sell user data. But it&amp;rsquo;s not just email. On the federated communication platform &lt;a href="https://www.matrix.org">Matrix&lt;/a> users are still heavily concentrated on the default matrix.org homeserver. So it&amp;rsquo;s not true that federation alone fixes social media for good. A &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peer-to-peer">peer-to-peer&lt;/a> social media platform could fix social media for good. But I&amp;rsquo;d still rather see everyone on &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fediverse#Communication_protocols_used_in_the_fediverse">The Fediverse&lt;/a> instead of the centralized social media platforms used today.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Video] TikTok - a Trojan Horse into China's Dystopia</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-tiktok-a-trojan-horse-into-chinas-dystopia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-tiktok-a-trojan-horse-into-chinas-dystopia/</guid><description>&lt;p>TikTok is a national security risk and yet people are still using it &lt;em>by the millions&lt;/em>. President Trump signed an &lt;a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/executive-order-addressing-threat-posed-tiktok/">executive order&lt;/a> to ban TikTok by prohibiting United States citizens from doing business with the Chinese company ByteDance that owns TikTok. However the restrictions have been stalled in court since last August. At the time of the &lt;a href="https://newsroom.tiktok.com/en-us/tiktok-files-lawsuit">TikTok lawsuit&lt;/a> ByteDance claimed they had &lt;strong>100 million active users in the United States&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The main concern in the executive order seems to be TikTok allows the CCP to collect Americans' personal information including federal employees and it can be used for disinformation and blackmail. But as &lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/channel/UCjr2bPAyPV7t35MvcgT3W8Q">TheHatedOne&lt;/a> points out, US-based social media platforms already do the same thing. Facecrook has collected personal user data &lt;em>way&lt;/em> before TikTok was around and it has more than twice as many users today as TikTok did in August. A consequence of Facecrook&amp;rsquo;s data collection is it enabled &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facebook%E2%80%93Cambridge_Analytica_data_scandal">Cambridge analytica&lt;/a> to manipulate the US presidential election in 2016 and yet the Federal Trade Commission only fined Bookface $5 billion dollars. Bookface made $15 billion in just the first quarter of 2019. The fine was &lt;em>barely&lt;/em> a slap on the wrist.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The moral is if you&amp;rsquo;re a US-based company that endangers national security through personal data collection and manipulation of public opinion through propoganda you get a slap on the wrist from the FTC while the NSA pats you on the back. If you&amp;rsquo;re a Chinese-based company doing more or less the same you get an executive order banning you from doing business in the United States. And the 2 core issues of &lt;strong>centralization of power&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>proprietary software&lt;/strong> of which the other issues are a symptom never even get so much as a mention in the mainstream media or the government.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I recommend TheHatedOne&amp;rsquo;s commentary on TikTok because he actually addresses the proprietariness and centralization of power in the case of TikTok. Have a listen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=5UooWpC4yJs&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1">[Video Link]&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Video] Vengeance</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-vengeance/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/video-vengeance/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/channel/UCLhtZqdkjshgq8TqwIjMdCQ">Darkmatter2525&lt;/a> explains punitive prison systems&lt;/p>
&lt;p>(5min 43sec - 11min 43sec).&lt;br>
Click &lt;a href="https://redirect.invidious.io/watch?v=LX2VeWumRQ8&amp;amp;dark_mode=true&amp;amp;autoplay=1&amp;amp;start=343&amp;amp;end=703">this link&lt;/a> to watch only the relevant part of the video.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>