<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>articles on Nicholas Johnson</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/articles/</link><description>Recent content in articles on Nicholas Johnson</description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>[Article] You Should Be Using an Old Computer</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/article-you-should-be-using-an-old-computer/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/article-you-should-be-using-an-old-computer/</guid><description>&lt;p>I was going to write my own post about this subject until I discovered Luke Smith, a GNU/Linux technology Youtuber, already wrote an article about it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Link Below]&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://lukesmith.xyz/articles/oldcomputer">https://lukesmith.xyz/articles/oldcomputer&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>His reasons for recommending an old computer (specifically Thinkpads) are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>New computers are unnecessary for most people&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New computers are expensive&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New computers are slim and break easier&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New computers are impractical to repair yourself&lt;/li>
&lt;li>New computers contain a potential backdoor&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>You can read his article for more details on each point. I have a few comments to make. Smith cites processor-intensive video rendering as a reason you might need a newer computer. There&amp;rsquo;s also training/running neural networks, mining digital currency and some exhaustive search algorithms. But again the average person won&amp;rsquo;t be doing those things.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="intel-management-engine">Intel Management Engine&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Smith also claims the Intel Management Engine (Intel ME), the hidden processor in every modern Intel chip, is a government backdoor. This isn&amp;rsquo;t yet proven but the code in Intel ME is proprietary and secret, so it should be treated as a &lt;em>potential&lt;/em> intentional backdoor. &lt;em>At minimum&lt;/em> it&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2017/05/intels-management-engine-security-hazard-and-users-need-way-disable-it">security hazard&lt;/a>. Smith notes that AMD processors have basically the same problem.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The potential backdoor is really the crux of the ethical problem. Even if you don&amp;rsquo;t care about the price and you never drop your computer and you never replace any parts there&amp;rsquo;s still the potential backdoor. &lt;strong>Intel ME is always on even when your computer is turned off. It can&amp;rsquo;t be removed. No one knows what it actually does and Intel won&amp;rsquo;t tell us. We know it has full control over system memory and it can connect to the internet.&lt;/strong> If you&amp;rsquo;re at all tempted to use the &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Nothing_to_hide">nothing to hide argument&lt;/a> I only ask that you apply that same logic to Intel. If Intel has nothing to hide, why can&amp;rsquo;t they show us the source code for the ME? Why keep it secret? Why not allay all fears of a backdoor once and for all by releasing the source code? Unless of course it is in fact a backdoor.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe you&amp;rsquo;re above nothing to hide though. You understand privacy is a human right. But, you reason, the Intel ME isn&amp;rsquo;t a big deal because an interested government could find out what they wanted to know some other way. Besides even without ME there&amp;rsquo;s other embedded software that, however unlikely it is, could possibly also have backdoors. All that&amp;rsquo;s beyond your &amp;ldquo;threat model&amp;rdquo; anyway. This goes back to a previous post I made. By using the &lt;em>least&lt;/em> potentially backdoored computer possible, you &lt;a href="../../raising-the-bar-on-privacy">raise the bar on privacy&lt;/a> (and freedom!). That&amp;rsquo;s a cause we &lt;em>all&lt;/em> need to be fighting for irrespective of threat models.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="retrofreedom">RetroFreedom&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The next most obvious question is &amp;ldquo;Where do I buy a computer without a backdoor?&amp;rdquo;. I recommend &lt;a href="https://retrofreedom.com/">RetroFreedom&lt;/a> (formerly Minifree). &lt;a href="https://vimuser.org/">Leah Rowe&lt;/a> operates the site. She maintains the &lt;a href="https://libreboot.org/">Libreboot&lt;/a> project, a free as in freedom alternative BIOS that ships with the old Thinkpads she sells. You can purchase products with cryptocurrency and several addons and upgrades are offered. I don&amp;rsquo;t mind the markup in price since I know it goes toward an important free software project. I can personally attest to the quality of the laptops from RetroFreedom. I&amp;rsquo;ve bought several laptops from there running exclusively free software and I&amp;rsquo;m very satisfied.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="free-software">Free Software&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I would never again use a nonfree laptop to do my everyday personal computing. I&amp;rsquo;ve given up videogames since all the popular titles are nonfree requiring me to run the Winblows operating system. &lt;a href="../../why-i-left-its">I quit my job&lt;/a> to avoid promoting proprietary software. &lt;a href="../../the-tipping-point-rejecting-windows-zoom-lockdown-browser-and-the-lockdown-monitor">I dropped out of college&lt;/a> so I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to use invasive proprietary malware. Too many people have told me I&amp;rsquo;m too extreme. I care too much about free software. Life is just too short to be so picky. But to them I would say this:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What does it say about society that the only way to get a non-backdoored laptop is to buy from a specific set of computers that are around 13 years old, replace the WiFi card, use special equipment to flash the BIOS with Libreboot/Coreboot and replace the operating system with GNU/Linux? Or pay someone else to do the procedure.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Further, what you have to realize is there is a war being waged on general-purpose computing. Every year manufacturers come up with new ways to make your computer harder to repair thereby increasing e-waste. Every year software companies make their ecosystems more locked down giving you less and less control over your own devices. To &lt;em>not&lt;/em> use an old Thinkpad is to be on the wrong side of this war. &lt;strong>I do not want to live in a world where I don&amp;rsquo;t have control over what I buy and cannot repair it&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Most people living in 1st world countries today are far too complacent&lt;/strong>. I can&amp;rsquo;t emphasize this enough. So when people ask me why I care so much, why I&amp;rsquo;ve given up &lt;em>so&lt;/em> much, I look at them in bewilderment. Why &lt;em>don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> they? If people like them don&amp;rsquo;t start caring soon we&amp;rsquo;re going to live in a dark world where computer users are totally subjugated. The 13 year old Thinkpads suffice for 95% of use cases for now but that won&amp;rsquo;t always be true. Proprietary threats are looming. Change needs to happen now, not 10 years from now. So use a free laptop even if it&amp;rsquo;s inconvenient because it&amp;rsquo;s not getting any easier.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="privacy">Privacy&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s also the whole privacy issue of having a potentially backdoored laptop. A college professor once told me privacy is dead. As if it were just a fact of the modern era and I hadn&amp;rsquo;t realized it yet. As long as there are people like me are around privacy is &lt;em>not&lt;/em> dead. I will &lt;em>never&lt;/em> accept a world without privacy. I will resist backdoors into my computer. I&amp;rsquo;ll tell you another thing. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t all the free software people that inspired this in me. It was the haters. Those who said it didn&amp;rsquo;t matter, privacy is dead, it&amp;rsquo;s unwinnable, I should just give up so my life is easier, etc. So please tell me any of those things. The naysayers keep me motivated. I don&amp;rsquo;t waste my time wondering whether free software is a fight we can win. It&amp;rsquo;s a fight we &lt;em>must&lt;/em> win. As long as there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>any&lt;/em> chance of winning, and even if it &lt;em>seems like&lt;/em> there&amp;rsquo;s not, we &lt;em>must&lt;/em> try.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You don&amp;rsquo;t need to quit your job and drop out to create change. All you have to do is create a rift. Get people to take notice. Force them to act by being unmoving in your commitment to free software. You won&amp;rsquo;t be popular. And you&amp;rsquo;ll be told you&amp;rsquo;re wrong &lt;em>a lot&lt;/em>. You might even start to doubt yourself. But let others say whatever they want and stay strong anyway. You have an advantage they don&amp;rsquo;t: the knowledge that you&amp;rsquo;re doing the right thing. You do have power. Those in power would like you to think that you don&amp;rsquo;t, but you do. Wield it wisely.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>