<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>info on Nicholas Johnson</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/info/</link><description>Recent content in info on Nicholas Johnson</description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/info/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Site Update 008</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-008/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-008/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="whats-new">What&amp;rsquo;s New&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It seems I&amp;rsquo;m making update posts more often than I imagined, but it&amp;rsquo;s fine. I&amp;rsquo;m going to try out a list format for this one.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Change &amp;ldquo;recommendation&amp;rdquo; tag to more specific tags. (e.g., &amp;ldquo;books&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;videos&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sign commits on &lt;a href="https://github.com/0Gitnick/0Gitnick.github.io">Github&lt;/a>/&lt;a href="https://gitlab.com/0Gitnick/0Gitnick.github.io">Gitlab&lt;/a> so users can &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trust_on_first_use">TOFU&lt;/a> this blog&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Minify html and css&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="future-plans">Future Plans&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Mirror site repo and scripts on &lt;a href="https://savannah.nongnu.org/users/gitnick">Savannah&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Write &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/content-management/summaries/">content summaries&lt;/a> for each post for improved site/RSS readability&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Reconsider posts displayed per page after adjusting site summaries&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Site Update 007</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-007/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-007/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="whats-new">What&amp;rsquo;s New&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I provisioned a new TLS certificate from &lt;a href="https://zerossl.com">ZeroSSL&lt;/a>. That&amp;rsquo;s why there was some downtime yesterday on 0gitnick.xyz. By default &lt;a href="https://caddyserver.com">Caddy&lt;/a> provisions TLS certs from &lt;a href="https://letsencrypt.org">Let&amp;rsquo;s Encrypt&lt;/a> with a P-256 public key. I &lt;a href="https://safecurves.cr.yp.to/rigid.html">don&amp;rsquo;t trust NIST curves&lt;/a> so 0gitnick.xyz uses a 4096 bit RSA key now. As of the time of this post all other clearnet &lt;a href="../../about#Site_Mirrors">site mirrors&lt;/a> use 2048 bit RSA which is also secure.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Site Update 006</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-006/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-006/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="whats-new">What&amp;rsquo;s New&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I changed the website theme. It&amp;rsquo;s darker now and much easier on the eyes. I didn&amp;rsquo;t particularly like the last theme ever since I started using it. I only picked it because it was easy to manage with how minimal it was. I added a favicon to identify my site:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="../../favicon.ico" alt="favicon">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s nothing to brag about. I just thought I ought to have &lt;em>something&lt;/em> there. The markdown is improved, especially the blockquotes. It didn&amp;rsquo;t seem like they were rendering on the previous theme, but now they do. Each post now has a word count and estimated reading time in the metadata section. Posts are paginated so they&amp;rsquo;re not all on one page like before. I&amp;rsquo;m allergic to client-side JS, so this site has none. I modified the theme to use CSS rather than JS for the interactive features. I&amp;rsquo;m happy with the way it turned out and I consider it a significant improvement. The new theme is everything I originally wanted for my blog, so it&amp;rsquo;s here to stay.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Site Update 005</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-005/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-005/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="whats-new">What&amp;rsquo;s New&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I removed the people and organizations sections on the &lt;a href="../../about">about&lt;/a> page. I never explained why those sections were there in the first place. I just filled them with links to organizations and people. My linking to them was not an endorsement of everything those people and organizations have ever said or done. For people I was just trying to indicate that each person in the list had &lt;em>some&lt;/em> important ideas. For organizations I was trying to indicate that I thought they fought for worthy causes &lt;em>on the whole&lt;/em>. But there was no way for readers to know just by looking at the links which words and actions I agreed with and which I disagreed with. I removed those links because, as I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205230110id_/https://0gitnick.xyz/about/">written before&lt;/a>, I want my blog to be chiefly about ideas, not people or organizations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With that said, there are so many ideas that I appreciate from others that sound better in their words rather than my own. I was conscious of this when writing about &lt;a href="../../free-will-is-incoherent-part-1">free&lt;/a> &lt;a href="../../free-will-is-incoherent-part-2">will&lt;/a>. Those posts were inspired by &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sam_Harris">Sam Harris&lt;/a>' book &lt;a href="https://samharris.org/books/free-will/">Free Will&lt;/a>. It&amp;rsquo;s not that I can&amp;rsquo;t make a good case against free will. It&amp;rsquo;s that I can&amp;rsquo;t make a better case against free will than Sam does in his book. So it might have been better for me to literally plug his book rather than write my own post on the subject. I feel this way when it comes to lots of topics. Why spend so much time and effort restating something someone else has already expressed in a clearer way than I can?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Therefore I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to create a new tag called &amp;ldquo;recommendation&amp;rdquo;. Posts under the recommendation tag will feature books, articles, academic papers, videos and ideas along with some commentary. The idea is this will give me the flexibility to write a new post when I want to share ideas in my own words and create a &amp;ldquo;recommendation&amp;rdquo; post when I want to endorse the ideas of others in their own words. After I&amp;rsquo;ve created a few recommendation posts and a few regular posts, I&amp;rsquo;ll reevaluate site organization and decide whether to keep recommendations or come up with something else.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Site Update 004</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-004/</link><pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-004/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="whats-new">What&amp;rsquo;s New&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>You may have noticed the site was down on the 11th and IPv6 was unavailable on the 12th. My hosting provider had an outage, but the situation is resolved now.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Site Update 003</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-003/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-003/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="whats-new">What&amp;rsquo;s New&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I removed the bootstrap JS that wasn&amp;rsquo;t really doing anything. The site should load faster and use less data now. I created a new tag called &amp;ldquo;info&amp;rdquo; for all site updates. The about page has been compacted so it&amp;rsquo;s cleaner and easier to read and not so long-winded. I also updated my PGP key to use Curve25519 instead of RSA. &lt;a href="https://secushare.org/PGP">PGP is awful&lt;/a>. I still use it for email only because it&amp;rsquo;s better than nothing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This site allows you to get filtered RSS feeds for just the content you&amp;rsquo;re interested in. For example, if you only want to read about privacy, then you can use &lt;a href="https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/privacy/index.xml">https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/privacy/index.xml&lt;/a> for a privacy feed or &lt;a href="https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/privacy/index.html">https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/privacy/index.html&lt;/a> for webpages. The category-centered feeds were broken with the same issue the aggregate site feed had last time with the relative URLs. They&amp;rsquo;re fixed now.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The biggest change I made is reorganizing the &lt;a href="../../tags">tags&lt;/a>. I renamed some tags and added new ones. The reason I did that is I have in mind the readers who just want a particular type of content and the tags were disorganized before. If I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if a post should be assigned a certain tag, I err on the side of too many tags since not tagging it could mean some readers will miss a relevant post. It&amp;rsquo;s better for readers to see a post they don&amp;rsquo;t care about now and then and just delete it rather than miss posts entirely because I was too strict with tagging.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Site Update 002</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-002/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-002/</guid><description>&lt;p>The RSS feed on my site works again. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how long it was broken. I generate this site using relative URLs in order to accomodate I2P, Tor and Zeronet users. That inadvertantly caused the XML for RSS to also use relative links. RSS doesn&amp;rsquo;t support relative links because it has no way of knowing the URL from only the XML data. I patched it so the XML now uses absolute links.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sorry to anybody using RSS! ¯\&lt;em>(ツ)&lt;/em>/¯&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Site Update 001</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-001/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/site-update-001/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="whats-new">What&amp;rsquo;s New&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I just finished migrating this site to a new server in Poland and I made a few changes along the way. I added &lt;strong>IPv6 support&lt;/strong> to the site. I cleaned up the &lt;a href="../../about">about&lt;/a> page and added some context to give the site a clear purpose. The primary crypto donation method is now Monero instead of Bitcoin. It&amp;rsquo;s better for privacy. I also switched from Ko-fi to &lt;a href="https://liberapay.com">Liberapay&lt;/a>. Liberapay supports multiple currencies and languages. It&amp;rsquo;s a non-profit that handles transactions transparently with &lt;a href="https://github.com/liberapay">free software&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As for the site mirrors, I removed the &lt;a href="https://www.siue.edu/~njohnag">SIUe&lt;/a> mirror since it&amp;rsquo;s insecure and I seem to have lost access since I don&amp;rsquo;t attend any more. I changed the onion address to a new &lt;a href="http://gitnickkff6dtksy4txvwmgibwa3x5syfcyzk6kjnisuknuutwtumdid.onion">vanity onion&lt;/a>. I also registered my &lt;a href="http://0gitnick.i2p">I2P site&lt;/a> with zzz&amp;rsquo;s I2P domain name service so it&amp;rsquo;s more memorable. It will take up to a week to propogate through all the nodes, so you&amp;rsquo;ll have to use the direct &lt;a href="http://xpw6ynhbxxuqsr6spcnfiyvuhvimm3jg7uti2oqv3jlh76j532oa.b32.i2p">base32 address&lt;/a> or a &lt;a href="http://stats.i2p/cgi-bin/jump.cgi?a=0gitnick.i2p">jump service&lt;/a> to access this blog over I2P for now. I don&amp;rsquo;t plan on changing the links again so &lt;strong>it&amp;rsquo;s safe to bookmark the new onion address and I2P link.&lt;/strong> I&amp;rsquo;ve made a backup of the private keys for the eepsite, onion, and zeronet addresses. In the event of a future server migration, I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to keep the addresses the same.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>