<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>spirituality on Nicholas Johnson</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/spirituality/</link><description>Recent content in spirituality on Nicholas Johnson</description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://0gitnick.xyz/tags/spirituality/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Addiction to Thinking</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/the-addiction-to-thinking/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/the-addiction-to-thinking/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I said in a &lt;a href="../../on-spirituality">previous post&lt;/a> that posts tagged &lt;a href="../../tags/spirituality">spirituality&lt;/a> aren&amp;rsquo;t to be interpreted as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Truth-apt">truth-apt&lt;/a> and that I wanted to be clearer about how to interpret these posts. Well this post is an exception. &lt;em>Do&lt;/em> interpret it as making truth claims. I&amp;rsquo;m going to be more rigorous than I normally am in spiritual posts and try not to make any false claims. So let&amp;rsquo;s get started.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="writing-meditation">Writing Meditation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This activity doesn&amp;rsquo;t require you to believe superstitions or unsubstantiated claims as a prerequisite. It&amp;rsquo;s very simple. All you need is a &lt;em>pen&lt;/em> and &lt;em>paper&lt;/em>. Be sure to use a pen, not a pencil.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here are the instructions:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Pick up the pen and hold it to the paper. Whenever you notice a thought that can be written down in words, you write it down. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry about grammar or spelling, that&amp;rsquo;s not the point. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry if it&amp;rsquo;s even coherent or continuous. Don&amp;rsquo;t scratch anything out. Redundancy is perfectly fine. Just write down whatever&amp;rsquo;s on your mind. If it&amp;rsquo;s kind, peaceful, helpful, write it down. If it&amp;rsquo;s hateful, vulgar, taboo, write it down anyway. It&amp;rsquo;s important that you don&amp;rsquo;t censor anything. Just let there be a continuous flow of thoughts from your mind to the paper.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Write until you notice enough thoughts that your mind outpaces your hand. Try to at least fill up 1 full page with thoughts. The more, the better. The goal is to write down as much of your own &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self_talk">self-talk&lt;/a> as you can.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h4 id="limitations">Limitations&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>This style of meditation has limitations that don&amp;rsquo;t inhibit practices like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vipassan%C4%81">Vipassana&lt;/a>. An obvious one is if your hand can&amp;rsquo;t keep up with your mind then you miss some thought-material. Another limitation is you can only capture a rather small fraction of thoughts. A significant portion of your thoughts aren&amp;rsquo;t words and sentences. They&amp;rsquo;re images, memories, abstract concepts, and emotions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>None of that matters for our purposes. What matters is you end up with a tangible object to reference. Please do it before you continue reading. You won&amp;rsquo;t get the full benefit otherwise.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now read the whole paper back to yourself. If you did the exercise correctly your writing will sound very unstructured. The important thing to realize is this: While you were writing your thoughts down, you were &lt;em>noticing&lt;/em> them. Otherwise how could you have written them? But in normal everyday experience, you are &lt;em>not&lt;/em> noticing them. Just because you stopped writing them down, just because you stopped &lt;em>paying attention&lt;/em> to them doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean they went away. That constant flow of thought is &lt;em>still&lt;/em> there. It&amp;rsquo;s just in the background.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="insanity">Insanity&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you wrote for long enough you might notice certain things reading it back. For example you might notice you had the same thought 3 times in a row. Imagine if you were having a conversation with another person and they repeated themselves 3 times in a row. You would probably be very confused.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You might notice in your writing things you already know. In fact &lt;em>all&lt;/em> of your thoughts might be things you already know. Imagine if you were invited into someone&amp;rsquo;s home and they started telling you what it looked like. &amp;ldquo;The walls are white. The door is made of wood. There&amp;rsquo;s a painting in the hallway&amp;rdquo;. That would be strange. But this is &lt;em>exactly&lt;/em> the character of the conversation going on in your own mind.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re an insecure person with self-doubt then you might have written &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m useless. I can&amp;rsquo;t accomplish my goals. I should just give up&amp;rdquo;. Even the confident have insecurities. But those aren&amp;rsquo;t fruitful thoughts. If you talked to someone else that way &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;re useless. You can&amp;rsquo;t accomplish your goals. You should just give up&amp;rdquo; you might catch a straight right hand to the jaw. Nevertheless you talk to yourself that way continuously.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Point being most of us live our lives spellbound by this endless stream of thought. Thinking thinking thinking&amp;hellip; from the moment we wake up in the morning until we close our eyes to sleep at night, from cradle to grave. We live our lives in a thought-trance with no obvious way out. You could probably stick your hand on a hot stove for 5 seconds if you &lt;em>really&lt;/em> wanted to. But even if your life depended on it you could not stop thinking even for a minute.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This incessant thinking, this addiction to thought, is a form of insanity. You&amp;rsquo;ll never hear about it in the media though because an addiction that everyone suffers from is no addiction at all. It&amp;rsquo;s just &amp;ldquo;life&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="unawareness-of-thought-is-the-problem-not-thought-itself">Unawareness of Thought Is the Problem, Not Thought Itself&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>None of this is &lt;em>new&lt;/em> information. &lt;strong>Contemplatives have said for centuries that being &amp;ldquo;hypnotized&amp;rdquo; by your own thoughts in &lt;em>every&lt;/em> moment is the normal way of being.&lt;/strong> That is to say you aren&amp;rsquo;t in the mode of noticing your thoughts most of the time. You&amp;rsquo;re simply thinking without knowing you&amp;rsquo;re thinking. Although contemplatives have talked about this mostly in religious contexts, there&amp;rsquo;s no reason you can&amp;rsquo;t recognize this fact of the mind firsthand in a secular context. That was the goal of the writing exercise.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have to clarify that thinking is an absolutely necessary faculty. It&amp;rsquo;s necessary for survival and human progress. For instance all technology first began with a thought. So thought is not the enemy here. &lt;strong>The problem is thinking without being aware of it.&lt;/strong> As contemplatives through the ages have discovered, having that background stream of thoughts is a primary source of human suffering. Reason being that internal conversation, even for the most average people, is &lt;em>often&lt;/em> negative and, as I discussed, sounds like how someone in a mental asylum might communicate.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="life-is-pain">Life is Pain&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There may be no more important fact to realize if you want to lead a fulfilling life than this one: Throughout the course of a normal human life, &lt;strong>the quality of one&amp;rsquo;s mind determines quality of one&amp;rsquo;s life&lt;/strong>. If you go through life entranced by your thoughts as most of us do, you will lead a life of dissatisfaction. You&amp;rsquo;ll never be fully content with the present moment. In my own experience and others', even the &lt;em>best&lt;/em> days of our lives don&amp;rsquo;t quite cut it. In ancient Indian literature, this is known as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dukkha">dukkha&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="an-alternative-perhaps">An Alternative, Perhaps?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Mystics, yogis and monks that have spent decades doing nothing but meditating in caves have suggested that there are alternatives to living entranced by your thoughts. They&amp;rsquo;ve suggested that contentment is actually a learnable skill. To most people it sounds strange that one could &lt;em>learn&lt;/em> to be content. It&amp;rsquo;s thought that contentment arises out of favorable life circumstances. This is contradicted by scientific studies showing people don&amp;rsquo;t report being much happier given increases in income once the threshold for basic needs is met.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unless you believe all the contemplative literature over the millenia is &lt;em>merely&lt;/em> a product of mental illness and self-deception, you have to admit &lt;strong>some people seem to have found an alternative to being entranced by thought, to being perpetually dissatisfied with life. Once you admit that, you also have to admit that if it was possible for them, then it just might be possible for you too.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And the alternatives to dissatisfaction don&amp;rsquo;t require you to ignore bad things happening in the world or accept religious dogma. They just require a shift in consciousness. For some the shift is gradual taking many years of practice. And for others like &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eckhart_Tolle">Eckhart Tolle&lt;/a> it&amp;rsquo;s instantaneous.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="is-spirituality-for-everyone">Is Spirituality For Everyone?&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Now I&amp;rsquo;m not saying there&amp;rsquo;s an alternative for &lt;em>everyone&lt;/em>. Oftentimes an interest in spirituality comes after seeing the mechanics of suffering. It&amp;rsquo;s not hard to notice. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t have been older than age 12 when I saw it. I wanted something. I got it. I was satisfied for an instant before it wore off and I wanted something else. At that point I had the revelation that the nature of the mind is to never be satisfied. At the time, like most westerners, I made nothing of it. I assumed that was the way life was and it couldn&amp;rsquo;t be any other way. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until I neared adulthood that I sincerely considered the possibility of alternative mind states.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is a basic level of introspection required to &lt;em>notice&lt;/em> the mechanics of suffering and to become suspicious of alternative ways of being. In my own experience I can&amp;rsquo;t imagine how you &lt;em>couldn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> notice the mechanics of suffering. To me it&amp;rsquo;s so plain and obvious I recognized it as an adolescent. But there are people that go their &lt;em>whole&lt;/em> natural lives not being the slightest bit curious about why they suffer. Some people are &lt;em>so&lt;/em> &amp;ldquo;grounded&amp;rdquo; that frankly &lt;em>only&lt;/em> psychoactive substances can get them to notice that experience can be vastly different than the usual. But most people, especially westerners, prematurely assume introspection offers nothing of practical importance.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="noticing-thoughts">Noticing Thoughts&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Even if your goal isn&amp;rsquo;t to be the next Eckhart Tolle it&amp;rsquo;s not a bad idea to keep in mind what it was like to read back your own thoughts written on paper. The next time you&amp;rsquo;re sad, frustrated or depressed, just notice the mechanics of your suffering. Notice the undercurrent of thought. The paper and pen were only there to help, but you don&amp;rsquo;t need them. You can actually notice &lt;em>more&lt;/em> when you&amp;rsquo;re not limited to what you can write on paper. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s not your internal dialogue that&amp;rsquo;s causing the suffering. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s a bad memory. Whatever it is, try being aware of it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The final point I want to make is that &lt;strong>every claim I&amp;rsquo;ve made about the mind in this post can be tested in your own experience&lt;/strong>. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to take my word for it. If you don&amp;rsquo;t believe that unawareness of thought is a primary cause of suffering then all I can do is urge you to do is pay closer attention. It&amp;rsquo;s just a common fact of experience and you don&amp;rsquo;t have to accept any unsubstantiated claims to recognize how distracted you are all the time. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to accept unsubstantiated claims to suspect that others have found alternative ways of existing in the world and that maybe you can too.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>[Book] Waking Up</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/book-waking-up/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/book-waking-up/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is my second book recommendation and here I am &lt;em>again&lt;/em> recommending a book authored by &lt;a href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris&lt;/a>. And it&amp;rsquo;s probably not the last time I&amp;rsquo;ll recommend his books. Allow me to justify why his content gets so much promotion on this blog.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-i-promote-sam-harris-content">Why I Promote Sam Harris Content&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When someone holds a false belief, especially if it&amp;rsquo;s a core belief, they are likely to accept other concomitant falsehoods. This is why you don&amp;rsquo;t hear about theoretical physicist flat earthers. Being a theoretical physicist entails beliefs about the physical universe which are &lt;em>incompatible&lt;/em> with believing the earth is flat. To knowingly hold contradictory beliefs, the phenomenon known as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_dissonance">cognitive dissonance&lt;/a>, is psychologically distressing. So people make some effort, however minimal, to reconcile their beliefs to create a consistent picture of reality.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The converse is also true. When someone holds true core beliefs, they&amp;rsquo;re usually right about concomitant truths as well. I&amp;rsquo;m vastly oversimplifying and I could mention many caveats but that&amp;rsquo;s generally the case. On several subject areas of my interest Sam Harris &lt;em>consistently&lt;/em> gets it right. He&amp;rsquo;s adept at navigating the pitfalls others find themselves trapped in when talking about spirituality. Sometimes I learn completely new information from him but I also find that he often expounds on my own thoughts better than I can. I hope I will eventually be as articulate on this blog as he is in his writing. Nonetheless I don&amp;rsquo;t agree with him about everything and I also don&amp;rsquo;t desire for my own voice to be identical to his.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="waking-up">Waking Up&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>When it comes to introducing spirituality to atheists and skeptics, Waking Up is &lt;em>the&lt;/em> book to read. I&amp;rsquo;ve read it and reread it and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find &lt;em>any&lt;/em> unsupported claims. It&amp;rsquo;s expressive, relevant and intelligible to sincere truthseekers. Waking Up elaborates on the self in a clearer, more comprehensible way than &lt;a href="../../the-self">my own&lt;/a> &lt;a href="../../ego-traps">past attempts&lt;/a>. It mentions the idea of headlessness which &lt;a href="../../the-eternal-here-and-now">I&amp;rsquo;ve also talked about before&lt;/a>. So before you read anything from other popular spiritual authors, I&amp;rsquo;d recommend reading Waking Up first. It gives the broader context that other books on spirituality leave out.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Waking Up is a refreshing, rational middleground on spirituality avoiding both &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Talk:Spirituality">denial of spiritual experiences&lt;/a> by skeptics &lt;em>and&lt;/em> mystical &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Woo">woo-woo&lt;/a> peddled by &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Deepak_Chopra">Deepak Chopra&lt;/a> and other pseudointellectuals. I recommend it to anyone remotely interested in spirituality.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[Link below]&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://samharris.org/books/waking-up">https://samharris.org/books/waking-up&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To finish off this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll leave you with a quote from the book.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Until we can talk about spirituality in rational terms—acknowledging the validity of self-transcendence—our world will remain shattered by dogmatism. This book has been my attempt to begin such a conversation.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; Sam Harris in Waking Up&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>On Spirituality</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/on-spirituality/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/on-spirituality/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="clarification">Clarification&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;The fundamental &lt;em>game&lt;/em> of being is like the game of hide and go seek. We hide in the thoughts we don&amp;rsquo;t know we&amp;rsquo;re having. They become who we are. Then one day, something or someone wakes us up and we realize we were playing a game the entire time. This could take 10 seconds or 10 years depending on the person. But, the game goes on several times in a single human life, played out in a different way each time. Just imagine all the ways the game is being played across all of humanity. The game of being a good person and not an evil one. The game of seeking happiness. The game of seeking enlightenment&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ndash; Me in &lt;a href="../../ego-traps">Ego Traps&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Some of you just read that thinking something along the lines of &amp;ldquo;What on earth is he talking about? He&amp;rsquo;s gone off the deep end&amp;rdquo;. Skeptics would say I&amp;rsquo;m peddling &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Deepak_Chopra">Deepak Chopra&lt;/a> level &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Woo">woo-woo&lt;/a>. And I can&amp;rsquo;t blame them for thinking that. Take the first sentence &amp;ldquo;The fundamental &lt;em>game&lt;/em> of being is like the game of hide and go seek&amp;rdquo;. If you read that as a literal statement, it&amp;rsquo;s unfalsifiable at best and meaningless at worst. The rest of that paragraph and parts of other posts tagged &amp;ldquo;spirituality&amp;rdquo; have the same problem. For that, I apologize. I never meant to peddle woo-woo. I am &lt;em>definitely&lt;/em> no Deepak Chopra and I have no intentions of promoting pseudoscience or irrational thinking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the time I probably wasn&amp;rsquo;t even sure how I wanted those posts to be interpreted. I was unsure of my &lt;em>writing&lt;/em> because I was unsure of my &lt;em>thinking&lt;/em>. You can see that in my protracted preface to &lt;a href="../../doublethink">Doublethink&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>As a quick note, what people post online is often taken as something they will forever agree with and are forever held to. This is unreasonable. There needs to be some equivalent of forgiveness if one posts something horrible online, but that&amp;rsquo;s a topic for another post. I&amp;rsquo;m not saying people aren&amp;rsquo;t responsible for what they post. But I am saying we should aspire to take the most charitable interpretation of what people post if we care about advancing the conversation. Obviously a person&amp;rsquo;s character is a factor in how you interpret what they post.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On my blog, I want to retain the right to post not only ideas that I understand well. But I also want the freedom to talk about things I&amp;rsquo;m not sure about. That means I run the risk of being wrong. No one posting their ideas online openly should expect to be immune to criticism. Criticism comes with the territory. But I want to say I&amp;rsquo;m interested in sharing ideas. If it&amp;rsquo;s clear to me you&amp;rsquo;re only interested in taking my words out of context, twisting what I write or using cheap gotcha&amp;rsquo;s because I didn&amp;rsquo;t state something perfectly, then I probably won&amp;rsquo;t respond. If you want clarification about anything I discuss, visit my &lt;a href="../../about">about page&lt;/a> for contact details. With that cleared up, let&amp;rsquo;s move on to the meat of this post.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&amp;ndash; Me in &lt;a href="../../doublethink">Doublethink&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Anyone who has tried to express spiritual experiences and concepts can attest to the difficulty of conveying them to others without sounding like a &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Quackery">quack&lt;/a>. I don&amp;rsquo;t have a good remedy for that. What I do have is an explanation for &lt;em>why&lt;/em> it&amp;rsquo;s so difficult.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="why-talking-about-spirituality-is-hard">Why Talking About Spirituality is Hard&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s a simple reason talking about spirituality is hard. It&amp;rsquo;s because words never do justice to spiritual experience. Nothing I can say in the English language, or any other language, can convey the &lt;em>gravity&lt;/em> of a truly spiritual experience. Spiritual orators therefore appropriately resort to analogy, myth and storytelling to allude to their spiritual experiences.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="spirituality-and-skeptics">Spirituality and Skeptics&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The problem skeptics readily point out is most spiritual orators are all too sympathetic to pseudoscience, religion and woo-woo. This leads them to conclude that spiritual experiences are just forms of mental illness and irrationality. What they don&amp;rsquo;t realize is spiritual orators gravitate to pseudoscience, religion and woo-woo precisely because &lt;em>&lt;strong>skeptics fail to connect to the character of spiritual experiences&lt;/strong>&lt;/em>. That is to say if I want to talk about spirituality I have a much better chance at effectively imparting my experiences to a priest than a skeptic. To quote Sam Harris' blog post &lt;a href="https://samharris.org/whats-the-point-of-transcendence/">What&amp;rsquo;s the Point of Transcendence?&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;experiences of self-transcendence are generally only sought and interpreted in a religious or “spiritual” context—and these are precisely the phenomena that tend to increase a person’s faith. How many Christians, having felt self-transcending love for their neighbors in church or body-dissolving bliss in prayer, decide to ditch Christianity? Not many, I would guess. How many people who never have experiences of this kind (no matter how hard they try) become atheists? I don’t know, but there is no question that these states of mind act as a kind of filter: they get counted in support of ancient dogma by the faithful; and their absence seems to give my fellow atheists yet another reason to reject religion.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Reading the comments on Jerry’s blog exposes the problem in full. There are several people there who have absolutely no idea what I’m talking about—and they take this to mean that I am not making sense. Of course, religious people often present the opposite problem: they tend to think they know exactly what I’m talking about, in so far as it can seem to support one religious doctrine or another. Both these orientations present impressive obstacles to understanding.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Harris has even had to &lt;a href="https://samharris.org/a-plea-for-spirituality/">defend his use of the word spiritual&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://samharris.org/on-spiritual-truths/">argue that spiritual experiences actually happen&lt;/a>. Us spiritual skeptics have always been on the defense of spirituality against skeptics that seem to have never had a spiritual experience in their life. Or if they have had such an experience they somehow failed to see &lt;a href="https://samharris.org/whats-the-point-of-transcendence/">the significance of it&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="going-forwarda-namegoing_forwarda">Going Forward&lt;a name="Going_Forward">&lt;/a>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I &lt;em>don&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> want to always be playing defense when sharing spiritual ideas. But I &lt;em>do&lt;/em> want to avoid making unsubstantiated and vague claims about the nature of experience. So from this point forward posts tagged &amp;ldquo;spirituality&amp;rdquo; are &lt;em>not&lt;/em> to be interpreted as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Truth-apt">truth-apt&lt;/a>, even in the limited context of subjective experience. In other words I&amp;rsquo;m not making &lt;em>any&lt;/em> truth claims. But I also want to clarify that I&amp;rsquo;m not writing &lt;em>mere&lt;/em> &amp;ldquo;poetry&amp;rdquo; either. What I am trying to do is offer a body of text, which is artistic in nature, that &lt;em>corresponds&lt;/em> to a real subjective experience had by myself or someone else.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you read &lt;a href="https://headless.org/experiments/">the experiments on headless.org&lt;/a> that I have referred to in the past, my spiritual writing going forward will be &lt;em>similar&lt;/em> to that writing style. It&amp;rsquo;s the same sort of writing. However the reason I want to avoid making truth-apt claims is that we all have &lt;em>different&lt;/em> subjective experiences. &lt;em>&lt;strong>The final authority on your experience is you.&lt;/strong>&lt;/em> If your subjective experience contradicts my writing, your subjective experience should take precedence. My inner world is almost certainly different than yours and I&amp;rsquo;m not trying to impose by saying you &lt;em>must&lt;/em> relate to a specific myth or &lt;a href="https://headless.org/poetry-home.htm">poem&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://headless.org/experiments">experiment&lt;/a> that I find compelling.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The reason I share that myth or poem or experiment is because &lt;em>I&lt;/em> found it compelling or at least I saw how others &lt;em>could&lt;/em> find it compelling in their spiritual journey. Your experience may be completely different and that&amp;rsquo;s absolutely fine. It&amp;rsquo;s to be expected because we&amp;rsquo;re dealing in &lt;em>subjectivity&lt;/em>, not &lt;em>objectivity&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As for my past posts on spirituality, you should interpret them in the same way. Think of my spiritual posts as doors to experiences. Some doors are locked. You&amp;rsquo;re forever barred from what lies behind them. Those experiences are simply not in the cards for you. Other doors require a key. It&amp;rsquo;s possible to find out what&amp;rsquo;s behind those doors, but it takes some effort. Other doors are missing doorknobs. They might already be cracked open or you might open them by accident. It&amp;rsquo;s perfectly fine to be drawn toward certain doors and not others. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you can&amp;rsquo;t make missteps on your spiritual journey. It just means my journey isn&amp;rsquo;t identical to yours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In summary, read the spiritual texts you find most compelling by all means but give your own conscious experience precendence over &lt;em>any&lt;/em> text. I&amp;rsquo;m not trying to make objective truth claims about reality or present a theory in the typical sense of the word. My spiritual writing is expressly written with the hope that you relate to it in your inner world or are entertained by it. In the best case it even helps to further your spiritual life journey. That&amp;rsquo;s all I&amp;rsquo;m trying to do with these posts. Nothing more.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ll link to this section in future spirituality posts where it&amp;rsquo;s applicable so there&amp;rsquo;s no confusion on how to interpret my writing.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Eternal Here and Now</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/the-eternal-here-and-now/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/the-eternal-here-and-now/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="mental-exercise">Mental Exercise&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I want to start this post with a few mental exercises. You&amp;rsquo;ll do them first, then I&amp;rsquo;ll try to explain their purpose.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imagine yourself, in first person, at a place you would like to be. If you like the beach, then imagine yourself at the beach. It&amp;rsquo;s not really important where, just that you can clearly picture it in your mind. Once you have an image in your mind, try to incorporate your other senses as well. If you&amp;rsquo;re picturing a beach, then imagine the sensation of the sand beneath your feet and in between your toes. You can also try the sensation of the wind blowing. If you succeed in that, then add in the sound of seagulls squawking. You can incorporate as many new features into your world as you want. Then when you finish, continue reading.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While you were imagining whatever place you picked, where were you? Where was the place you were imagining? As you incorporated more features into your imagination, where did those new features come from? Where did they go after you finished the exercise?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Time for the second exercise. Stand up if you aren&amp;rsquo;t already. Take 2 steps forward. Where is the first step you took? Take another step. Recall the last step you just took. Where is it now? When is it? Where and when is it while you&amp;rsquo;re remembering it? You can sit back down now.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The third exercise involves paying close attention. Focus your attention on the sensation of breathing. Take a few breaths in and out, just focusing on breathing. If a thought comes careening into consciousness and it interrupts, that&amp;rsquo;s fine. Just observe it the same way you observe your breathing. Expand your awareness as wide as it can go to other sensations in the body such as tension, tiredness, or restlessness. Don&amp;rsquo;t limit yourself to bodily sensations. Emotions of happiness, enjoyment, sadness, anger, disgust and anything without a noun attached to it is also permitted. Nothing that enters consciousness can be &lt;em>invalid&lt;/em>. It&amp;rsquo;s all valid and it&amp;rsquo;s all acknowledged. Just observe as much of it as you can. After you finish, continue reading.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now that you&amp;rsquo;ve completed the third exercise, here are some questions. Where were the sensations you noticed? If you noticed any thoughts during the exercise, where were those thoughts? Were they the same place as the sensations or a different place? Since I&amp;rsquo;m asking about them, you may be &lt;em>recalling&lt;/em> the thoughts and sensations. Where and when is your recollection of your thoughts and sensations?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For more exercises, you can visit &lt;a href="https://www.headless.org/experiments-home.htm">headless.org&lt;/a>. I&amp;rsquo;d highly recommend checking out the site. The experiments found there are clever. Different techniques work better for different people. You might find a technique which works better for you than the exercises I&amp;rsquo;ve written.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="whats-the-point">What&amp;rsquo;s the Point?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>By now I think I&amp;rsquo;ve exhausted my allowance of strange sounding questions directed at the reader. For readers that don&amp;rsquo;t get the idea yet, I&amp;rsquo;m going to come out and say it. All these exercises are trying to get you to experience one thing: The only time and place is here and now. In objective reality, there are separate places and times. Events &amp;ldquo;happen&amp;rdquo; here, or there. They happen in the past, present or future. To say everything happens at the same time and place seems like gibberish. Who would say such a thing? The catch is, it&amp;rsquo;s meant in a very specific sense. I&amp;rsquo;m not denying that there&amp;rsquo;s a real world that persists independently of our experience. Trees that fall down in the forest do make a sound even if no one is there to hear it. I&amp;rsquo;m merely pointing out that to experience something is synonymous with it appearing in consciousness. Consciousness is the only place for anything to appear. Past events are just memories recalled in the present. Future possibilities are imagined in the present. The reality of our experience is always now. We all live in an Eternal Here and Now.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The Darth Vader of responses to this is &amp;ldquo;So what? What does it matter?&amp;rdquo;. It can be really hard to show someone why this matters if they don&amp;rsquo;t already see significance. There could be practical benefits to this kind of realization but the primary one is no longer being confused about what you are any more, and no longer suffering for it. People in the midst of this realization sometimes have a peculiar way of phrasing things. Instead of saying &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m happy&amp;rdquo;, they say &amp;ldquo;There is happiness&amp;rdquo; as in &amp;ldquo;Happiness is present in consciousness&amp;rdquo;. &lt;em>You&lt;/em> are never really happy, but &lt;em>there is&lt;/em> happiness sometimes. Our usual way of talking is with subject-object form. But the sensation of being a subject in relation to a separate, external world of objects is itself a sensation appearing in consciousness. &amp;ldquo;There is a sensation of I&amp;rdquo;. As a side note, none of this entails that it&amp;rsquo;s not useful or important to have a sense of personal identity. A sense of identity is socially necessary. The contrapositive of that is that in order to lose your sense of &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo;, it&amp;rsquo;s useful to undergo social isolation as many monks do.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="am-i-just-an-observer">Am I just an Observer?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>You might wonder after reading all this if you&amp;rsquo;re just some passive observer to this flow of experience. I&amp;rsquo;ve written at length about this before, but it&amp;rsquo;s certain that &lt;a href="../../free-will-is-incoherent-part-1">you don&amp;rsquo;t have free will&lt;/a>. It&amp;rsquo;s possible through meditation and other means to notice this firsthand. While it&amp;rsquo;s possible to &lt;em>feel&lt;/em> either way about it, that you are doing things or that things are happening to you, we know neuroanatomically that the feeling of being the author of your actions, that you are doing things, has to be an illusion. There&amp;rsquo;s nowhere for the author to be hiding. There are only actions. And in that sense &lt;a href="../../free-will-is-incoherent-part-2">you aren&amp;rsquo;t ultimately responsible for your actions&lt;/a>, at least not in a way that justifies punishment for the sake of it. It&amp;rsquo;s just because of the way language is that we have to talk about a &amp;ldquo;do-er&amp;rdquo; and an &amp;ldquo;action&amp;rdquo; as if you could ever really separate the two.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s no satisfying way I can answer the question directly because the question assumes it makes sense to talk about an observer separately from that which is being observed. My suggestion is that dualistic distinctions about the subjective nature of reality are arbitrary. In subjective reality, there is only a &amp;ldquo;happening&amp;rdquo;. Consciousness is just the word we use for the space that we imagine the happening taking place in. We imagine that experiences must occur in some place at some time, so we call that place consciousness. The phrase &amp;ldquo;consciousness and its contents&amp;rdquo; shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be understood to indicate dualism I think. It&amp;rsquo;s just a way of talking. &amp;ldquo;Consciousness and its contents&amp;rdquo; gets across the idea that experience is ever-changing. Everything is transitory because the contents are always changing. And the phrase &amp;ldquo;a happening&amp;rdquo; standing on its own better communicates the idea that experience is non-dual, that there is no experiencer in addition to the experience.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One possible answer to the question &amp;ldquo;Am I just an observer of experience?&amp;rdquo; is that the question is incoherent. But perhaps the best response is &amp;ldquo;Who&amp;rsquo;s asking?&amp;rdquo;. In truth, it&amp;rsquo;s far more rich to directly experience no-self, The Eternal Here and Now, rather than trying to nail down answers to philosophical questions about subjectivity. When it comes to non-dual experience, words fail us because they differentiate. There&amp;rsquo;s no substitute for direct experience, so go try some more &lt;a href="https://www.headless.org/experiments-home.htm">exercises&lt;/a> and see what you find.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ego Traps</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/ego-traps/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/ego-traps/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-ego">The Ego&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Before I get into ego traps, I need to explain what the ego is. I made a post previously about &lt;a href="../../the-self">the self&lt;/a>. But, for this post, I&amp;rsquo;m going to give a simple definition. Ego is the sensation of &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo;. Ego is &lt;em>your idea&lt;/em> of yourself. When asked to describe yourself, the ego is what you&amp;rsquo;re describing. The ego is your &amp;ldquo;persona&amp;rdquo; that you display not only to others, but that you yourself believe. It&amp;rsquo;s incomplete. This has to be true because consciousness can never be an object of itself.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Notice that I don&amp;rsquo;t say it&amp;rsquo;s inaccurate, just incomplete. You can never know exactly who you are. This is because, as far as we know, systems can&amp;rsquo;t simulate themselves. It always leads to infinite regression. Let&amp;rsquo;s use a computer system as a thought experiment.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="thought-experiment">Thought Experiment&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s say we want to build a computer system which perfectly simulates the universe. I mean the exact state and location of every atom, every gravitational wave, etc. We won&amp;rsquo;t concern ourselves about practicalities like speed, power draw, the limits of physics, or how it gets the initial state of the universe. We are going to ignore quantum randomness and locality issues like quantum entanglement. I&amp;rsquo;m sure there are other quirks of physics I don&amp;rsquo;t know about, but we are going to ignore all of those and assume the universe is far more Newtonian than it is. The point of this experiment doesn&amp;rsquo;t depend on the actual universe being Newtonian. It&amp;rsquo;s just to demonstrate a point.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our computer system will be located on earth. Picture an imaginary sphere around our galaxy. Outside of this sphere is what our computer simulates. It ignores the inside. The simulation gets inaccurate over time because the part which it isn&amp;rsquo;t simulating (our galaxy) propogates light out at the speed of light away from us, affecting the simulation. But, since we are good system designers, we account for this. We program it so that the imaginary sphere automatically expands at the speed of light (the fastest information can travel in our universe). This means that the system does not try to simulate the slowly, ever-expanding sphere (our galaxy) in which it resides. We now have a perfectly accurate simulation of the universe, minus a relatively small expanding sphere.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is working fine, so let&amp;rsquo;s upgrade the system. Now, it simulates the whole universe minus earth. We use the same solution as before, making an expanding sphere around the earth which it ignores. It will only take 8 minutes until that sphere touches the sun and we can no longer simulate the sun. Soon enough, we won&amp;rsquo;t be able to simulate the solar system either, and it just gets worse from there. So, we upgrade the system again. Now, it simulates a sphere outside the building in which it sits. In no time flat, we already can&amp;rsquo;t simulate the earth any more.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How small can we shrink this sphere? The smallest we can make it is if our initial non-simulated volume is coterminous with the outline of our computer system. Perhaps we can even shrink it smaller if our system is very large and some parts don&amp;rsquo;t come online immediately. But we can never create a perfect simulation with this strategy because we can&amp;rsquo;t shrink the non-simulated area to zero. If we try to simulate the inside of our imaginary volume, then we get an infinite regression. If a system simulates itself, then it has to simulate the simulation of itself. And so on to infinity. Maybe this is somehow possible, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem so.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="returning-to-the-ego">Returning to the Ego&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The brain is a kind of computer. Like the system described in the thought experiment above, the brain also has a model of itself. Some people know themselves very well and their model is very good, others seem to have no self-awareness at all. But no one can have a complete model of who they are. Therefore, you always have a mysterious element to yourself. I wanted to use a thought experiment to make the problem clear, but Alan Watts explained this idea in terms of a set of simpler analogies which advocate the same idea:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;Trying to define yourself is like trying to bite your own teeth&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br>
&amp;ldquo;You cannot touch the tip of this finger with the tip of this finger&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m using the term &amp;ldquo;model of oneself&amp;rdquo; very loosely. Obviously we don&amp;rsquo;t have to simulate all our neurons to know things about ourselves. There are other meaningful mental representations that we use to understand ourselves, such as the labels others give us. Yogis that spend years in caves can be compared to a system where the &amp;ldquo;sphere&amp;rdquo; of unawareness is kept very small. Yogis are some of the most self-aware members of our species in a manner of speaking. And humans are already the most self-aware species on earth. At the other end of the spectrum you have orangutans, chimps and gorillas. Some can pass the &amp;ldquo;mirror test&amp;rdquo;, the ability to recognize themselves in a mirror. They are less self-aware, but the capacity is still there.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="ego-traps">Ego Traps&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Assuming a high level of awareness is desirable, and I believe it is for almost everyone, there are some things to watch out for. They are called &amp;ldquo;ego traps&amp;rdquo;. What they do is they take you from an aware and alert state of consciousness in touch with reality to one that is spellbound by thoughts, hardly perceiving the world around you. Perhaps only perceiving it enough not to bump into things. One thought after another, oftentimes negative and unproductive, with no ability to stop their steady flow. Ego traps are the &amp;ldquo;gateway thoughts&amp;rdquo; that get you started in this insane state of mind.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The ego traps which everyone talks about are thoughts in the form of words. That&amp;rsquo;s because words are all language allows us to use and everything else is simply referenced by the words. But keep in mind anything that is in consciousness can be an ego trap. The nature of each person&amp;rsquo;s mind is different, so the ego traps they fall for are different. I just want to explicitly list a few common ones because once you get an idea of what you&amp;rsquo;re looking for, it&amp;rsquo;s easier not to be fooled. Here are a few:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Feeling superior or inferior to others.&lt;br>
Thinking you are enlightened.&lt;br>
Wanting to be perfectly safe and secure.&lt;br>
Always desiring happiness.&lt;br>
Thinking there is something missing in your life and chasing after it.&lt;br>
Needing to always be right.&lt;br>
Trying to control how other people act.&lt;br>
Needing the approval of someone else or society.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I want to be clear that I&amp;rsquo;m not saying these desires are wrong to have or that myself and others who write about spirituality never have them. I&amp;rsquo;m saying they are often a gateway into a false sense of identity; your egoic identity. So, to be more aware, watch out for these thoughts. They can often enter in through the back door without you noticing, kicking off a chain reaction of other thoughts which create a grand myth. The ego likes to make up a grand cohesive story about who you are and it hopes you&amp;rsquo;ll buy into it. The more you think about it and feed into its narrative, the more you identify with that story.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>How does this work? It&amp;rsquo;s very simple. All that I have listed basically boils down to a feeling of something being missing in your life. If you pursue the approval of others, then you subconsciously think that you must &lt;strong>need&lt;/strong> the approval of others. The harder you pursue others' approval, the more you feel you must need it. Otherwise, why would you be pursuing it, right? This is the rationalization your mind creates. This isn&amp;rsquo;t to say that every instance of trying to gain someone&amp;rsquo;s approval is bad or you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t try. I&amp;rsquo;m saying be aware of those thoughts. If you want to be aware, don&amp;rsquo;t pursue the approval of others without knowing that&amp;rsquo;s what you&amp;rsquo;re doing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Your sensation of identity takes the form of the thoughts you don&amp;rsquo;t know you&amp;rsquo;re having. The harder you pursue happiness, the more you will feel like you lack it. The more you always need to be right, the more you worry that you&amp;rsquo;re not. The more you want to be safe and secure, the less safe and secure you will feel. It&amp;rsquo;s okay to have desires. The desire to eat and continue living is necessary for survival. Just be aware of desire. Without the awareness, you take on a false sense of identity.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="hide-and-go-seek">Hide and Go Seek&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The fundamental &lt;em>game&lt;/em> of being is like the game of hide and go seek. We hide in the thoughts we don&amp;rsquo;t know we&amp;rsquo;re having. They become who we are. Then one day, something or someone wakes us up and we realize we were playing a game the entire time. This could take 10 seconds or 10 years depending on the person. But, the game goes on several times in a single human life, played out in a different way each time. Just imagine all the ways the game is being played across all of humanity. The game of being a good person and not an evil one. The game of seeking happiness. The game of seeking enlightenment. The game of chasing after something. The game of pretending things are serious, that you&amp;rsquo;re not even playing a game. That&amp;rsquo;s why we find the joker character so fascinating. He plays devil&amp;rsquo;s advocate. While everyone is taking life deadly serious, he dares to treat it like a game. The Christian religion is an absolutely marvelous game. The stakes of the game are eternal bliss versus eternal damnation. Christianity is the version of the game taken to the extreme.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t publish this because I&amp;rsquo;m giving away a secret. I&amp;rsquo;m spoiling your opportunity to find out what it&amp;rsquo;s all about on your own. As Alan Watts says, I&amp;rsquo;ve given the show away. The main idea I want to get across in this post is that if you want to stop playing &amp;ldquo;hide and go seek&amp;rdquo;, if you want to stay found for a while, then you need awareness. And ego traps are the thoughts that pull you out of awareness, so watch out for them.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Doublethink</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/doublethink/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/doublethink/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="quick-note">Quick Note&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>As a quick note, what people post online is often taken as something they will forever agree with and are forever held to. This is unreasonable. There needs to be some equivalent of forgiveness if one posts something horrible online, but that&amp;rsquo;s a topic for another post. I&amp;rsquo;m not saying people aren&amp;rsquo;t responsible for what they post. But I am saying we should aspire to take the most charitable interpretation of what people post if we care about advancing the conversation. Obviously a person&amp;rsquo;s character is a factor in how you interpret what they post.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On my blog, I want to retain the right to post not only ideas that I understand well. But I also want the freedom to talk about things I&amp;rsquo;m not sure about. That means I run the risk of being wrong. No one posting their ideas online openly should expect to be immune to criticism. Criticism comes with the territory. But I want to say I&amp;rsquo;m interested in sharing ideas. If it&amp;rsquo;s clear to me you&amp;rsquo;re only interested in taking my words out of context, twisting what I write or using cheap gotcha&amp;rsquo;s because I didn&amp;rsquo;t state something perfectly, then I probably won&amp;rsquo;t respond. If you want clarification about anything I discuss, visit my &lt;a href="../../about">about page&lt;/a> for contact details. With that cleared up, let&amp;rsquo;s move on to the meat of this post.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="caring-what-others-think">Caring What Others Think&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Most people are going around supremely concerned with what other people think of them. People convince themselves they don&amp;rsquo;t care about what others think, almost as a badge of honor. If someone tells you this, express disbelief as a test. If they insist they don&amp;rsquo;t care, then you might say they care enough about what you think to try to convince you that they don&amp;rsquo;t. If I get any emails from people who insist they don&amp;rsquo;t, I&amp;rsquo;ll probably find it funny because it only serves to further my point. Humans are social animals. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty well baked into all of us to be concerned with what other people think. Our brains have the capacity for theory of mind not by accident. It keeps us all in check so to speak. This is especially true if you&amp;rsquo;re around a lot of people, in a densely populated city like NYC for example. You literally have less room to think without the input of others.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="meeting-expectations">Meeting Expectations&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There is no shortage of outside influences telling us how we ought to think, feel, and behave. In Japan, due to the influence of social conformity, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiger_parenting">tiger parenting&lt;/a> and strict societal expectations to perpetual the status quo, there are over a million &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hikikomori">hikikomoris&lt;/a> in Japan. For those who don&amp;rsquo;t know, a hikikomori is a reclusive person who undergoes self-isolation for extended periods of time. This could be months or years even. There are surely other contributing factors to hikikomoris such as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hikikomori#Psychiatric_disorders">psychiatric disorders&lt;/a>, but I want to focus on social conformity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In an extremely socially conformist culture where differences are not well-tolerated, is it any surprise that young Japanese are rejecting it, opting to live in isolation? Japanese children are often being crushed under the weight of parent&amp;rsquo;s and peer&amp;rsquo;s expectations, especially in education. Some hikikomoris attended &amp;ldquo;cram schools&amp;rdquo;, or juku. Ikuo Amano, professor of Sociology at the University of Tokyo said &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s not healthy for kids to have so little free time. It is not healthy to become completely caught up in competition and status at such a young age&amp;rdquo;. In some cases in cram schools, Japanese children spend almost all their waking hours short of basic biological needs cramming. This is not good for their emotional or physical well-being. It&amp;rsquo;s not allowing enough room for the individual to flourish.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="feeling-the-right-way">Feeling the Right Way&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="mens-feelings">Men&amp;rsquo;s Feelings&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I have to add a disclaimer that not everyone is ready to face their repressed emotions head on. For example, veterans suffering from PTSD should &lt;em>not&lt;/em> try to revisit the bad memories alone. That is where the role of a therapist comes in. They can gently guide you to facing your fears, in a professional setting. This goes for anyone who faces emotional trauma.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how true this is across different cultures, so I&amp;rsquo;ll speak on behalf of my own. There is something very misguided that young men are still taught in the US. I see the situation improving. Younger generations are becoming more aware of this, but it&amp;rsquo;s still a very present part of American culture. There is a taboo against boys and men displaying any negative emotion, except anger or maybe dissatisfaction. Displaying upset, sadness, depression, or anxiety is &amp;ldquo;unmanly&amp;rdquo;. Men talking to each other about their feelings is very taboo in our culture still. We have the phrase &amp;ldquo;man up&amp;rdquo;. Don&amp;rsquo;t you know men don&amp;rsquo;t cry? Men don&amp;rsquo;t complain. Be a man. This is a dangerous thing to impart to young boys because bottled up emotions end up coming out somehow. And better to have emotions coming out through tears than self-destructive habits or violence.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is a huge pressure on men not to display emotions, to outright pretend their emotions don&amp;rsquo;t even exist, and to never talk about their problems. And it would serve us all well to change that extremely toxic part of our culture. There will be men who read and agree, yet &lt;em>&lt;strong>still&lt;/strong>&lt;/em> won&amp;rsquo;t feel comfortable showing emotions because it&amp;rsquo;s ingrained in the culture. You will be judged by other men for showing emotions. You might even lose your &amp;ldquo;man card&amp;rdquo;, respect from other men in the community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is this strange idea given to us by society which is this: If you show your emotions, if you cry, if you get upset and display it, then you aren&amp;rsquo;t in control. You don&amp;rsquo;t have a lid on it. This is completely backwards. In fact, the &lt;em>only&lt;/em> way to manage so called negative feelings is to not push them away. It&amp;rsquo;s to allow yourself to feel them. By pushing negative emotions away, you push away a part of yourself. I&amp;rsquo;m not saying one should dwell on negative events in one&amp;rsquo;s life. But if they keep coming up in your mind, don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily push them away. If you distract yourself from them, you might succeed temporarily in not dealing with how you feel. But if you always do that and never face yourself, it will degrade your mental stability and your quality of life.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="being-happy">Being Happy&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Besides the taboo against men&amp;rsquo;s emotions, there is also a taboo that applies to everyone. It is the taboo against being sad. I have to add another disclaimer here that I&amp;rsquo;m not talking about someone that is severely depressed. People with depression should get professional help. I&amp;rsquo;m not trying to give advice that treats or cures mental illness. I&amp;rsquo;m not saying people shouldn&amp;rsquo;t seek out what makes them happy in life. I&amp;rsquo;m talking about the natural state of every person of being sad sometimes. No one is happy all the time. In my experience, most people are vaguely discontent most of the time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The idea is pushed on people by society that they ought to never be sad or anxious. Cheer up, don&amp;rsquo;t be a negative nancy, don&amp;rsquo;t be a party pooper, don&amp;rsquo;t worry, be happy, don&amp;rsquo;t be mad, and just relax. This is a form of doublethink. It is commanding someone to do something that can&amp;rsquo;t be forced. It&amp;rsquo;s as if you told someone to grow their hair faster, or beat their heart faster. If you pay very close attention, the physical sensations of stress and happiness have a very similar profile. It&amp;rsquo;s not the sensation of sadness itself that&amp;rsquo;s so bad. It&amp;rsquo;s what we think it means, because society has told us that it&amp;rsquo;s not a good thing to be sad. Why not? It&amp;rsquo;s a necessary emotion that healthy people feel sometimes. Why not be content being sad? It&amp;rsquo;s not the sensation of sadness that causes suffering. That&amp;rsquo;s a myth. It&amp;rsquo;s the aversion to sadness that causes the suffering.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is a message that is more often implicitly than explicitly pushed on us. You don&amp;rsquo;t see sad people in advertisements. Everyone is always smiling. If you just buy this product, you&amp;rsquo;ll be as happy as those in the advertisement! Except that never happens. The nature of the mind is to invent a new obstacle as soon as you overcome the current one. In the US, food service workers are expected to produce a fake smile and be overly kind to customers, even if it&amp;rsquo;s not genuine. &amp;ldquo;Service with a smile&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;enjoy your meal&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;Thank you for calling &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;. I tune out when I hear these phrases because I know they&amp;rsquo;re just socially mandated platitudes. It&amp;rsquo;s a very sick thing about our culture that we are always expecting happiness. There needs to be more room to express sadness and discontent. Maybe if there was, we would have less food service workers spitting in people&amp;rsquo;s food.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The lesson here is if you allow yourself to feel how you actually feel, instead of how you&amp;rsquo;ve been told you are supposed to feel, you&amp;rsquo;ll be in a much better position to manage your emotions.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="being-a-good-person">Being a Good Person&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Society teaches us we have to be a good person. Do the right thing. Be kind to others. While being kind to others is useful if you have the same instrumental goals as the vast majority of the human species, that is goals that further other instrumental or ultimate goals, it is not useful for those who don&amp;rsquo;t share those goals. It&amp;rsquo;s just a mantra for them. If you share top goals that are typically associated with being a &lt;em>good&lt;/em> person such as prosperity of the human race and other species and eliminating needless suffering, then you will naturally try to promote &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo;. If deep down, you sincerely don&amp;rsquo;t care about anyone else at all and never will, you may be a psychopath.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Society has taught as that being a psychopath is a very bad thing to be. It has a highly negative connotation. We tend to avoid associating with people we recognize as psychopaths since they are incapable of empathy or remorse. While genuine psychopaths are very rare, many completely neurologically typical people wouldn&amp;rsquo;t like to see others succeed. They have particular people that they don&amp;rsquo;t feel compassion or remorse for, that they hold a grudge against, and they come by that honestly. The families of Ted Bundy&amp;rsquo;s victims probably felt great relief to see him electrocuted to death. This comes from a feeling of wanting revenge, not out of compassion. The compassionate view is that unfortunately someone whose values are incompatible with society ended up causing a lot of suffering. So I feel compassion for my own suffering and compassion for the victims for losing their lives and compassion for the perpetrator who, through being a victim of a chain of causality that wired his brain the way it did through his genes and upbringing, inevitably pushed him into becoming a serial killer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m not saying don&amp;rsquo;t be a &lt;em>good&lt;/em> person. If you really want the best for everyone, then feel free to promote goodness in the world. But if there are people you can&amp;rsquo;t empathize with, that you can&amp;rsquo;t relate to, then don&amp;rsquo;t pretend to. Maybe try talking to them to get their perspective. It is yet another form of doublethink to feel that you &lt;em>must&lt;/em> have compassion for all people. Entertain the idea that disliking people is okay. Maybe it is not a good guide to what you should do in regard to that person, but it&amp;rsquo;s important that you accept your dislike of them, and not force yourself to like them. It&amp;rsquo;s true that one can cultivate compassion for even someone who did horrible things like Ted Bundy or Hitler. But there is no &amp;ldquo;contest&amp;rdquo; of who can be the most compassionate person.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="being-nonjudgemental">Being Nonjudgemental&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There is the idea that you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t judge other people. &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t judge&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Love, not hate&amp;rdquo;. Being judgemental is seen as a bad thing. What I think this means more precisely is not to look down on other people for the way they are or their actions. But this is doublethink at its finest. Because in the command &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t judge&amp;rdquo;, there is an assumption that judging is not a good thing to do. So if you believe in not judging others, then you cannot judge the judgemental either.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Another reason this idea of not judging doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense is that you can&amp;rsquo;t not judge others. It&amp;rsquo;s not voluntary in any sense. It is not always appropriate to vocalize your judgement, but you cannot stop yourself from judging. It&amp;rsquo;s easy for me to point out someone like Kim Jong Un that everyone judges to be a bad human being. But you may meet someone with Tourette Syndrome and think to yourself, &amp;ldquo;Wow, their verbal tics are really annoying. Why can&amp;rsquo;t they shut up&amp;rdquo;? And next you think &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m not &lt;em>supposed&lt;/em> to feel that way. I know they can&amp;rsquo;t help it. What&amp;rsquo;s wrong with me&amp;rdquo;? This encapsulates the essence of doublethink. You feel like you&amp;rsquo;re not &lt;em>allowed&lt;/em> to find it annoying because the disabled can&amp;rsquo;t help it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="first-hand-story">First-Hand Story&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>So far, this post has been very philosophical. So, I want to add in a personal story for concreteness. I once overheard a conversation between a student and a professor in his office. She was studying accounting. And she was absolutely struggling with it. She ended up audibly upset and crying about it. She didn&amp;rsquo;t want to disappoint her parents by doing something else. I don&amp;rsquo;t know how far along she was in her degree, but that gave me the impression that she already invested some effort into it. She hated accounting, but felt like that&amp;rsquo;s what she had to do because of family pressure. This is a very common thing in my experience. Many students study &lt;em>just&lt;/em> to avoid disappointing family, their main motivation not really being to learn. In her case though, it seemed like she just didn&amp;rsquo;t like accounting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The professor gave her some really good advice. He told her that she doesn&amp;rsquo;t want to be doing something she doesn&amp;rsquo;t like to do for decades. And that she should consider what she really wants, instead of what other people have told her she should do. She listened intently and took his advice. If I remember correctly she ended up changing majors, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t know her personally so I&amp;rsquo;m not certain. That was some very solid advice he gave her though.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="death">Death&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>I have to add yet another important disclaimer. I worry that some readers could take this section the wrong way and I really don&amp;rsquo;t want that to happen. If you are suicidal, seek out professional help. I am not in any way condoning or encouraging suicide in this section. This is a purely philosophical discussion about the taboo of death. If someone you know has recently died or is dying, you might consider skipping ahead. If you are not mentally well or have depression, skip this section. It&amp;rsquo;s not worth the risk of reading into it something I didn&amp;rsquo;t intend. It&amp;rsquo;s not necessary for the rest of this post to make sense. If you have any questions, feel free to &lt;a href="mailto:nicholasjohnson@posteo.org">email me&lt;/a>. With that out of the way, I&amp;rsquo;ll continue.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Death is perhaps one of the greatest taboos in our modern society. It is &lt;em>not&lt;/em> something you bring up at the dinner table. People don&amp;rsquo;t like to be reminded that they won&amp;rsquo;t be here some day. There is a lot of anxiety around death. People generally avoid thinking about it. One benefit of believing in Christianity, Judaism, Islam, or Hinduism is that you get an afterlife or a next life. You never really have to die. To me, living for eternity is more terrifying. After a trillion billion years, I think anyone would have had enough. People don&amp;rsquo;t consider how long forever really is.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The fear of death, I believe, is largely taught. Children learn to be afraid of it from their parents, teachers and peers. For example, everyone is supposed to act solemn and sad at funerals. The dead are underground, cremated, or burned. Out of sight and out of mind. As another example, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed people tend to have similar attitudes toward death as their parents and the prevailing culture. One thing that fascinates people about the joker character is that he doesn&amp;rsquo;t take anything seriously. He makes a mockery of even death itself. Ask yourself, why be afraid of death? What is there to fear? Maybe your family needs you. You are afraid of their grief. That&amp;rsquo;s fair. So then I ask, why be afraid of the fear of death? Fear is simply another sensation arising in the body. Are you afraid of the wind blowing against your skin? Then why be afraid of the feeling of fear? Why does it get a special status as opposed to any other feeling that passes by?&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="wu-wei">Wu Wei&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Where am I going with all this? I want to invite every reader to consider something. What would happen if you simply let go of all expectations society has of you? What would happen if you gave no thought to what others think of you? What if you forgot about being a good person, loving and not hating, being happy and not sad? What would happen if you allowed yourself to feel whatever you feel, without judging it? What would happen if you allowed your thoughts, emotions, and sensations to come and go like clouds in the sky without trying to label them? Healthy or unhealthy, good or bad, acceptable or taboo?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-sky">The Sky&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The sky is simply the &lt;em>&lt;strong>space&lt;/strong>&lt;/em> in which the clouds appear and dissapate. The sky does not follow the clouds. The sky does not push the clouds away. The sky simply allows the clouds to come and go. Consciousness is where thoughts, emotions, and sensations appear and dissapate. The sensation of being identified with your thoughts, is itself a sensation arising in consciousness. From an experiential perspective, there is nowhere outside of consciousness.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You might object: &amp;ldquo;You said earlier one cannot resist caring about what others think. So how can I be like the sky if I can&amp;rsquo;t stop judging my thoughts&amp;rdquo;? This is why they call it meditation &lt;em>practice&lt;/em>. Non-attachment takes practice. And mindfulness meditation is one of the most effective ways to achieve that state. It&amp;rsquo;s not always easy to let go, because you have been conditioned your whole life to be passionate and cling. If you can&amp;rsquo;t resist judging your thoughts, then judge them. Just don&amp;rsquo;t judge your judgements of your thoughts. Let your judgements of your thoughts pass like clouds in the sky. So on and so forth. With meditation, your mind will tire of thinking and judging everything all the time. You will become thoughtless. That doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you can&amp;rsquo;t think when you need to. It means you won&amp;rsquo;t be held hostage by the next so called negative thought you have. You can see you true nature, prior to any idea about who society has told you you are supposed to be. It is a state of nonjudgemental, pure awareness. Some people report getting the feeling that their mind is in complete harmony with all that is.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is not a state of mind you can force. It&amp;rsquo;s a state of mind that comes about naturally as you practice meditation. It relates to the Chinese term &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wu_wei">Wu Wei&lt;/a>&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ldquo;Non-action&amp;rdquo; can be seen as not acting upon the contents of consciousness, nor judging them. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you are completely isolated from society. To me, it means not being so involved in society that you lose who you are. Being in a state of mindlessness might sound contrary to intellectualism, but that&amp;rsquo;s a misunderstanding. The opposite is true. It&amp;rsquo;s easier to think when your mind &lt;em>isn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em> getting in the way.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Self</title><link>https://0gitnick.xyz/the-self/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://0gitnick.xyz/the-self/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="language">Language&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Starting at a young age, we pick up language, mainly from our parents. We are very much conditioned to think in certain ways by the language we speak. This is known as the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linguistic_relativity">Sapir-Whorf hypothesis&lt;/a>. What I want to talk about is similar to Sapir-Whorf. It isn&amp;rsquo;t about how particular languages affect one&amp;rsquo;s worldview, but about how any language can create a false image of the world. Language is a tool for getting information from one mind to another. But it&amp;rsquo;s more than that. It is a tool for thinking. One thing that should be taught more in English classes is that writing is useful for crystallizing and refining thoughts, not just communicating them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The problem with any spoken language is that in order to be useful, it has to create abstractions. These abstractions are fuzzy, inexact ways of talking about things. Mathematical language is not fuzzy and imprecise like spoken language is. Mathematical language is symbolic and rigorous. What is written is unambiguous. But this fuzziness of concept is a necessary evil, otherwise natural language would be inefficient and slow and still inexact. The problem isn&amp;rsquo;t language itself. It comes when we treat language as reality, when we forget we are dealing with these inexact fuzzy abstractions which are nouns, pronouns, adjectives, verbs, etc. A lot of the words in spoken language are fuzzy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is something that I have always found intuitive but is an easy mistake to make in philosophy. I would argue that a rather large fraction of academic papers about philosophy aren&amp;rsquo;t actually creating an interesting argument or bringing any substance to the table. Academics are simply bickering about how words should be used without even realizing it. For example, look at &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ship_of_Theseus">the Ship of Theseus&lt;/a>. The essential question it poses is this: &amp;ldquo;Is an object the same object if all its component parts are replaced over time?&amp;rdquo;. I agree with Noam Chomsky that this is a cognitive issue manufactured by humans because we get really bent out of shape if we don&amp;rsquo;t know what to label something. We have to have a label. So what we do we call something if all its parts are replaced? Do we call it something else or do we call it the same thing? Now the problem becomes more clear. It&amp;rsquo;s a question about language.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The right question is &amp;ldquo;If an object&amp;rsquo;s parts are replaced, should we still call it the same object?&amp;rdquo;. We could make a pros and cons list of calling it the same object versus giving it a different name and decide what makes more sense. One might think I&amp;rsquo;m being being pedantic about this and philosophers understand the real question is about what we call the object. My own personal experience has shown that this is not true. People often do not understand that they&amp;rsquo;re arguing about what to call something, and it&amp;rsquo;s not any deeper than that. This is called &lt;a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Mistaking_the_map_for_the_territory">Mistaking the Map for the Territory&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But we have also created another problem. What is an object? Let&amp;rsquo;s take a car for example. Let&amp;rsquo;s say we haven&amp;rsquo;t replaced any parts. Where does the car stop and the car&amp;rsquo;s environment begin? Is the air inside the car also the car? What if the car is in orbit around the earth and it has no air, is the space inside the car still the car, or is it just empty space? This questioning is ridiculous in one sense because when I say the word &amp;ldquo;car&amp;rdquo;, every English speaker intuitively knows what the word &amp;ldquo;car&amp;rdquo; means. For all practical usages of the word &amp;ldquo;car&amp;rdquo; we will never have to worry about bizarre philosophical quandries about the identity of the car (especially since there&amp;rsquo;s no &amp;ldquo;Car of Theseus&amp;rdquo;). We all just sort of know what other people talk about when they talk about a &amp;ldquo;car&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="opposites">Opposites&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Everything implies its opposite or negation. I don&amp;rsquo;t mean this in a logical sense. I mean it as a matter of language. The word &amp;ldquo;black&amp;rdquo; implies that there are words for other colors. It implies &amp;ldquo;not black&amp;rdquo; colors because otherwise we wouldn&amp;rsquo;t need the word black. Left implies right. Up implies down. Forward implies backward. Here implies there. Car implies &amp;ldquo;not car&amp;rdquo; or environment for a better term. Just by using the word &amp;ldquo;car&amp;rdquo; we imply that there exists (in language, not literally exists in space) an environment which at least is defined as not being the car. The car is not its environment. This can be applied to any object. It also applies to adjectives and other features of language. Colorful implies colorless. Dumb implies smart. Yin-yang. It words for verbs as well. Running implies walking or crawling or not running. A pair of opposites that depend on one another. They cannot exist (conceptually) separately. So if they can&amp;rsquo;t exist separately, why call them opposites?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s possible to see things from another point of view. What if instead of treating what we call a &amp;ldquo;car&amp;rdquo; as a separate idea from the environment of the car, we treat the car and the environment as one whole system. It could be called the &amp;ldquo;car-environment&amp;rdquo;. We are not accustomed to thinking of objects in these terms, primarily because we are conditioned to think using language that pretends that our distinction of what is a car and what is its environment is a real distinction made by the universe itself, not a somewhat arbitrary distinction as a product of evolved language. This is why we forget that voice in our head that we hear when reading this sentence is not us. So what about the word I? Where is the self that answers to the word &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo;, that is yourself?&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="the-self">The Self&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>As a matter of language, the word &amp;ldquo;self&amp;rdquo; implies the word &amp;ldquo;other&amp;rdquo;. Other than self. Not self. Are you you&amp;rsquo;re brain? Where do the boundaries of &amp;ldquo;you&amp;rdquo; begin and end exactly? Where do &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo; go when I sleep? The right question to ask is &amp;ldquo;What definition should the word I have?&amp;rdquo;. But we must remember that &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo; is just a word, a concept. The concept of &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo; is no more you than the concept of a &amp;ldquo;car&amp;rdquo; is an actual car. No matter how far you zoom in to a continuous function, you won&amp;rsquo;t see the discrete points that make it up. Eventually you get the idea of continuity. The self is similar. The more you zoom in to what you are calling &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo;, the less it makes sense to separate &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo; from the rest of the cosmos. You are continuous with everything that is. You are one with the unfolding process that is this cosmos. You are not physically separate from it, despite the pesky word &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo; that would have you think otherwise.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Meditation is a practice that can help you experience this oneness, but it takes practice. Specifically, mindfulness meditation is a good place to start. Instead of &amp;ldquo;zooming in&amp;rdquo;, I often use the phrase &amp;ldquo;getting behind oneself&amp;rdquo;. For instance, you are reading this sentence and suddenly a thought pops into your head &amp;ldquo;What should I make for dinner tonight?&amp;rdquo;. Let&amp;rsquo;s say the thought pops up exactly like that, in a bit of language. And then it passes and you keep reading. Where did that thought come from and where did it go? Did you generate that thought or did it just pop up? If you pay close enough attention, you can see how thoughts, moods, and sensations come and go without you &amp;ldquo;doing&amp;rdquo; anything. One might call this level one of getting behind yourself. When you have an angry thought, you are no longer entranced by it. You are the self that notices the angry thought or the physiological change that comes with resurrecting that thought. You are no longer your thoughts. You are behind them, listening as a passive observer as if they are someone else&amp;rsquo;s thoughts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Getting behind yourself a second time could mean that you notice the observer of your thoughts. To recap, level one is observing your thoughts and sensations. You are not behind your eyes, in your head as a matter of experience. You are the self that notices the feeling of having a head, the feeling of being behind your eyes, but you are not in your head behind your eyes. You are the noticer. Level two means that you notice the self that notices the feeling of having a head. What the ultimate goal here is, is trying to find the self that is doing the searching. You are trying to pay attention to your attention itself. I can call this level one and level two for clarity, but I think it&amp;rsquo;s more of a continuous spectrum of awareness without clearly defined &amp;ldquo;levels&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Think about a dog chasing its own tail. Puppies might not realize that what they&amp;rsquo;re chasing is their own tail. But once they catch it and bite down, they know. Perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s better explained as a game of hide and go seek. You forget who you really are as you grow up. Others give you a name and assign adjectives to you as if that&amp;rsquo;s who you really are. You are told you are John, the clever thirty year old quirky accomplished artist and you better not think you&amp;rsquo;re anything else. To use the words of Alan Watts, you are an isolated ego inside a &amp;ldquo;bag of skin&amp;rdquo;. Life is like playing a game of hide and go seek where you are both the one hiding and the one seeking. And meditation is a technique for looking in the mirror and finding out the hider and seeker are the same person. Except the seeker goes by the name of &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo; and the one hiding goes by the name of &amp;ldquo;the environment&amp;rdquo;. And when I say &amp;ldquo;the environment&amp;rdquo;, I don&amp;rsquo;t mean just the physical environment. I mean the thoughts inside your head including the feeling of having a head.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conceptual-understanding-of-self-versus-experience">Conceptual Understanding of Self Versus Experience&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If you get what I&amp;rsquo;m saying about the self so far, that&amp;rsquo;s great. You have a conceptual understanding of it. But to only have a conceptual understanding is to miss the point. It&amp;rsquo;s like if a person were blind from birth. They can learn every fact there is to know about color. They can learn the cultural significance. For example, in American culture, blue means calmness and security. Black means darkness. Purple represents mystery. The blind person can learn the wavelengths that produce every color. They can know what colors go well together and what art styles are used with what color. But they have never actually seen color. So we would still say they lack perhaps the most important thing there is to know about color. The experience. The experience of color can&amp;rsquo;t be replaced by knowing facts about it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An understanding of the self is precisely the same. You might understand everything you&amp;rsquo;ve read in this post so far, but you may have never looked within. This makes you like the blind man who knows all the facts about color, but has never seen it. Experiencing the loss of one&amp;rsquo;s ego can be described in words, but you&amp;rsquo;ll never get across in words the most important aspect, the experience, of the disillusionment one&amp;rsquo;s ego. It&amp;rsquo;s much richer to be the one that has seen color, experienced it, yet knows nothing about it than to be the blind person that knows every color fact. There are yogis and zen masters that are expert meditators but can&amp;rsquo;t articulate their experience outside of religious dogma. I think fewer are those that understand the self but don&amp;rsquo;t have some experience of it, because often accidental life experiences of self create the interest.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is a growing interest in the west around meditation and self which has been understood in the east for over two and a half thousand years. This shows that it&amp;rsquo;s not a matter of knowing more facts. We have gained immense knowledge as a species over the past two and a half thousand years, but for most of us westerners we still have no clue about the self despite our technological advancement. It&amp;rsquo;s just a matter of looking within and regular practice meditating. Turns out there are some places more thinking can&amp;rsquo;t get you and the experience of oneness or &amp;ldquo;inner peace&amp;rdquo; is one of them. This I think is the hardest thing for a western person to digest because in almost every other area of human endeavor we can make progress by thinking. In meditation, the goal is to be thought-less, or at least aware of your thoughts. Awareness is a completely different mode than most of us westerners are used to using our brains. That&amp;rsquo;s another reason some struggle to wrap their mind around it. I can talk to some western people about the self and awareness and it&amp;rsquo;s as if they have no inner life whatsoever and don&amp;rsquo;t understand what I&amp;rsquo;m talking about.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>If you take away anything from this post, understand that knowing facts about self versus experiencing it are orthogonal. If you want to really experience oneness with reality and get with your self, one way to do it is repeated meditation practice. There is no substitute. If you have any interest, just try it. Try different forms of meditation even for five or ten minutes, but start with mindfulness if you&amp;rsquo;re a beginner. And keep practicing even if you don&amp;rsquo;t notice anything the first few times. You really can&amp;rsquo;t fail because it&amp;rsquo;s like dancing. There is no end goal. You just do it for the sake of it. The most important thing is that you are doing it. Meditation doesn&amp;rsquo;t guarantee a profound experience, but I&amp;rsquo;d be surpised if I met someone who meditated properly for one week, an hour per day and found nothing of value.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>